I wanted to start by showing you something
that I'm kind of excited about which is here
is the Dogs vs Cats competiton, which we all
know so well.
It was interesting that the winner of this
competition won by a very big margin.
A 1.1% error, vs a 1.7% error.
This is very unusual in this type of competition
to see anybody win by 50% or 60% margin.
After that, it was generally clustering about
1.7% error, about the same kind of number.
This was a pretty impressive performance.
This is the guy who actually created a piece
of deep-learning software called OverFeat.
I want to show you something pretty interesting
which is this week I tried something new and
on Dogs Vs Cats got 98.95.
So I want to show you how I did that.
The way I did that was by using merely only
techniques I've already showed you which is
basically I created a standard model (which
is basically a dense model) and then I pre-computed
the last convolutional layer and then I trained
the dense model a couple times and the other
thing I did was to use some data augmentation.
I didn't have time to figure out the best
data augmentation parameters, so I just picked
some that seemed reasonable.
I should also mention this 98.95, it would
be easy to make it a lot better.
I'm not doing any pseudo labeling here and
I'm not even using the full dataset; I put
aside 2000 for the validation set.
So with those two changes, we would definitely
get over 99% accuracy.
The missing piece that I added is I added
batch normalization to VGG.
Batch normalization (if you guys remember)
I said the important take-away is that all
modern networks should use batchnorm because
you can get 10X or more improvement in training
speed, and it tends to reduce overfitting.
Because of the second one, you can use less
drop-out, and drop-out is destroying some
of your network, so you don't want to use
more dropout than is necessary.
So why didn't VGG already have batchnorm?
Because it didn't exist.
VGG was kind of mid to late 2014 and batchnorm
was maybe early 2015.
So why haven't people added batchnorm to VGG
already.
And the answer is really interesting to think
about.
To remind you of what batchnorm is - batchnorm
is something which first of all normalizes
every intermediate layer, so it normalizes
all the activations by subtracting the mean
and dividing by the standard deviation, which
is always a good idea.
I know somebody on the forum today asked why
it is a good idea, and I put a link to some
more information about that.
So anybody who wants to know more about why
do normalization, check out the forum.
But just doing that alone isn't enough because
SGD is quite bloody-minded, so if it was trying
to denormalize the activations because it
thought that was a good thing to do, it would
do so anyway, so every time you tried to normalize
them, SGD would just undo it again.
So what batchnorm does is it adds two additional
trainable parameters to each layer, one which
multiplies the activations, and one which
is added to the activations.
So it basically allows it to undo the normalization,
but not by changing every single weight, but
by just changing two weights for each activation.
So it makes things much more stable in practice.
So you can't just go ahead and stick batchnorm
in to a pre-trained network because if you
do, it's going to take that layer and divide
all the incoming activation layers, subtract
the mean and divide by the standard deviation.
Which means now those pre-trained weights
from then on, and they're wrong.
Because those weights were created for a completely
different set of activations.
[Time: 5 minute mark]
So, it's not rocket science.
But I realized that all we need to do is to
insert a batchnorm layer and figure out what
the mean and standard deviations of the incoming
activations would be for that dataset and
basically create the batchnorm layer such
that the two trainable parameters immediately
undo that.
Because that way we could insert a batchnorm
layer and it would not change the outputs
at all.
So I grabbed the whole ImageNet, and I created
our standard dense layer model.
I pre-computed the convolutional outputs for
all of ImageNet and then I created 2 batchnorm
layers, and I created a little function which
allows us to insert a layer into an existing
model (inset_layer).
So I inserted the layers just after the two
dense layers.
And then here is the key piece, I set the
weights on the new batchnorm layers equal
to the variance and the mean, which I calculated
on all of ImageNet.
So I calculated the mean of each of those
two layer outputs and the variance of each
of those two layer outputs.
So that allowed me to insert these batchnorm
layers into the existing model.
Then afterwards I evaluated it and I checked
that indeed it's giving me the same answers
as it was before.
As well as doing that, I then kind of thought
that if you train a model with batchnorm from
the start, you're going to end up with weights
which are going to take advantage of the fact
that the activations are being normalized.
So I wondered what would happen if we now
fine-tuned the ImageNet network on all of
ImageNet after we added these batchnorm layers.
So I then tried training it for one epoch
on both the ImageNet images and the horizontally-fit
ImageNet images (that's what these 2.5 million
here are).
As you can see, with modern GPUs and with
pre-computed convolutional layers it takes
less than an hour to run the entirety of ImageNet
twice.
And the interesting thing was that my accuracy
on the validation set went up from 63% to
67%.
So adding batchnorm actually improves ImageNet,
which is cool.
That wasn't the main reason I did it, the
main reason I did it was that we can now use
VGG with batchnorm in our models.
So I did all that, I saved the weights, I
then edited our VGG model.
If we now look at fully-connected block in
our VGG model, it now
has batchnorm in there, and I also saved to
our website a new weights file, called vgg16_bn
(for batchnorm), so then when I did Cats vs
Dogs, I used that model.
So now if you go and re-download from platform.ai
the vgg16_py it will automatically download
the new weights; you will have this without
any changes to your code.
I'll be interested to hear if during the week
if you try this out (just rerun the code you've
got) whether you see improvements (and hopefully
you will).
Hopefully you'll find it trains more quickly
and you get better results.
At this stage, I've only added batchnorm to
the dense layers, not to the convolutional
layers.
There's no reason I shouldn't add it to the
convolutional layers as well.
Since most of us are mainly fine-tuning just
the dense layers, this is going to impact
most of us the most anyway.
So that's an exciting step which everybody
can now use.
The other thing to mention is now that you'll
be using batchnorm by default in your vgg
networks, you should find that you can increase
your learning rates.
Because batchnorm normalizes the activations,
it makes sure that there's no activation that's
gone really high or really low, and that means
that generally speaking you can use higher
learning rates.
If you try higher learning rates in your code
than you used before, you should find that
they work really well.
You should also find that things that previously
you couldn't get to train, now will start
to train, because often the reason they don't
train is that one of the activations shoots
off into really high or really low and screws
everything up and that kind of gets fixed
when you use batchnorm.
So there's some things to try this week.
I'll be interested to hear how you go.
[Time: 10 minute mark]
So, last week we looked at collaborative filtering.
To remind you, we had a file that basically
meant something like this - we had a bunch
of movies and a bunch of users and for some
subset of those combinations we had a review
of that movie by that user.
The way the actual file came to us it didn't
look like this, this is a cross-tab.
The way the file came to us it looked like
this - each row with a single user with a
single rating at a single time.
So I showed you in Excel how we could take
the crosstab version and we could create a
table of dot products, where the dot products
would be between a set of 5 random numbers
for the movie and 5 random numbers for the
user, and that we could then use gradient
descent to optimize those sets of 5 random
numbers for every user and every movie, and
if we did so, we end up getting pretty decent
guesses as to the original ratings.
Then we went a step further in the spreadsheet
and we learned how you could take the dot
product and you could also add on a single
bias, a movie bias and a user bias.
So we saw all that in Excel and we also learned
that Excel comes with a gradient-descent solver,
called Solver.
We saw that if we ran Solver telling it that
these are our varying cells and that this
is our target cell, then it came up with some
pretty decent weight matrices.
We learned that these kind of weight matrices
are called embeddings.
An embedding is basically something where
we can start with an integer, like 27, and
look up movie #27's vector of weights, that's
called an embedding.
There is also, in collaborative filtering,
this particular type of embedding known as
latent factors.
We hypothesized that, once trained, each of
these latent factors may mean something.
I said next week we might come back, have
a look and see if we can figure out what they
mean.
So that was what I thought I would do now.
So, I'm going to take the bias model we created
- the bias model we created was the one where
we took a user embedding and a movie embedding,
and we took the dot product of the two, and
then we added to it a user bias and a movie
bias, where those biases are just embeddings
which have a single output.
Just like in Excel, the bias was a single
cell for each movie and a single cell for
each user.
So then we tried fitting that model, and you
might remember we ended up getting an accuracy
that was quite a bit higher than previous
state-of-the-art.
Actually, for that one we didn't -- the previous
state-of-the-art we broke by using a neural
network.
I discovered something interesting during
the week, which is I can get a state-of-the-art
result using just this simple bias model,
and the trick was that I just had to increase
my regularization.
We haven't talked too much about regularization,
we've briefly mentioned it a couple of times
but it's a very simple thing where we can
basically say add to the loss function the
sum-of-the-squares of the weights.
We're trying to minimize the loss, so if you're
adding the sum of the squares of the weights
to the loss function, then the SGD solver
is going to have to try avoid increasing the
weights where it can.
So we can pass to most Keras layers a parameter
called W_regularizer (that stands for weight
regularizer) and we can tell it how to regularize
our weights.
In this case I tell it to use a l2 norm (that
means sum-of-the-squares), and how much, in
this case I used 1e-4.
It turns out that if I do that and I train
it for a while (it takes quite a lot longer
to train), I got down to a loss of .7979,
which is quite a bit better than the best
results that that Stanford paper showed.
[Time: 15 minute mark]
It's not quite as good as the neural net,
the neural net got .7938 at best.
But it's still interesting that this very
simple approach actually gets results better
than the academic state-of-the-art as of 2012
or 2013, and I haven't been able to find more
recent academic benchmarks than that.
So I took this model and I wanted to find
out what we can learn from these results.
Obviously one thing we would do with this
model is just to make predictions with it.
So if you are building a website for recommending
movies, and a new user came along and said,
"I like these movies this much, what else
would you recommend?", you could just go through
and do a prediction for each movie for each
userId and tell them which ones had the highest
number.
That's the normal way we use collaborative
filtering.
We can do some other things, we can grab the
top 2,000 most popular movies (just to make
this more interesting) and we can say let's
just grab the bias term.
I'll talk more about this particular syntax
in a moment, but just for now this is a particularly
simple kind of model.
It's a model which simply takes the movieId
in and returns the movie bias out.
It does a look-up in the movie bias table
and returns the movie bias indexed by this
movieId.
That's what these two lines do [get_movie_bias
= Model(movie_in, mb); movie_bias = get_movie_bias.predict(topMovies)].
I then combine this bias with the actual name
of the rating and print out the top and bottom
15.
So, according to MovieLens, the worst movie
of all time is the Church of Scientology classic,
Battlefield Earth, sorry John Travolta.
This is interesting because these ratings
are quite a lot more sophisticated than your
average movie rating.
What this is saying is these have been normalized
-- some reviewers are more positive than negative
than others, some people are watching better
or krappier films than others, so this bias
is removing all that noise, and really telling
us that after removing all that noise, these
are the least good movies.
And Battlefield Earth (-.2616) is even worse
than Spice World (-.1390) by a significant
margin.
On the other hand, here are the best.
Miyazaki fans would be pleased to see Howl's
Moving Castle at #2.
So that's interesting.
Perhaps what's more interesting though
is to try and figure out what's going on,
not in the biases but in the latent factors.
The latent factors are a little bit harder
to interpret because for every movie we have
50 of them.
In the Excel spreadsheet we have 5.
In our version, we have 50 of them.
So what we want to do is we want to take from
those 50 latent factors, we want to find two
or three kind of main components.
The way we do this (the details aren't important,
but a lot of you will already be familiar
with it) which is that there's something called
PCA, Principal Components Analysis.
Principal Components Analysis does exactly
what I just said -- it looks through a matrix
(in this case its got 50 columns) and it says,
what are the combination of columns that we
can add together because they tend to move
in the same direction.
So in this case, we say start with our 50
columns and I want to create just 3 columns
that capture all of the information of the
original 50.
If you're interested in learning more about
how this works, PCA is something which is
everywhere on the Internet, so there's lots
of information about it.
The details aren't important.
The important thing is to recognize that we're
squishing our 50 latent factors down to 3.
So if we look at the first PCA factor and
we sort on it, we can see that on one end
we have fairly well-regarded movies, like
The Godfather, Pulp Fiction, Usual Suspects,
these are all things which are kind of classics.
At the other end, we have things like Ace
Ventura and RoboCop 3, which are perhaps not
so classic.
So our first PCA factor is some kind of is_classic
score.
[Time: 20 minute mark]
On our second one, we have something similar
but actually very different.
At one end, we've got 10 movies that are huge
Hollywood blockbusers with lots of special
effects, and at the other end we have things
like Annie Hall and Brokeback Mountain, which
are kind of dialog-heavy, not big Hollywood
hits.
So there's another dimension.
This is the first most important dimension
by which people judge movies differently,
and this is the second most important dimension
by which people judge movies differently.
The third most important one by which people
judge movies differently is something where
at one end we have a bunch of violent and
scarey movies.
At the other end, we have happy movies.
For those of you who haven't seen Babe, an
Australian movie, happiest movie ever.
It's about a small pig and its adventures
and its path to success.
Happiest movie ever according to MovieLens.
So that's interesting, right?
It's not just saying that these factors are
good or bad or anything like that, it's just
saying that these are the things that when
we've done this matrix decomposition, these
things pop out as the ways people are different
in their ratings for different kinds of movies.
So one of the reasons I wanted to show you
this is to say that these kind of SGD-learned
many-parameter networks are not inscrutable.
Indeed, it's not great to go in and look at
every one of those 50 latent factor coefficients
in detail, but you have to think about how
to visualize them, how to look at them.
In this case, I actually went a step further
and grabbed a couple of principal components
and tried drawing a picture.
With pictures, of course, you can start to
see things in multiple dimensions.
So here, I've got the first and third principal
components.
So you can see here, on the right hand side
we have more of the Hollywood-type movies,
at the far left, some of the more classic
movies, and at the top the more violent movies,
and at the bottom the happier movies.
Babe's so far happy that it's right off the
bottom.
So if you wanted to find a movie that was
violent and classic, you'd go into the top
left, and Kubrick's A Clockwork Orange would
probably be the one that most people would
come up with first.
If you wanted to come up with something that
was very Hollywood and very non-violent, you
would be down here with Sleepless in Seattle.
You can really learn a lot by looking at these
kind of models, but you don't do it by looking
at the coefficients.
You do it by visualizations, you do it by
interrogating it.
For any of you that have done much statistics
before or have a background in the social
sciences, you've spent most of your time doing
regressions and looking at coefficients and
t-tests and stuff, and this is a very different
world.
This is a world where you're asking the model
questions and getting the modeled results,
which is kind of what we're doing here.
I mentioned I would talk briefly about this
syntax.
This syntax is something we're going to be
using about a lot more often and it's part
of what's called the Keras Functional API.
The Keras functional API is a way of doing
exactly the same things you've already learned
how to do using a different API.
That is not such a dumb idea.
The API you've learned so far is the sequential
API, it's where you use the word "sequential"
[model=Sequential()] and then you write in
order the layers of your neural network.
That's all very well, but what if you wanted
to do something like what we wanted to do
just now where we had like two different things
coming in - we had a userId coming in and
a movieId coming in, and each one went through
its own embedding and then they got multiplied
together - how do you express that as a sequence?
It's not very easy to do that.
So the functional API was designed to answer
this question.
The first thing to note about the functional
API is that you can do everything you can
do in the sequential API.
Here's an example of something you can do
perfectly well with the sequential API, which
is something with two dense layers.
But it looks a bit different.
Every functional API model starts with an
input layer, and then you assign that to some
variable.
And then you list each of the layers in order,
and for each of them, after you've provided
the details for that layer you then immediately
call the layer passing in the output of the
previous layer.
[Time: 25 minute mark]
So this passes in inputs and calls it x [x=Dense(64,activation='relu')(inputs)].
And then this passes in our x and this is
our new version of x [x=Dense(64,actiation='relu')(x)].
And then this dense layer gets the next version
of x and returns predictions [predictions=Dense(10,activation="softmax")(x)].
So you can see that each layer is saying what
its previous layer is, so it's doing exactly
the same thing as a sequential API, just in
a different way.
As the docs note here, the sequential model
is probably a better choice for this particular
network because it's easier.
This is just showing that you can do it.
On the other hand, the model that we just
looked at would be quite difficult, if not
impossible, to do with a sequential API, but
with the functional API, it's very easy.
We created a whole separate model which gave
an output 'u', for user, and that was the
result of creating an embedding.
We said an embedding has its own input and
then goes through an embedding layer, and
then we return input to that and the embedding
layer, like so.
So that gave us our user input and our user
embedding and our movie input and our movie
embedding.
So there's like two separate little models.
And then we did a similar thing to create
two little models for our bias terms; they
were both things that grabbed an embedding,
returning a single output and then flattened
it.
And then we grabbed their biases.
And so now we have four separate models, and
we can merge them.
There's this function called merge.
It's pretty confusing -- there's a small m
'merge' and a big M 'Merge'.
In general, you will be using the small m
merge.
I'm not going into the details of why they
are both there.
They are there for a reason.
If something weird happens to you with merge,
try remembering to use the small m merge.
The small m merge takes two previous outputs
that you've just created using the functional
API and combines them in whatever way you
want.
In this case, the dot product {x=merge([u,m],
mode='dot'}.
So that grabs our user and movie embeddings
and takes the dot product.
We grab the output of that and take our user
bias and the sum, and the output of that and
the movie bias and the sum.
So that's a functional API to creating that
model at the end of which we then use the
model function to actually create a model,
saying what are the inputs to the model and
what is the output of the model.
So you can see this is different to usual
because we've now got multiple inputs.
Then when we call fit, we now have to pass
in an array of inputs, userId and movieId.
So the functional API is something that we're
going to be using increasingly from now on,
now that we've kind of learned all the basic
architectures (just about), we're going to
be starting to build more exotic architectures
for more special cases and we'll be using
the functional API more and more.
Question: Is the only reason to use an embedding
layer so that you can use provide a list of
integers as input?
Answer: That's a great question -- Is the
only reason to use an embedding layer so that
you can use it as an input?
Absolutely yes!
So instead of using an embedding layer, we
could have one-hot encoded all of those userId's
and one-hot encoded all of those movieId's
and create dense layers on top of them, then
it would have done exactly the same thing.
Question: Why choose 50 latent factors and
reduce them down with a Principal Component
Analysis.
Why not just have 3 latent factors to begin
with?
Answer: Sure, if we only used 3 latent factors,
then our predictive model would have been
less accurate.
We want an accurate predictive model so that
when people come to our website we can do
a good job of telling them what movie to watch.
So 50 latent factors for that.
But then for the purpose of visualization
for understanding what those factors are doing,
we want a small number so that we can interpret
them more easily.
So one thing you might want to try during
the week is taking one or two of your models
and converting them to use the functional
API.
Just as a little thing to try to start to
get a hang of how this API looks.
Question: Are these functional models how
we would add additional information to images
in CNN's -- say driving speed or turning rate?
[Time: 30 minute mark]
Answer: Yes, absolutely.
In general, the idea of adding additional
information to a CNN is basically like adding
metadata.
This happens in collaborative filtering a
lot.
You might have a collaborative filtering model
that as well as having the ratings table,
you also have information about what genre
the movie is in.
Maybe the demographic information about the
user.
So you can incorporate all that stuff by having
additional inputs.
With a CNN, let me give you an example.
With the new Kaggle fish recognition competition,
one of the things it turns out is a useful
predictor (it's a leakage problem) is the
size of the image.
So you could have another input which is the
height and width of the image (just as integers)
and have that as a separate input that is
concatenated to the output of your convolutional
layer after the first flatten layer and then
your dense layers can incorporate both convolutional
outputs and your metadata.
Two great questions.
You might remember from last week that this
whole thing about collaborative filtering
was a journey to somewhere else, and the journey
is to NLP, Natural Language Processing.
Question: This is a question about collaborative
filtering.
So if we need to predict the missing values,
the NANs of 0.0, so the user hasn't watched
the movie.
What would be the prediction?
How do we go about predicting that?
Answer: The key purpose of creating this model
is so that you can make predictions for movie-user
combinations you haven't seen before.
The way you do that is to simply do something
like this -- you just call model.predict and
pass in a movieId-userId pair that you haven't
seen before.
And all that's going to do is it's going to
take the dot product of that movie's latent
factors and that user's latent factors and
add on those biases and return you back the
answer.
It's that easy.
If this was a Kaggle competition, that would
be how we would generate our submission for
the Kaggle competition, would be to take that
test set, a bunch of user-movie pairs, that
we hadn't seen before.
Natural Language Processing.
Collaborative filtering is extremely useful
of itself.
Without any doubt, it is far more commerically
important right now than NLP is.
Having said that, fast-ai's mission is to
impact society in as positive a way as possible,
and doing a better job on predicting movies
is not necessarily the best way to do that,
so we're maybe less excited about collaborative
filtering than some people in industry are.
That's why its not our main destination.
NLP, on the other hand, can be a very big
deal if you can do a good job, for example,
of reading through lots of medical journal
articles or family histories or patient notes,
you could be a long way towards creating a
fantastic diagnostic tool to use in the developing
world to help bring medicine to people who
don't currently have it.
Which is almost as good as telling them not
to watch Battlefield Earth.
They're both important.
Let's talk a little bit about NLP.
In order to do this, we're going to look at
a particular dataset.
This dataset is a classic example of what
people do with Natural Language Processing,
and it's called Sentiment Analysis.
Sentiment Analysis means that you take a piece
of text - could be a phrase, a sentence, a
paragraph, or a whole document - and decide
whether or not that is a positive or negative
sentiment.
Keras actually comes with such a dataset,
which is called the IMDb Sentiment dataset.
The IMDb sentiment dataset was originally
developed from the Stanford AI group, and
the paper about it (I think it was actually
published in 2012) is this one here (Learning
Word Vectors for Sentiment Analysis) and they
talk about all the details about what people
want to do with sentiment analysis.
[Time: 35 minute mark]
In general, although academic papers tend
to be way more math-y than they should be,
their introductory sections often do a great
job of capturing why this is an interesting
problem, what kinds of approaches people have
taken and so forth.
The other reason papers are super-helpful
is that you can skip down to the experiments
section (every machine learning paper pretty
much has an experiments section) and find
out what the score is.
Here's the score section.
So here they showed that using this dataset
they created of IMDb movie reviews along with
their sentiment, their full model plus an
additional model, got a score of 88.33% accuracy
in predicting sentiment.
They had another one here where they also
added in some unlabeled data, we're not going
to be looking at that today - that would be
a semi-superised learning problem.
So today our goal is to beat 88.33 as being
the academic state-of-the-art for this dataset
as of this time.
So, to grab it we can just say "from keras.datasets
import imdb".
Keras actually fiddles around with it in ways
that I don't like, so I actually copied and
pasted from the Keras file these three lines
to import it directly, without screwing with
it.
So that's why, rather than using the Keras
dataset directly I'm using these 3 lines.
There are 25,000 movie reviews in the training
set, and here is an example of one: "bromwell
high is a cartoon comedy, it ran at the same
time as some other programs ..."
So the dataset does not actually come to us
in quite this format, it actually comes to
us in this format, which is a list of IDs.
So these IDs then, we can look up in the word
index, which is something they provide.
And so for example, if we look at idx_array.
The word index, as you can see, basically
maps an integer to every word.
It's in order of how frequently those words
appeared in this particular corpus, which
is kind of handy.
So then I also created a reverse index, which
goes from word to ID.
So I can see in the very first training example,
the very first word is number 23022, so if
I look up index to word 23022, idx2word[23022],
it is the word 'bromwell'.
And so then I just go though and I map everything
in that first review to idx2word and join
it together with a space, and that's how we
can turn the data they give us back into a
movie review.
As well as providing the reviews, they also
provide labels.
1 is positive sentiment, 0 is negative sentiment.
So our goal is to take these 25,000 reviews
that look like this, and predict whether it
will be positive or negative in sentiment.
And the data is actually provided to us as
a list of word IDs for each review.
Is everybody clear on the problem we are trying
to solve and how it's laid out?
Okay, you guys are great.
So there's a couple of things we can do to
make it simpler.
One is we can reduce the vocabulary.
So currently there are some pretty unusual
words, like word #23022 is 'Bromwell'.
And if we're trying to figure out how to deal
with all these different words, having to
figure out the various ways in which the word
'Bromwell' is being used is probably not going
to net us much for a lot of computation and
memory cost.
So we're going to truncate the vocabulary
down to 5,000.
And it's very easy to do that because the
words are already ordered by frequency, I
simply go through everything in our training
set and I just say if the word ID is less
than this vocab_size of 5,000, we'll leave
it as it is.
Otherwise, we'll replace it with the number
5000.
So at the end of this, we now have repaced
all of our rare words with a single ID.
[Time: 40 minute mark]
Here's a quick look at these sentences.
The reviews are sometimes up to 2493 words
long (some people spend far too much time
on IMDb), some are as short as 10 words, on
average they are 237 words.
As you'll see, we actually need to make all
of our reviews the same length, so allowing
this 2493 word review uses a lot of memory
and time, so we re going to decide to truncate
every review to 500 words, and that's more
than twice as big as the mean.
So we're not going to lose too much.
Question: What if the word "5000" gets a bias?
Answer: Whatever the word "5000" is Let's
find out what the word "5000" is, idx2word(5000)
... I guess the year "1987".
That's fine, we're about to learn a machine-learning
model and so the vast majority of the time
it comes across the word #5000, it's actually
going to mean rare word; it's not going to
specifically mean 1987.
And it's going to learn to deal with that
as best as it can.
The idea is the rare words don't appear too
often, so hopefully this is not going to cause
too much trouble.
Question: Doesn't just using frequency favor
stop-words
Answer: We're not just using frequencies,
all we're doing, we're just truncating our
vocabulary at this point.
Question: So the 5000 word, can we just replace
it with some neutral word and we don't need
to take care of that bias thing?
Answer: There's really not going to be a bias
here.
We're just replacing it with a random ID.
The fact that occasionally the word 1987 actually
pops up is totally insignificant.
We could replace it with -1.
It's just a sentinal value which has no meaning.
Comment: Also, we're getting rid of all the
words that are 5000 and beyond.
It's not a single word.
Response: That's correct.
It represents all of the less common words.
It's one of those design decisions which it's
not worth spending a lot of time thinking
about because it's not significant.
I just picked what happened to be easiest
at the time.
As I said, I could have just as well used
-1 because it's not important.
What is important is that we have to create
a rectangular matrix which we can pass to
our machine learning model.
Quite conveniently Keras comes with something
caled pad_sequences that does this for us.
It takes everything greater than this length
and truncates it and everything less than
this length and pads it with whatever we ask
for, which in this case is 0's.
So at the end of this, the shape of our training
set is now a numpy array with 25,000 rows
and 500 columns, and as you can see, it's
padded the front with 0's, such that it has
500 words in it.
Other than that, it's exactly the same as
before.
And as you can see "bromwell" is not replaced
with 5000, but with 4999.
So this is our same movie review again after
going through that padding process.
Question: Does it matter if we pad from the
left or the right?
Answer: I know that there's some reason that
Keras decided to pad the front rather than
the back.
I don't recall what it is.
Since it's what it does by default, I don't
worry about it; I don't think it's important.
Now that we have a rectangular matrix of numbers,
and we have some labels, we can use the exact
techniques we've already learned to create
a model.
As per usual, we should try and create the
simplest models we possible can to start with.
And we know that the simplest model we can
is one with 1 hidden layer in the middle.
This is the simplest model that we generally
think ought to be useful for just about everything.
Now, here is why we started with collaborative
filtering - it is because we started with
an embedding.
So if you think about it, our input are word
IDs and we want to convert that into a vector,
and that is what an embedding does.
[Time: 45 minute mark]
Rather than one-hot encoding this into a 5,000
column long huge input thing and then doing
a matrix product, an embedding just says,
look up that movieId and grab that vector
directly.
So it's just a computational and memory shortcut
to creating a one-hot encoding followed by
a matrix product.
So we're creating an embedding where we're
going to have 5,000 latent factors, or 5,000
embeddings, each one we're going to have 32
items, rather than 50.
So then we're going to flatten that, have
our single dense layer, a bit of drop out,
and then our output to a sigmoid.
That's a pretty simple model.
It's a good idea to go through and make sure
you understand why all these parameter counts
are what they are.
That's something you can do during the week
and double-check that you're comfortable with
all of those.
So this is the size of each of the weight
matrices at each point.
We can fit it and after
one epoch we have 88% accuracy on the validation
set.
And so let's just compare that to Stanford
where they had 88.3 and we have 88.04.
So we're not yet there, but we're well on
the right track.
Question: Why 32?
Answer: This is always the question about
why have X number of filters in your convolutional
layer, or why have X number of outputs in
your dense layer?
It's just a case of trying things and seeing
what works, and also getting some intuition
by looking at other models.
In this case, I think 32 was the first I tried.
I kind of felt like from my understanding
of really big embedding models (which you'll
learn about shortly) even 50 dimensions is
enough to capture vocabularies of size 100,000
or more, so I felt like 32 was likely to be
more than enough to capture a vocabulary of
size 5,000.
I tried it, I got a pretty good result and
basically left it there.
If at some point I decided I wasn't getting
great results, I would try increasing it.
Question: Why sigmoid in the final layer?
Answer: You can always use a SoftMax instead
of a sigmoid.
It just means that you would have to change
your labels - remember, our labels were just
1s or 0s, a single column.
If I wanted to use SoftMax I would have to
create two columns - it wouldn't just be one,
it would be one-zero-one-zero-one-zero.
In the past, I've generally stuck to using
SoftMax and then categorical cross-entropy
loss, just to be consistent, because then
regardless of whether you have two classes
or more than two classes, you can always get
the same thing.
In this case I want to show the other way
that you can do this, which is to have a single
column output.
And remember signmoid is exactly the same
thing as SoftMax if you have a binary output.
Question: And so here, 1 is positive and 0
is negative?
Answer: Yes.
And so, rather than using categorical cross_entropy,
we used binary_crossentropy, and again, it's
exactly the same thing.
It just means I don't have to worry about
one-hot encoding the output because it's just
a binary output.
Question: Do we know what the inter-rater
agreement is for this dataset?
Answer: No we don't.
It's not something I have looked at.
The important thing as far as I'm concerned
is what is the benchmark that the Stanford
people got.
They compared it to a range of other previous
benchmarks and they found that their technique
was the best, so that's my goal here.
And I'm sure there have been other techniques
to come out since then (probably better),
but I haven't seen them in any papers yet,
so this is my target.
You can see that we can in one second of training,
get an accuracy which is pretty competitive,
and it's just a simple neural net.
Hopefully you're starting to get a sense that
a neural net with one hidden layer is a great
starting point for nearly everything.
You now know how to create a pretty good sentiment
analysis model, and before today, you didn't,
so that's a good step.
[Time: 50 minute mark]
Question: Just to confirm, whenever we use
binary_crossentropy, we use sigmoid for the
final layer.
Answer: Yes.
Question: Could you explain embedding again?
What is the actual imput to the dense layer
for Word 2345?
Answer: This is an embedding (col-H->col-V;
row-20->row-24).
I think it would be particularly helpful if
we go back to our MovieLens recommendation
dataset (lesson4.ipynb, Set up data).
And remember that the actual data coming in
does not look like this, it looks like this.
So then when we then come along and say, okay
what do we predit the rating would be for
userId 1 for movieId 1172, we actually have
to go through our list of movieIds and find
movieId 31, and then having found 31, then
look up its latent factor.
Then we have to do the same thing for userId
1 and then find its latent factor, and then
we have to multply the two together.
So that step of taking a ID, finding it in
a list and returning the vector it is attached
to, that is what an embedding is.
So an embedding returns a vector which is
or length (in this case) 32.
(note that the "None" here always means your
mini-batch size)
So for each movie review, for each of the
500 words in that sequence, you're getting
a 32-element vector.
And so therefore you have a mini-batch size,
by 500 X 32 tensor coming out of this layer.
That gets flattened (so 500*32=16,000), and
then that is the input to your first dense
layer.
Comment: I also think it might be helpful
to show that for a review, instead of having
that word that's being entered as a sequence
of numbers, where that number is ...
Response: Yes, that's right.
So we look at this first review, and remember
the 23022 word review has now been truncated
to 499, this is 309 so it's going to take
309 and look up the 309th vector in the embedding,
and it's going to return it and it's going
to concatenate it to create this tensor.
So that's all an embedding is.
An embedding is a shortcut to a one-hot encoding,
followed by a matrix product.
Question: Can you show us words which have
similar latent features?
I'm hoping these words would be synonyms or
semantically similar.
Answer: Yes, we'll see that shortly.
Question: Who made the labels and why should
I believe them?
It seems difficult and subjective.
Answer: That's the whole point of sentiment
analysis and these kinds of things is that
it's totally subjective.
The interesting thing about NLP is that we're
trying to capture something which is very
subjective.
So in this case, you would have to read the
original paper (Learning Word Vectors for
Seniment Analysis) to find out how they got
these particular labels.
The way that people tend to get labels is
either in this case, the IMDb dataset.
IMDb has ratings - so you could just say everything
higher than 8 is very positve, everything
lower than 2 is very negative, and we'll throw
away everything in the middle.
The other way people tend to label academic
datasets is to send it off to Amazon Mechanical
Turk and pay them a few cents to label each
thing.
That's the kinds of ways that you can label
stuff.
Comment: And there are places where people
don't just use Mechanical Turk, but they specifically
try to hire linguistics PhD's.
Response: Yes.
You certainly wouldn't want to do that for
this because the whole purpose here is to
capture normal people's sentiments.
For example, when I was in medicine, we went
through all these radiology reports and tried
to capture which ones were critical findings
and which ones weren't critical findings and
we used good radiologists, rather than Mechanical
Turk for that purpose.
Question: So you're not considering any sentence
construction or bigrams?
Just a Bag of Words and the literal set of
words that are being used?
[Time: 55 minute mark]
Answer: It's not actually just a Bag of Words.
If you think about it, this dense layer here
has 1.6 million parameters and its connecting
every one of those 500 inputs to our output.
Not only that, but it's doing that for every
one of the incoming factors.
So it's creating a pretty complex, big cartesian
product of all of these weights.
It's taking account of the position of a word
in the overall sentence.
It's not terribly sophisticated and it's not
taking into account its position compared
to other words, but it is taking into account
where abouts it occurs in the whole review.
It's not like the dumbest kind of model I
could come up with, it's a good starting point.
But we would expect with a little bit of thought
(which we're about to use), we could do a
lot better.
So why don't we go ahead and do that.
So the slightly better - hopefully you guys
have all predicted what that would be - a
convolutional neural network.
And the reason I hope you predicted that is:
A) we've already talked about how CNN's are
taking over the world and
B)
specifically they're taking over the world
any time we have some kind of ordered data.
And clearly a sentence is ordered.
One word comes after another word.
It has a specific ordering.
So therefore we can use a convolution.
We can't use a 2D convolution because a sentence
is not in 2D, a sentence is in 1D.
So we're going to use a 1D convolution.
So a 1D convolution is even simpler than a
2D convolution.
We're just going to grab a string of a few
words and we're going to take their embeddings,
and we're going to take that string and we're
going to multiply it by some filter.
And then we're going to move that sequence
along our sentence.
So this is our normal next place we go as
we try to gradually increase the complexity,
which is to grab our simplest possible CNN,
which is a Convolution, Dropout, MaxPooling
and then Flatten that and we have our Dense
layer and our Output.
So this is exactly like exactly what we did
when we looking at gradually improving our
State Farm result, but rather than having
Convolution2D, we have Convolution1D.
The parameters are exactly the same -- how
many filters do you want to create, and what
is the size of your convolution.
Originally I tried 3 here but 5 turned out
to be better so I'm looking at 5 words at
a time and multiplying them by each one of
64 filters.
So we're going to start with the same embedding
as before.
We take our sentences and we turn them into
a 500x32 matrix for each of our inputs.
We then put it through our convolution.
And because our convolution has a border_mode='same',
we get back exactly the same shape as we gave
it.
We then put it through our 1D MaxPooling,
and that will halve its size and then we stick
it through the same dense layers as we had
before.
So that's a really simple convolutional network
for words.
Compile it, run it, and we get 89.47, compared
to 88.33.
So we've already broken the academic state-of-the-art
as of when this paper was written.
Again, a simple convolutional neural network
gets us a very, very long way.
Question: Convolution2D for images is easier
to understand, element-wise multiplication
and addition.
But what does it mean for a sequence of words?
Answer: Don't think of it as a sequence of
words.
Remember, it's been through an embedding.
So it's a sequence of 32-element vectors.
So it's doing exactly the same thing we were
doing in a 2D convolution, but rather than
having 3 channels of color, we have 32 channels
of embedding.
[Time: 1 hour mark]
Just like in our convolution spreadsheet,
remember how in the second one, once we had
two filters already, our filter had to be
a 3x3x2 tensor in order to allow us to create
the second layer.
For us, we now don't have a 3x3x2 tensor,
we have a 5x1x32, or more conveniently a 5x32
matrix.
So each convolution is going to go through
each of the 5 words and each of the 32 embeddings,
do an element-wise multiplication and add
them all up.
The important thing to remember is once we've
done the embedding layer, which is always
going to be our first step, for every NLP
model, is that we don't have words anymore.
We now have vectors which are attempting to
capture the information in that word in some
way, just like our latent factors captured
information about a movie and a user in our
collaborative filtering.
We haven't yet looked at what they do.
We wil in a moment, just like we did with
the movie vectors, but we do know from our
experience that SGD is going to try to fill
out those 32 places with information about
how that word is being used, which allow us
to make these predictions.
Just like when you first learned about 2D
convolutions, it took you probably a few days
of fiddling around with spreadsheets, and
pieces of paper, and Python, and checking
inputs and outputs to get a really intuitive
understanding of what a 2D convolution is
doing.
You may find it is the same with a 1D convolution,
that it will take you probably a fifth of
the time to get there because you've really
done all the hard work already.
There's a couple of concepts that we come
across in this class that there is no way
that me lecturing to you is going to be enough
for you to get an intuitive understanding
of it.
The first, clearly, is the 2D convolution.
Hopefully, you've had lots of opportunities
to experiment and practice and read; these
are things you have to tackly from many, many
different directions to understand a 2D convolution.
2D convolutions, in a sense, are really 3D,
because if it's in full color, you've got
3 channels, that's something you've all played
with.
And once you have multiple filters, later
on in your image models, you still have 3D
and you have more than 3 channels.
You might have 32 filters, or 64 filters.
In this lesson, we've introduced one much
simpler concept, but it's still new - the
1D convolution, which is really a 2D convolution,
because just like with images, we have red-green-blue,
now we have the 32 embedding factors.
So that's something you'll definitely need
to experiment with.
Create a model with just an embedding layer,
look at what the output is, what is its shape,
what does it look like and then how does a
1D convolution modify that.
Then trying to understand what an embedding
is is kind of your next big task.
If you're not already feeling comfortable
with it and you haven't seen them before today,
I'm sure you won't.
This is a big, new concept.
It's not in any way mathematically challenging
- it's literally looking up an array, and
returning the thing at that ID.
So an embedding looking at movieId 3 is go
to the third column of the matrix and return
what you see.
That's all an embedding does.
It couldn't be mathematically simpler, it
is the simplest possible operation - return
the thing at this index.
But the kind of intuitive understanding of
what happens when you put an embedding in
an SGD and learn a vector which turns out
to be useful is something which is kind of
mind-blowing because as we saw from the MovieLens
example with just a dot product and this simple
look-up something in an index operation, we
ended up with vectors which captured all kinds
of interesting features about movies, without
us in any was asking it to.
So I kind of wanted to make sure that you
guys felt that after this class, you're going
to go away and try and find a dozen different
ways of looking at these concepts.
[Time: 1.05 hour mark]
One of these ways is to look at how other
people explain them.
Chris Olah has one of the very very best technical
blogs I've come across and I've often referred
to in this class.
In his Understanding Convolutions post (colah.github.io/posts/2014-07-Understanding-Convolutions/),
he has a very interesting example of thinking
about what a dropped ball does as a convolutional
operation, and he shows how you can think
about a 1D convolution using this dropped
ball analogy.
Particularly if you have some background in
mechanical or electrical engineering, I suspect
you'll find this a very helpful example.
There are many resources out there for thinking
about convolutions, and I hope some of you
will share on the forums any that you come
across.
Question: Essentially are we training the
input too?
Answer: Yes, we are absolutely training the
input.
Because the only input we have is 25,000 sequences
of 500 integers.
And so we take each of those integers and
we replace them with a look-up into a 500
column matrix.
Initially that matrix is random.
Just like in our Excel example, we started
with a random matrix (these are all random
numbers) and then we created this loss function,
which was the sum-of-squares of differences
between the dot-product and the rating.
If we then used the gradient descent solver
in Excel to solve that, it attempts to modify
the two embedding matrices (as you can see,
the objective is going down) to try and come
us with the two matrices which give us the
best approximation of the original rating
matrix.
So this Excel spreadsheet is something which
you can play with and do exactly what our
first MovieLens example is doing in Python.
The only difference is the version in Python
also has L2 regularization.
So this one's just finished here.
It's come up that these are no longer random.
We've now got 2 embedding matrices which have
got the loss function down from 40 to 5.6.
So you can see now that these ratings are
very close to what they're meant to be.
So this is exactly what Keras and SGD are
doing in our Python example.
Question: You said we got an embedding in
which each word is a vector of 32 elements?
Answer: Exactly.
Each word in our vocabulary of 5,000 is being
converted into a vector of 32 elements.
Question: What would be the equivalent dense
network if we didn't use a 2D embedding in
the initial model?
A dense layer with input size of embedding
size half size?
Answer: I actually don't actually know what
that is.
Question: Does it matter that encoded values
which are close by in case of color in case
of pictures, which is not word vectors.
For example, 254 and 255 are close as colors
but as words they have no relationship.
Answer: The important thing to realize is
that the word IDs are not used mathematically
in any way at all other than as an index to
look up into integer.
So the fact this this is movie 27, the number
27 is not used in any way.
We just take the number 27 and find its vector.
What's important is the values of each latent
factor as to whether they are close together.
So in the movie example there was some latent
factor "Is it a Hollywood blockbuster?" and
there was some latent factors that were about
"Is it a violent movie or not?".
It is the similarity on those factors that
matter.
The ID is never ever used other than as an
index to simply index into a matrix to return
the vector that we found.
[Time: 1.10 hour mark]
As Ynette was mentioning, in our case now
for the word embeddings we are looking up
in our embeddings to return a 32-element vector
of floats that are initially random and the
model is trying to learn the 32 floats for
each of the words that is semantically useful.
In a moment, we're going to look at some visualizations
of that to try and understand what it's actually
learned.
Question: Can I use the drop-off on the embedding
as well as on the next layer?
What is the signficance and what is the difference
between the two?
Answer: Great question.
You can apply the drop-out parameter to the
embedding layer itself and what that does
is it zeroes out at random 20% of each of
these 32 embeddings to each word.
So its avoiding overfitting the specifics
of each word's embeddding.
This dropout, on the other hand, is removing
at random some of the words effectively, some
of the whole vectors.
The significance of which one to remove where
is not something that I've seen anybody research
in depth, so I'm not sure that we have an
answer that says use this amount in this place.
I just tried a few different values in different
places and it seems that putting the same
amount of drop-out on all these different
spots seems to work pretty well in my experiments.
So it's a reasonable rule-of-thumb.
If you find you're massively overfitting or
massively underfitting, try playing around
with different values and report back to us
on the forum.
Perhaps you'll find some different, better
configurations that I've come up with.
I'm sure some of you will.
Let's think about what's going on here.
We're taking each of the 5,000 words in our
vocabulary and we're replacing them with a
32-element long vector, which we are training
to hopefully capture all of the information
about what this word means and what it does
and how it works.
You might expect intuitively that somebody
might have done this before.
Just like with ImageNet and VGG, you can get
a pre-trained network that says if you've
got an image that looks a bit like a dog,
we've trained a network which has seen lots
of dogs, so it will probably take your dog
image and return useful predictions, because
we've done lots of dog images before.
The interesting thing here is your dog picture
and the VGG author's dog pictures are not
the same; they're going to be different in
all kinds of ways.
So to get pre-trained weights for images,
you have to give somebody a whole pre-trained
network, which is like 500 MBytes worth of
weights and a whole architecture.
Words are much easier.
In a document, the word "dog" always appears
the same way -- it's the word "dog".
It doesn't have different liking conditions,
or facial expressions or whatever, it's just
the word "dog".
The cool thing is that in NLP we don't have
to pass around pre-trained networks, we can
pass around pre-trained embeddings, or as
they're commonly known, pre-trained word vectors.
That is to say other people have already created
big models with big text corpuses where they've
attempted to build a 32-element vector (or
however long vector) which captures all of
the useful information about what that word
is and how it behaves.
So, for example, if we google "word embeddings
download", lots of questions and answers and
pages about where we can download pre-trained
word embeddings.
Question: That's pretty cool.
But I guess what is non-intuitive to me is
I think this means that if I can train a corpus
on the works of Shakespeare somehow that tells
me something about how I can understand movie
reviews.
I imagine that in some sense that's true about
how language is structured, but the meaning
of the word "dog" in Shakespeare is probably
a little bit different.
Answer: We're getting to that now.
[Time: 1.15 hour mark]
So the word vectors that I'm going to be using
(and I don't strongly recommend, but slightly
recommend) the GloVe word vectors.
The other main competition to these is called
the word2vec word vectors.
The GloVe word vectors come from a researcher
named Jeffrey Pennington from Stanford.
The word2vec word vectors come from Google.
I will mention that the TensorFlow documentation
for the word2vec vectors is fantastic, so
I would definitely highly recommend checking
this out.
The GloVe word vectors have been been pre-trained
on a number of different corpuses.
One of them has been pre-trained on all of
Wikipedia and a huge database full of newspaper
articles; 6 billion words, covering a 400,000
size vocabularly.
They provide a 50 dimensional, 100 dimensional,
200 dimensional and 300 dimensional pre-trained
vectors.
They have another one which has been trained
on 40 billion words of a huge dump of the
entire Internet.
And they have another one which has been pre-trained
on 2 billion tweets, of which all of the Donald
Trup tweets have been carefully cleaned out
prior to usage.
So in my case what I've done is I've downloaded
the 6 billion token version and I will show
you what one of these looks like.
Question: Are you losing context because of
the capital letters, punctuation?
Answer: We'll look at that in a moment.
Sometimes these are cased, so you can see
for example this particular one includes case.
There are 2.2 million items in the vocabulary
in this.
Sometimes they're uncased.
And we'll look at punctuation in a moment.
Here is the start of the GloVe 50-dimensional
word vectors trained on a word corpus of 6
billion.
Here is the word "the" and here are
the 50 floats which attempt to capture all
of the information in the word "the".
Punctuation - here is the word full stop,
and here are the 50 floats that attempt to
capture all of the information captured by
a full stop.
Here is the word "in".
Here is the word double quote.
Here is apostrophe-s.
So you can see that the GloVe authors have
tokenized their text in a particular way and
the idea that apostrophe-s should be treated
as a thing makes a lot of sense.
It certainly has that thing-y-ness in the
English language.
And so the way the authors of a word embedding
corpus have chosen to tokenize their text
definitely matters.
One of the things I like about GloVe is that
they've been pretty smart, in my opinion,
about how they've done this.
Question: What was the target variable?
Answer: The question is how does one create
word vectors in general, what is the model
you're creating and what are the labels you're
building.
One of the
things that we talked about getting to at
some point is unsupervised learning.
This is a great example of unsupevised learning.
We want to take 840 billion tokens of an Internet
dump and build a model of something.
What do we build a model of?
This is a great example of unsupervised learning.
We're trying to capture some structure of
this data.
In this case, how does English look, work
and feel.
The way that this is done, at least in the
word2vec example, is quite cool.
What do is they take every sentence of 11
words long, every 11 long string of words
that appears in the corpus.
The first thing they do is they create a copy
of it, an exact copy.
[Time: 1.20 hour mark]
In the copy they delete the middle word and
replace it with some random word.
So we now have 2 strings of 11 words, one
of which makes sense because it's real, one
of which probably doesn't make sense because
the middle word has been replaced with something
random.
And so the model task that they create is
the label is 1 if it is a real sentence and
0 if it is a fake sentence; that is the task
they give it.
You can see it's not a directly useful task.
Unless somebody comes along and says I just
found this corpus in which somebody has replaced
half of the middle words with random words.
But it is something where in order to be able
to tackle this task, you're going to have
to know something about language.
You're going to have to be able to recognize
that this sentence doesn't make sense and
this sentence does make sense.
So this is a great example of unsupervised
learning.
Generally speaking, in deep-learning, unsupervised
learning means coming up with a task which
is as close to the task you're going to be
eventually interested in as possible, but
which doesn't require labels, or where the
labels are really cheap to generate.
Question: The language aspect - how does
this change across languages?
Answer: So it turns out that the embeddings
that is created when you look at Hindu and
Japanese turn out to be nearly the same.
So one way to translate language is to create
a bunch of word vectors in English for various
words, and then to create a bunch of word
vectors in say, Japanese, for various words.
Then what you can do is say I want to translate
this word, which might be "queen" to Japanese.
You can basically look up and find the nearest
word in the same vector space in the Japanese
corpus and it turns out it works.
So it is a fascinating thing about language.
Google has just announced that they replaced
Google Translate with a neural translation
system, and part of what that is doing is
basically doing this.
Here are some interesting examples of some
word embeddings.
The word embeddings for king-queen has the
same distance and direction as the word embedding
for man-woman.
Ditto for walked-walking and swam-swimming.
Ditto for Spain-Madrid and Italy-Rome.
So the embeddings that have to get learned
in order to solve this stupid meaningless
random sentence task are quite amazing.
So I've actually downloading those GloVe embeddings
and I've pre-processed them and I'm going
to upload them for you shortly into a form
that's going to be really easy for you to
use in Python.
And I've created load_glove which preprocessed
stuff that I created for you.
It's going to give you three things.
It's going to give you the word vectors, which
is the 400,000 x 50 dimensional vectors, a
list of the words, and a list of the word
indexes.
So you can now take a word and call word2vec
(w2v) and get back its 50 dimensional array.
And so then I drew a picture.
In order to turn a 50 dimensional vector into
something 2-dimensional that I can plot we
have to do something called dimensionality
reduction.
There's a particular technique (the details
don't really matter) called TSNE, which attempts
to find a way of taking your high-dimensional
information and plot it in 2 dimensions, such
that things that were close in the 50 dimensions
are still close in the 2 dimensions.
So I used TSNE to plot the first 350 most
common words, and here they all are.
You can see that punctuation appears close
to one another, numerals appear close to one
another.
Seasons, games, leagues played are all close
to each another.
Various things about politics, school and
university.
President, general, prime, minister and bush
are close.
[Time: 1.25 hour mark]
This is a great example of where this TNSE
2 dimensional projection is misleading about
the level of complexity that's in these word
vectors.
In a different projection, bush would be very
close to tree.
The 2 dimensional projection is losing a lot
of information, the true detail here is a
lot more complex than us mere humans can see
on a page, but hopefully you get a sense of
this.
All I've done here is taken those 50 dimensional
word vectors and I've plotted them in 2 dimensions.
So you can see that when you learn a word
embedding - and not just a word embedding,
we've seen for movies, we were able to plot
some movies in 2 dimensions and see how they
relate to each other, and we can do the same
thing for words.
In general, when you have some high cardinality
categorical variable - could be lots of movies,
lots of reviewers, lots of words, or whatever
- you can turn it into a useful lower dimensional
space using this very simple technique of
creating an embedding.
Question: The explanation on how unsupervised
learning was word2vec was pretty smart.
How was it done in GloVe?
Answer: I don't recall how it was done in
GloVe.
I believe it was something similar.
I should mention that both GloVe and word2vec
did not use deep-learning.
They actually tried to create a linear model.
And the reason they did that was they specifically
wanted to create representations which had
these kinds of linear relationships because
they felt this would be a useful characteristic
of these representations.
I'm not even sure if anybody has even tried
to create a similarly useful representation
using a deeper model, or whether it turns
out any better.
Obviously with these linear models, it saves
a lot of computational time as well.
The embeddings, however, even though they
were built using linear models, we can now
use them as inputs to deep models, which is
what we're about to do.
Question: So, Google SyntaxNet, the new model
that just came out, is that the one you were
mentioning before?
Answer: No, I was mentioning word2vec.
Word2vec has been around for 2 or 2.5 years.
SyntaxNet is a whole framework.
Question: I think it might have been Parsey?
That one is the one where it was 97% on NLP
and it also returns parts of speech.
It will tell you, if you give it a sentence
- this is a word, this is an action verb ...
Answer: Parsey McParseface.
All of these word vectors do all of these
things in that high-dimensional space.
So you can see here (swim-swam), there's information
about tense.
It's very easy to create a word vector and
use it to create a part of speech recognizer.
You just need a fairly small labeled corpus
(and it's actually pretty easy to download
a rather large labeled corpus) and build a
simple model that goes from word vector to
part of speech.
There's a really interesting paper, Exploring
the Limits of Language Modeling.
That Parsey McParseface thing got far more
PR than it deserved.
It was not really an advance over the state-of-the-art
language models of the time, but since that
time there have been a lot more interesting
things.
One of the more interesting papers is Exploring
the Limits of Language Modeling, which is
looking at what happens when you take a very,
very, very large dataset and spend s-loads
of Google's money on lots and lots of GPUs
for a very long time.
They have some genuine massive improvements
to the state-of-the-art in language modeling.
In general, when we're talking about language
modeling, we're talking about everything from
"Is this a noun or a verb" to "Is this a happy
sentence or a sad sentence" to "Is this formal
speech or informal speech", and so on and
so forth.
And all those things NLP researchers do, we
can now do super-easily with these embeddings.
[Time: 1.30 hour mark]
Question: Did they use an optimizer Adam to
generate all those latent factors?
Answer: So this uses two techniques.
One of which you know, and one of which you're
about to know.
Convolutional Neural Networks and Recurrent
Neural Networks, specifically a type called
LSTM.
So you can check out this paper to see how
they compare.
Since this time, there has been an even newer
paper which has furthered the state of the
art in language modeling, and it's using a
convolutional neural network.
Right now, CNNs with pre-trained word embeddings
are the state-of-the-art.
So, given that we can now download these pre-trained
word embeddings, that leads us to the question
of why are we using randomly generated word
embeddings when we do our sentiment analysis.
That doesn't seem like a very good idea, and
indeed it is not an even remotely good idea.
You should never do that.
From now on, you should now always use pre-trained
word-embeddings, every time you do NLP.
Over the next few weeks, we will be gradually
be making this easier and easier.
At this stage, it requires slightly less than
a screen of code.
You have to load the embeddings off disk,
create your word vectors, your words and your
word indexes.
And the next thing you have to do - the word
indexes that come from GloVe are going to
be different to the word indexes in your vocabulary.
In our case, 23022 was the word "Bromwell",
in the GloVe case it is probably not the word
"Bromwell".
So this little piece of code is something
that is simply mapping from one index to the
other index.
So this create embedding function (create_emb)
is then going to create an embedding matrix
where the indexes are the indexes in the IMDb
dataset, and the embeddings are the embeddings
from GloVe.
So that's what emb now contains - the GloVe
word vectors indexed according to the IMDb
dataset.
So now I have simply copied and pasted the
previous code and I have added weights equals
pre-trained embeddings; since we think these
weights are pretty good, I've set trainable
to False (weights=[emb], trainable=False).
I won't leave it at False, because we're going
to fine-tune them, but we'll start it at False.
One particular reason that we cannot leave
it at False is that sometimes I have had to
create a random embedding, because sometimes
the word that I looked up in GloVe didn't
exist.
For example, anything that finishes with apostrophe-s,
in GloVe they tokenize that to have the word
and apostrophe-s as separate tokens, but in
IMDb, they were combined into one token, so
all of those things, there aren't vectors
for them.
So I just randomly created embeddings for
anything that I couldn't find in the GloVe
vocabulary.
For now, let's just start using the embeddings
we are given.
We will set this to non-trainable and we will
train a convolutional neural network using
those embeddings for the IMDb task.
After the two epochs, we have 89.8.
Previously, with random embeddings we had
89.5, and the academic state-of-the-art was
88.3.
So we've made significant improvements.
Let's now go ahead and say first layer trainable
is true (model.layers[0].trainable=True),
decrease the learning rate a bit (model.optimizer.lr=1e-4)
and do just one more epoch, and we're now
up to 90.1.
So we got way beyond the academic state-of-the-art
here.
We're kind of cheating because we're now not
just building a model, we're now using a pre-trained
word embedding model that somebody else has
provided for us.
But why would you ever not do that if that
exists?
So you can see that we've had a big jump and
it's only taken us 12 seconds to train this
network.
[Time: 1.35 hour mark]
So we started out with the pre-trained word
embeddings, we set them initially to non-trainable
in order to just train the layers that used
them, waited until that was stable (which
took really 2 epochs), and then we set them
to trainable and did one more little fine-tuning
step.
This kind of approach of these 3 epochs of
training is likely to work for a lot of NLP
stuff that you'll find.
Question: Do you not need to compile the model
after resetting the layer to trainable=True?
Answer: No you don't.
The architecture of the model has not changed
in any way, it's just changed the metadata
attached to it.
There's never any harm in compiling the model.
Sometimes if you forget to compile, it just
continues to use the old model, so best to
err on the side of using it.
Something I thought was pretty cool was during
the week, one of our students here had an
extremely popular post appear all over the
place (I saw it on the front page of Hacker
News) talking about how his company, Quid,
uses deep-learning, I'm very happy to see
with small data.
For those of you that don't know it, Quid
is a very successful start-up that is processing
millions and millions of documents - patents
and things like that - and providing enterprise
customers with really cool visualizations
and interactive tools that lets them analyze
huge datasets.
This is by Ben Bowles, one of our students
here, and he talked about how he compared
three different approaches to NLP classification
tasks, one of which involved some pretty complex
and slow to develop carefully engineered features.
But Model 3 in this example was a convolutional
neural network, so I think this is pretty
cool and I was hoping to talk to Ben about
this piece of work.
Jeremy: Ben, could you give us a little bit
of context about what you were doing in this
project?
Ben: The task is about detecting marketing
language in company descriptions, so it has
a flavor very similar to sentiment analysis.
You have two classes of things, they're kind
of different in some kind of semantic way.
Marketing vs informative.
And you've got some examples here.
One was, "Our patent-pending support system
is engineered and designed to bring comfort
and style" - more marketing, I guess.
"Spatial Scanning software for mobile devices"
is more informative.
The semantics of the marketing language is
like, "Oh, this is exciting!" - there are
certain semantics around which marketing tends
to cluster and I realized that this would
be a nice task for deep-learning.
Jeremy: How were these labeled?
Ben: Basically by a couple of us.
We found some good ones and we found the bad
ones and literally tried it out.
Literally as hacky as you could imagine.
Super, super scrappy.
But it actually ended up being quite useful
for use.
That's the lesson there - sometimes scrappy
gets you most of the way you need.
Think about how you can get your data for
your project - you can just create it.
Jeremy: Exactly.
I love this lesson because when I talk to
big executives, they're all about their 5-year
metadata and data-like repository infrastructure
program, at the end of which maybe they'll
try to get some value out of it.
While start-ups are like, okay what have we
got that we can do by Monday; let's throw
it together and see if it works.
The latter approach is so much better because
by Monday you know if it looks good, you know
which kind of things are important and you
can decide on how much its worth investing
in.
One of the things I wanted to show is your
convolutional neural network did something
pretty neat.
I want to use this same neat trick for our
convolutional neural network, it's a multi-size
CNN.
I mentioned earlier that when I built this
CNN and I tried using a filter size of 5 and
I found it better than 3.
What Ben points out in his blog post is that
there's a neat paper in which they describe
doing something interesting - not just using
one size convolution, but trying a few sized
convolutions.
You can see here is that this is a great use
of the functional API.
[Time: 1.40 mark]
So I haven't exactly used your code, I've
rewritten it a little bit.
Let's try size 3 and size 4 and size 5 convolutional
filters and let's create one big convolutional
filter size 3 and then size 4 and then size
5.
And then for each one, using the functional
API, we'll add MaxPooling, we'll flatten it
and we'll add it to a list of these different
convolutions.
And then at the end we will merge them all
together by simply concatenating them -- so
we'll now have a single vector containing
the result of the 3 and 4 and 5 sized convolutions
(why settle for one!?).
And then let's return that whole model as
a little sub-model, which in Ben's code equaled
"graph".
I assume you called this graph because people
tend to think of these things and call them
a computational graph.
A computational graph is a computation expressed
as a graph of various inputs and outputs.
Once you've got this little multi-layer convolution
layer module, you can stick it inside a standard
sequential model by simply replacing the Convolution1D
and MaxPooling1D piece with graph, where graph
is the concatenated version of all of these
different scales of convolution.
Trying this out, I got a slightly better answer
again, which is 90.63% -- and I hadn't seen
that paper before, so thank you for giving
that great idea.
Jeremy: Did you have anything to add about
this multi-scale convolution idea?
Ben: Not really, other than I think it's super
cool.
I'm still trying to figure out all the ins
and outs of exactly how it works.
In some ways, the implementation is easier
than understanding.
Jeremy: That's exactly right.
In a lot of these things, the math is ridiculously
simple, then you throw it at an SGD and let
it do billions and billions of calculations
in a fraction of a second, and what it comes
up with is hard to grasp.
Question: You are using capital-M Merge in
this example?
Do you want to talk about that?
Answer: Not really.
Ben used capital-M Merge and I just did the
same thing.
Were it me, I would have used small-m merge,
so we'll have to agree to disagree here.
We have a few minutes to talk about something
enormous.
We're going to do a brief introduction to
RNNs and next week week we will do a deep
dive.
Everything we've learned so far about Convolutional
Neural Networks does not necessarily do a
great job of solving a problem like, how would
you model this.
This model has to recognize when you have
a start tag and know to close that tag, but
over a longer period of time that it's in
a weird XML-y comment thing and to know that
it has to finish off that weird XML-y comment
thing.
Which means it has to keep memory about what
happened in the distant past if you're going
to do modeling with a thing that looks like
this.
With that kind of memory, it can handle long-term
dependencies.
Also, think about these two different sentences
("I went to Nepal in 2009", "In 2009, I went
to Nepal").
They both mean, effectively, the same thing,
but in order to realize that, you're going
to have to keep some kind of state that knows
that after this ("In 2009") has been read
in, you're now talking about something that
happened in 2009.
And then you then have to remember all the
way to the end of the sentence when it was
that the thing happened that you did in Nepal.
So we want to create some kind of stateful
representation.
Furthermore, it would be nice (if we're going
to deal with big long pieces of language like
this with a lot of structure) to be able to
handle variable-length sequences - we can
handle some things that might be really long
and some things that might be really short.
These are all things that Convolutional Neural
Networks don't necessarily do all that well.
So we're going to look at something else,
a Recurrent Neural Network, which handles
that kind of thing well.
[Time: 1.45 hour mark]
Here's a great example of a good use of a
Recurrent Neural Network.
At the top here, you can see that there is
a Convolutional Neural Network that is looking
at images of house numbers.
These images are coming from really big Google
StreetView pictures and it has to figure out,
what part of the image should I look at next
in order to figure out the house number.
You can see that there is a little square
box that is scanning through and figuring
I want to look at this piece next.
At the bottom, it's showing you what it's
actually seeing after each time step.
So the thing that is figuring out where to
look next is a Recurrent Neural Network.
It's something that is taking its previous
state and figuring out what should its next
state be.
This kind of model is called an Attentional
Model and it's a really interesting field
of research when it comes to things like very
large images - images which might be too big
for a single Convolutional Neural Network
with our current hardware constraints.
On the left is another great example of a
Recurrent Neural Network, an Android and iOS
text extry system called SwiftKey.
SwiftKey had a post-up a few months ago where
they announced that they had just replaced
their language model with a neural network
of this kind, which basically looked at your
previous words and figured out what word are
you likely to be typing in next, and then
it could predict that word.
A final example - Andrej Karpathy showed a
really cool thing where he was able to generate
random mathematical papers by generating random
LaTeX.
And to generate random LaTeX you have to learn
things like \begin and \end
and these kind of long-term dependencies.
He was able to do that successfully.
So this is a randomly generated piece of LaTeX
which is being created with a Recurrent Neural
Network.
So today I am not going to show you exactly
how it works, I'm going to kind of try and
give you an intuition.
I'm going to start out by showing you how
to think about neural networks as computational
graphs (this is coming back to the idea that
Ben used earlier, computational graphs).
Here is a picture of a single hidden layer
basic neural network.
We can think of it as having an input of size
batch_size and contain width of number of
inputs.
This arrow represents something that we're
doing to that matrix.
Each of the boxes represents a matrix and
each of the arrows represents one or more
things we do to that.
In this case we do a matrix product and then
we throw it through a rectified linear unit.
And then we get a circle - which represents
a matrix, but it's a hidden layer which is
of size batch_size by number of activations.
Number of activations is just - when we created
that dense layer, we would have said "Dense(n",
and that n is some number representing the
number of activations we create.
And then we put that through another operation,
which in this case is a matrix product followed
by a SoftMax.
And the triangle here represents our output
matrix, which is of size batch_size by, if
it's ImageNet, 1,000.
So this is my little way of representing the
computation graph of a basic neural network
with a single hidden layer.
I'm now going to create some slightly more
complex models, but I'm going to slightly
reduce the amount of stuff on the screen.
One thing to note is that batch_size appears
all the time, so I'm going to get rid of it.
So here's the same thing where I've removed
batch_size.
Also the specific activation function, it's
probably reLu everywhere except the last layer
where it's SoftMax, so I can remove that as
well.
[Time: 1.50 hour mark]
So let's now look at what a convolutional
neural network with a single dense hidden
layer would look like.
So we'll have our input, which this time will
be (remember, I've removed batch size) number
of channels by height by width (Input:#channel*h*w),
the operation (we're ignoring the activation
function) is going to be a convolution followed
by a MaxPool (remember, any shape is representing
a matrix).
So that gives us a matrix which will be size
number of filters by height/2 by width/2 [Conv1:#filters*(h/2)*(w/2)],
since we did a MaxPooling.
And then we take that and we Flatten it.
I put Flatten in parantheses because mathematically
Flatten does nothing at all.
Flattening is just telling Keras to think
of it as a vector.
It doesn't actually calculate anything, it
doesn't move anything, it doesn't do anything.
It just says think of it as being a different
shape, that's is why I put it in parantheses.
So then let's take a matrix product (remember,
I'm not putting in the activation functions
anymore).
So that would be our dense layer and gives
us our first fully connected layer which will
be of size number of activations [FC1:#activations]
and then we put that through a final Matrix
product to get an output of size number of
classes [Output:#classes].
So here is how we can represent a convolutional
neural network with a single dense hidden
layer.
Question: What is the number of activations?
Answer: The number of activations is the same
as we had last time.
It is whatever the n was when we wrote Dense(n).
Just like the number of filters is when we
write Convolution2D, we say number of filters,
followed by its size (C2D,n,3)
So I'm going to create a slightly more complex
computation graph, but again I'm going to
slightly simplify what I put on the screen.
This time I'm going to remove all of the layer
operations.
Now that we have removed the activation function,
you can see that in every case we have some
kind of linear thing, either a matrix product
or a convolution, and optionally there might
also be a MaxPool.
So really this is not adding much additional
information, so I'm going to get rid of that
[remove: Convolution; max_pool, (Flatten);
matrix product, Matrix product].
So we're now not showing the layer operations.
Remember, every arrow is representing one
or more layer operations which will generally
be a convolution followed by a matrix product
followed by an activation function, and maybe
there will be a MaxPooling in there as well.
So let's say we wanted to predict the third
word of a 3-word stream based on the previous
2 words.
Now there's all kinds of ways we can do this,
but here's one interesting way, which you
will now recognize you could do with Keras'
functional API.
Which is we could take Word-1 input, and that
could be either one-hot encoded thing, in
which case its size would be vocab size, or
it could be an embedding.
Doesn't really matter either way.
We then stick that through a layer operation
to get a matrix output which is our first
fully connected layer [FC1:#activations].
And this thing here we could then take and
then put through another layer operation,
but this time we could also add in the Word-2
input, either of vocab size or the embedding
of it.
Put that through a layer operation of its
own.
Then when we have two arrows coming in together,
that represents a merge.
A merge could either be done as a sum or a
concat.
I'm not going to say one is better than the
other; they're two ways that we can take two
input vectors and combine them together.
So now, at this point we have the input from
Word-2 (after sticking that through a layer),
we have the input from Word-1 (after sticking
that through 2 layers), merge them together
and stick that through another layer to get
our output, which we could then compare to
Word-3 and try to train that to recognize
Word-3 from Word 1 and Word 2.
You could try this.
You could try to build this network from some
corpus you find online and see how it goes.
Pretty obviously then you could bring it up
another level to try to predict the fourth
word of a three-word string, using Word-1
and Word-2 and Word-3.
[Time: 1.55 hour mark]
The reason I'm doing it in this way is each
time I'm going through another layer operation
- bringing in Word-1 and going through a layer
operation, bringing in Word-2 and going through
a layer operation, bringing in Word-3 and
going through a layer operation - is I am
collecting state.
Each of these things has the ability to capture
state about all of the words that have come
so far and the order in which they've arrived.
By the time I get to Word-4, this matrix has
had the opportunity to learn what does it
need to know about the previous words' orderings
and how they're connected to each other and
so forth, in order to predict this fourth
word.
We're actually capturing state here.
It's important to note we have not yet built
a model in Keras which has input coming in
anywhere other than the first layer, but there's
no reason we can't.
One of you asked a great question earlier
-- could we use this to bring in metadata,
like the speed a car was going, to add in
the the convolutional neural network's image
data.
I said, yes we can.
In this case, we're doing the same thing;
we're bringing in an additional words worth
of data.
Each time you see a convolutional arrow coming
in, that represents a merge operation.
So here's a perfectly reasonable way of trying
to predict the fourth word from the previous
three words.
This leads to a really interesting question.
What if instead we bring in our Word-1 and
then we had a layer operation in order to
create a hidden state.
And that would be enough to predict Word-2.
And then to predict Word-3 could we just do
a layer operation and generate itself, and
then that could be used to predict Word-3.
And run it again to predict Word-4, and again
to predict Word-5.
This is called an RNN.
Everything you see here is exactly the same
structurally as I've shown before.
The colored-in areas represent matrices and
the arrows represent layer operations.
One of the really interesting things about
an RNN is each of these arrows (here you see
3 arrows), there's only one weight matrix
attached to those.
In other words, it's the equivalent thing
of saying every time you see an arrow from
a circle to a circle, those two weight matrices
have to be exactly the same.
Everytime you see an arrow from a rectangle
to a circle, those 3 matrices have to be exactly
the same.
Finally, you've got an arrow from a circle
to a triangle, and that weight matrix is separate.
The idea being that if you have a word coming
in and being added to some state, why would
you want to treat it differently depending
on whether its the first word in a string
or the third word in a string, given that
generally speaking, we kind of split up strings
pretty much at random anyway.
One of the nice things about it going back
to itself is that you can very clearly see
there is one layer operation (one weight matrix)
for input-to-hidden, one for hidden-to-hidden
(circle-to-circle), and one for hidden-to-output
(circle-to-triangle).
We're going to talk about that in a lot more
detail next week.
For now, I'm going to quickly show you something
in the last minute.
We can train something which takes, for example,
the text of all the texts of Nietzsche.
Here's a bit of his text, I just read it in
here.
We could split it up, go through the whole
text and grab every sequence of length 40.
Then I've created an RNN.
It's goal is to take the sentences which represents
the indexes from i to i+40 and predict the
sentence from i+1 to i+40+1.
So every string of length maxlen, I'm trying
to predict the string one word after that.
[Time: 2 hour mark]
I can take that now and create a model, which
has an LSTM (an LSTM is a kind of Recurrent
Neural Network, we'll talk about it next week),
starts with an embedding.
Then I can train that by passing in my sentences,
and my sentence one character later.
Then I can say let's try and generate 300
characters by building a prediction - what
do you think the next character will be.
I have to see it with something, so I seeded
it with something very Nietzsche-n, "ethics
is a basic foundation of all that".
After training it for only a few seconds,
I get "ethics is a basic foundation of all
thatscrriets sdi ,s lrrbmh ..."
This Nietzsche corpus is slightly annoying
- it has carriage returns after every line,
and it's got some pretty hideous formatting.
So then I train it for another 30 seconds,
and it's getting to the point where it kind
of understands punctuation and spacing.
And then I train it for 640 seconds and it's
starting to create real words.
And then I train it for another 640 seconds.
Interestingly, each section of Nietzsche starts
with a numbered section which looks exactly
like this.
It's even starting to learn to close its quotation
marks.
It's also learned that at the start of a chapter
it always has three blank lines, so it's learned
to start chapters.
After another 640 seconds and another 640
seconds, it's actually gotten to a point where
its saying some things which are so obscure
and difficult to understand it could really
be Nietsche.
These car RNN models are fun and all, but
the reason that this is interesting is that
we are showing that we only provided a small
amount of text and it was able to generate
text out here, because it has state, it has
recurrence.
What this means is that we could use this
to generate something like SwiftKey, where
as you're typing, it's saying this is the
next thing you're going to type.
I'd like you to think about, during the week,
whether this is likely to help our IMDb sentiment
model or not, that will be an interesting
thing to talk about.
Next week we will look into the details of
how RNNs work.