So one of the things I wanted to talk about
(this really came up when I was looking at
the survey responses) what is different about
how we're trying to teach this course and
how will it impact you as participants in
this course.
Really we're trying to teach this course in
a very different way from the way most teaching
is done, at least most teaching in the United
States.
Rachel and I are both very keen fans of David
Perkins, who has this wonderful book called
"Making Learning Whole, How Seven Principles
of Teaching can Transform Education".
We are trying to put these principles in practice
in this course.
I'll give you a little anecdote from the book
to give you a sense of how this works.
If you were to learn baseball the way that
math is taught, you would first learn about
the shape of a parabola.
Then you would learn about the materials science
design behind stitching baseballs, and so
forth.
And 20 years later, after you completed your
PhD and post-doc, you'd be taken to your first
baseball game and you'd be introduced to the
rules of baseball.
And then 10 years later, you might get to
hit.
The way that in practice baseball is taught
is we take a kid down to the baseball diamond
and we say, "These people are playing baseball,
would you like to play?"
And they say, "Yea, sure I would."
"Okay, stand here, I'm going to throw this.
Hit it, now run."
Good, you're playing baseball.
So that's why we started our first class with,
"Here are 7 lines of code you can run to do
deep-learning."
Not just to do deep-learning but to do image
classification on any dataset as long as you
structure it in the right way.
So this means you will very often be in the
situation (we've heard a lot of your questions
about this during the week); Gosh, there's
a whole lot of details I don't understand.
Like this fine-tuning thing.
What is fine-tuning?
And the answer is we haven't told you yet.
It's a thing you do in order to do effective
image classification in deep-learning.
We're going to start from the top and gradually
work our way down, and down, and down.
The reason that you are going to want to learn
the additional level of detail is so that
when you get to the point where you want to
do something that no one's done before, you'll
know how to go into that detail and create
something that does what you want.
We're going to keep going down a level and
down a level and down a level through the
hierarchy of software libraries, through the
hierarchy of the way computers work, through
the hierarchy of the algorithms and the math,
but only at the speed that's necessary to
let's make a better model, or let's make a
model that can do something we couldn't do
before.
Those will always be our goals.
So it's very different.
I don't know if anybody's been reading the
Yoshua Bengio, Ian Goodfellow and Aaron Courville
book (www.deeplearningbook.org), which is
a great mathematical deep learning book.
It literally starts with 5 chapters of everything
you need to know about probability, everything
you need to know about calculus, everything
you need to know about linear algebra, everything
you need to know about optimizations, and
so forth.
I don't know that in the whole book, there's
ever actually a point where it says, here
is how you do deep-learning.
Even if you read the whole thing.
I've read 2/3 of it.
It's a really good math book.
Anybody who's interested in understanding
the math of deep-learning, I would strongly
recommend.
But it's kind of the opposite of how we're
teaching this course.
So if you often find yourself thinking, I
don't really know what's going on, that's
fine.
But I also want you to always be thinking
about, okay how can I figure out a bit more
about what's going on.
So we're trying to let you experiment.
Generally speaking, the assignments during
the week are trying to give you enough room
to find a way to dig in into what you've learnt
and do a little bit more.
Make sure you can do what you've seen and
also that you can learn a little bit more
about it.
So you are all coders.
So you are all expected to look at that first
notebook, and look at what are the inputs
to every one of those cells, what are the
outputs from every one of those cells.
How is it that the output can be used as the
input to that cell, why is this transformation
going on.
This is why we did not tell you how do you
use Kaggle CLI, how do you prepare a submission
in the correct format, because we wanted you
to see if you could figure it out and also
to leverage the community that we have to
ask questions when you're stuck.
[Time: 5 minute mark]
Being stuck and failing is terrific because
it means you have found some limit of your
knowledge or your current expertise.
You can then think really hard, read lots
of documentation and ask the rest of the community
until you are no longer stuck.
At which point you now know something you
didn't know before.
So that's the goal.
Asking for help is a key part of this, so
there is a whole wiki page called "How to
ask for Help".
It's really important, and so far about half
the times I have seen people ask for help,
there is not enough information for your colleagues
to really help you effectively.
So when people point you at this page, it's
not because they're trying to be a pain, it's
because they're saying I want to help you
but you haven't given me enough information.
So, in particular, what have you tried so
far.
What did you expect to happen?
What actually happened?
What do you think might be going on?
What have you tried to test this out?
And tell us everything you can about your
computer and your software?
Show us screenshots, error messages, your
code.
The better you get at asking for help, the
more enjoyable experience you're going to
have because continually you'll find your
problems can be solved very quickly and you
can move on.
There was a terrific recommendation from the
head of Google Brain, Vincent Vanhoucke, on
a Reddit AMA a few weeks ago where he said
he tells everybody in his team, if you're
stuck work at it yourself for half an hour
(you have to work at it yourself for half
an hour).
If you're still stuck, you have to ask for
help from somebody else.
The idea being that you are always making
sure that you try everything you can, but
you're also never wasting your time when somebody
else can help you.
I think that's a really good suggestion, so
maybe you can think about this half an hour
rule yourself.
I wanted to highlight a great example of a
really successful how to ask for help a great
example of a really successful how to ask
for help.
Who asked this particular question?
That was really well done, really nice.
What's your background before taking this
class, maybe you can introduce yourself quickly.
I graduated from USF two years ago with a
bachelor's in Data Science.
You can see here that he explained here what
he's going to do, what happened last time,
what error message he got.
He's got a screenshot to show you want he
typed and what he came back.
He shows what resources he's going to use,
what these resources say and so forth.
Did you get your question answered?
Kicho says, yes, Rachel emailed me.
Okay, great.
Rachel says the question was so clear, it
was easy to answer.
As you might have noticed, the wiki is rapidly
coming out with some great information, so
please start exploring it.
You'll see on the left-hand side, there is
a recent changes section and you can see every
day there's lots of people who've been contributing
lots of things, so it's continually improving.
There's some great kind of diagnostic sections.
If you are trying to diagnose something which
is not covered and you solve it, please add
your solution to this diagnostic section.
One of the things I lvoed seeing today was
Tom
was asking a question about how fine-tuning
works, we talked about the answers and then
he went ahead and created a very small little
wiki page.
There's not much information there, but there's
more than there used to be.
This is exactly what we want.
You can even see in the places where he wasn't
quite sure, he put some question marks.
So now somebody else can go back and edit
his wiki page, and Tom's going to come back
tomorrow and say now I've got even more questions
answered.
This is the kind of approach where you're
going to learn a lot.
[Time: 10 minute mark]
This is another great example of something
that I think is very helpful.
Melissa, who we heard from earlier, went ahead
and told us all, Here is my understanding
of the 17 steps necessary to complete the
things we were asked to do this week.
So this is great for Melissa to make sure
she understands it correctly, but everybody
else can say that's a really handy resource
that we can draw on as well.
There are 718 messages in Slack in a single
channel.
That's way too much to expect to use this
as a learning resource, so this is my suggestion
as to how you might want to be careful of
how you use Slack.
I wanted to spend maybe quite a lot of time
talking about the resources that are available,
because I feel like if we get that out now
then we're all going to speed along a lot
more quickly.
Thanks for your patience as we talk about
some non-deep-learning stuff.
We expect the vast majority of learning to
happen outside of class.
In fact, if we go back and finish off our
survey, I know that one of the questions asked
about that.
How much time are you willing to commit most
weeks to this class?
And the majority was 8-15 hours.
Some are 15-30, and a small number are Less
than 8.
If you're in the Less than 8 group, I understand
that's not something you can probably change.
If you had more time, you'd put in more time.
So if you're in the Less than 8 group, think
about how you want to prioritize what you
want to get out of this course.
Be aware that it's not really designed that
you're going to be able to do everything in
less than 8 hours a week, so maybe make more
use of the forums and the wiki and focus your
assignments during the week on the stuff that
you're most interested in.
Don't worry too much if you don't feel like
you're getting everything because you have
less time available.
For those of you in the 15-30 group, I really
hope that you'll find that you're getting
a huge amount out of the time that you're
putting in.
Something I'm glad I asked (because I found
it really helpful) was "How much of the material
from Lesson 1 was new to you?"
And for half of you, the answer is Most of
it.
And for well over half of you, Most of it
or Nearly all of it.
If you're one of the people that I've spoken
to during the week who's said, "Holy shit,
that was a firehose of information.
I feel kind of overwhelmed, kind of excited,"
you are amongst friends.
Remember, during the week there are about
100 of you going through this same journey.
So if you want to catch up with some people
during the week and have a coffee and talk
more about the class, or join a study group
here at USF, or if you're from the South Bay,
find some people from the South Bay, I would
strongly suggest doing that.
So for example, if you're in Menlo Park, you
could create a Menlo Park Slack Channel and
put out a message, "Hey, anybody else in Menlo
Park availabe on Wednesday night, I'd like
to get together and maybe do some peer programming
or whatever."
For some of you, not very much of it was new
and for those of you, I do want to make sure
that you feel comfortable pushing ahead, trying
out your own projects and so forth.
Basically in the last lesson, what we learned
was a pretty standard data science computing
stack - AWS, JuPyteR notebook, a bit of Numpy,
Bash.
This is all stuff that regardless of what
kind of data science you do, you're going
to be seeing a lot more of (if you stick in
this area).
These are all very, very useful things.
Those of that who have spent some time in
this field will have seen most of it before.
Hopefully that is useful background.
So last week we were really looking at the
basic foundations, computing foundations necessary
for data science more generally, and for big
learning more particularly.
This week, we're going to do something very
similar, but we're going to be looking at
the key algorithm pieces.
[TIme: 15 minute mark]
So in particular, we're going to go back and
say, "Hey, what did we actually do last week,
and why did that work, and how did that work."
For those of you who don't have much algorithmic
background around machine learning, this is
going to be the same firehouse of information
as last week was for those of you who don't
kind of have a software, Bash, AWS background.
So again, if there's a lot of information,
don't worry.
This is being recorded.
There are all the resources during the week.
So the key this is to come away with an understanding
of what are the key pieces being discussed.
Why are those pieces important?
What are they doing (even if you don't understand
the detail).
So if at any point you're thinking, okay Jeremy's
talking about activation functions.
I have no idea what he just said about what
an activation function is, or why I should
care.
Please go on to the InClass Slack Channel,
and probably @Rachel I don't know what Jeremy's
talking about at all; Rachel's got a microphone
and she can let me know.
Or else put up your hand and ask.
So I do want to make sure you guys feel very
comfortable asking questions.
I have done this class now once before because
I did it for the Skype students last night.
I've heard a few of the questions already,
so hopefully I can cover some things that
are likely to come up.
Before we look at digging in to what's going
on, the first thing we're going to do is see
how do we do the basic homework assignment
from last week.
So the basic homework assignment from last
week was can you enter the Kaggle Dogs and
Cats Redux competition.
So how many of you managed to submit something
to that competition and get some kind of result?
Okay, that's not bad.
So for those of you who haven't yet, keep
trying during this week and use all of those
resources I showed you because quite a few
of your colleagues have done it successfully
and therefore we can all help you.
And I can show you how I did it.
The basic idea here
is we have to download the data to a directory,
so to do that I just use "kg download" after
using the "kg config" command.
kg is part of the Kaggle CLI and Kaggle CLI
can be installed by typing "pip install kaggle-cli".
This works fine without any changes if you're
using our AWS instances and setup scripts.
In fact, it's fine if you're using Anaconda
pretty much anywhere.
If you're not doing any of those two things,
you may have found this step more challenging.
But once it's installed it's as simple as
saying "kg config", with your username, password
and competition name (kg config -g -u userName
-p password -c competitionName).
When you put in the competition name, you
can find that out by just going to the Kaggle
website and you'll see that when you go to
the comptetion in the URL, it has here a name.
So just copy and paste that, that's the competion
name.
kaggle-cli is a script that somebody created
in their spare time and didn't spend a lot
of time on it.
There's no error-handling, there's no checking,
or anything.
So for example, if you haven't gone to Kaggle
and accepted the competition rules, then attempting
to run "kg download" will not give you an
error, it will create a zip file that actually
contains the contents of the Kaggle webpage
saying, Please accept the competition rules.
So for those of you that had to unzip that,
and it said it's not a zipfile.
If you go ahead and cat that, you'll see it's
not a zipfile it's a HTML file.
So this is pretty common with recent-ish data
science tools, and particularly with deep-learning
stuff.
A lot of it's pretty new, it's pretty rough
and you really have to expect to do a lot
of debugging.
It's very different than using Excel or PhotoShop
or something.
So when I said "kg download", it created a
test.zip and a train.zip, so I went ahead
and I unzipped both of those things, that
created a test and a train, and they contain
a whole bunch of files, cat.1.jpg, and so
forth.
[Time: 20 minute mark]
So the next thing I did to make my life easier
was I made a list of what I belived I had
to do (I find life much easier with a to-do
list).
I need to create a validation set, I need
to create a sample, I need to move my cats
into a cats directory, my dogs into a dogs
directory, I'm going to have to fine-tune
and train, I then need to submit.
I went ahead then and created Markdown headings
for these things and started filling them
out.
So Create Validation Set and Sample.
A very handy thing in JuPyteR notebook is
you can create a cell that starts with a "%" (percent
sign), and that allows you to type magic commands.
There are lots of magic commands, all kinds
of useful things.
They do include things like "%cd", and "%mkdir"
and so forth.
Another cool thing you can do is you can use
the "!" (exclamation mark) and then type any
Bash command.
The nice thing about doing this stuff in a
notebook rather than Bash is that you've got
a record of everything you did.
So if you want to go back and do it again,
you can.
If you make a mistake, you can go back and
figure it out.
This kind of reproducible research is very
highly recommended.
I try to do everything in a single notebook
so I can go back and fix the problems that
I always make.
Here you can see I've gone into the directory,
I've created my validation set.
I then used 3 lines of Python to go ahead
and grab all of the jpg file names [g=glob('*.jpg')],
create a random permutation of them [np.random.permutation(g)].
And so then the first 2000 of that random
permutation are 2000 random files, and then
I move them into my validation directory,
valid.
I did the exact same thing for my sample,
but rather than moving them, I copied them.
And then I did that for my sample training
and my sample validation, and that was enough
to create my validation set and sample.
The next thing I had to do was move all my
cats into my cats directory and my dogs into
my dogs directory.
Which was as complex as typing "%mv cat.*.jpg
cats/" and " mv dog.*.jpg dogs/".
And the cool thing is that now that I've done
that I can just copy and paste the 7 lines
of code from our previous lesson, these lines
of code are totally unchanged.
I added one more line of code which was save_weights.
Once you've trained something, it's a great
idea to save the weights so that you don't
have to train it again.
You can always go back later and say load_weights.
So I now had a model which predicted cats
and dogs through my Redux competition.
My final step was to submit it to Kaggle.
Kaggle tells us exactly what they expect.
The way they do that is by showing us a sample
of the submission file.
And the sample shows us that they expect an
id column and a label column.
The id is the file number.
So if you have a look at the test set, you'll
see everyone's got a number.
So it's expecting to get
the number of the file along with your probability.
So you have to figure out how to take your
model and create something of that form.
This is clearly something that you're going
to be doing a lot, so once I figured out how
to do it, I actually created a method to do
it in one step.
So I'm going to go and show you the method
I wrote.
So I've got this utils module that I usually
kind of tuck everything in, but I'm going
to put this in my vgg module (vgg16.py).
There's a few ways you can possibly do this.
Basically you know you have a way of grabbing
a mini-batch of data at a time, or a mini-batch
of predictions at a time.
So one thing you could do would be to grab
your mini-batch of size 64, you grab your
64 predictions and you just keep appending
them, 64 at a time to an array until eventually
you have your 12500 test images, all with
a prediction, in an array.
That is actually a perfectly valid way to
do it.
How many people solved it using that kind
of approach?
Not many of you.
That's interesting, but works perfectly well.
[Time: 25 minute mark]
Those of you who didn't (I guess) either asked
on the forum or read the documentation and
discovered there's a very handy thing in Keras
called predict_generator.
And what predict_generator does is it lets
you send in a bunch of batches (something
we created with get_batches) and it will run
the predictions on every one of those batches
and return them all in a single array.
So that's what we want to do.
If you read the Keras documentation (which
you should do very often), you will find out
that predict_generator generally will give
you the labels but not the probabilities (cat
1, dog 0).
In this case, for this competition, they told
us that they want probabilities, not labels.
So instead of calling the get_batches which
we wrote; here is the get_batches we wrote;
you can see all it's doing is it's calling
something else which is flow_from directory.
To get predict_generator to give you probabilities
instead of classes, you have to pass in an
extra argument, which is class_mode= and rather
than "catgorical", you have to say "none".
So in my case, I actually modified get_batches
to take an extra argument, which was "class_mode".
And then in my test mode that I created, I
then added class_mode="none".
And so then I could call model.predict_generator
passing in my batches, and that is going to
give me everything I need.
So once I do, I can say vgg.test, pass in
my test directory, pass in my batch size.
That returns two things, it returns the predictions
and it returns the batches.
I can then use batches.filenames to grab the
filenames because I need the filenames in
order to grab the IDs.
So that, looks like this.
There's a few predictions, there's a few filenames.
Now one thing interesting, at least for the
first 5 is the probabilities are all 1's and
0's, rather than .6, .8, and so forth.
We're going to talk about why that is in just
a moment.
For now, it is what it is.
It's not doing anything wrong, it really thinks
that that's the answer.
Because Kaggle wants something which is isDog,
we grab the second column from this, and the
numbers from this, paste them together as
columns and send that across.
So here is grabbing the first column from
the predictions, call it "isdog".
Here is grabbing from the 8th character until
the dot in filenames, turning it into an integer
to get my IDs.
Numpy has something called stack which lets
you put 2 columns next to each other.
So here is my IDs and my probabilities.
And then Numpy lets you save that as a CSV
file using savetxt.
You can now either ssh to your AWS instance
and use "kg submit", or my preferred technique
is to use a handly little iPython thing called
FileLink.
If you type FileLink and pass in a file that
is on your server, it gives you a little URL
like this, which I can click on and it downloads
it to my computer.
And so now on my computer I can go to Kaggle
and I can submit it in the usual way.
I prefer that because it lets me find out
if there's any error messages, or if there's
anything going wrong on Kaggle, I can see
what's happening.
So as you can see, rerunning what we learnt
last time to submit something to Kaggle really
requires just a little bit of coding to just
creat the submission file, a little bit of
Bash scripting to move things to the right
place, and rerunning the 7 lines of code,
the actual deep-learning itself is incredibly
straightforward.
Here's where it gets interesting.
When I submitted (my 1's and 0's) to Kaggle,
the first thing I submitted was isCat rather
than isDog, so that put me in last place.
[Time: 30 minute mark]
Then when I was putting in 1's and 0's, I
was in 110th place, which is still not that
great.
Now the funny thing was I was pretty confident
that my model was doing well because the validation
set for my model told me that my accuracy
was 97.5%.
I'm pretty confident that the people are not
all of them doing better than that.
So I thought something weird's going on.
So that's a good time to figure out what does
this number mean?
What is 12, what is 17?
So let's go and find out.
It says here that it is a LogLoss, so if we
go to Evaluation, we can find out what LogLoss
is, and here is the definition of LogLoss.
LogLoss is known in Keras as binary entropy
or categorical entropy.
You'll actually find it very familiar because
every single time we've been creating
the model, when we compile the model we have
been using categorical_crossentropy.
So it's probably a good time for us to find
out what this is.
The short answer is that it's this mathematical
function.
But let's dig into this a little bit more
and find out what's going on.
I would strongly recommend that when you want
to figure out how something works, you whip
out a spreadsheet.
Spreadsheets are my favorite tool for doing
small scale data analysis.
They are among the least well-utilized tools
among professional data scientists.
Which I find really surprising because back
when I was in consulting, everybody used them
for everything.
They were the most over-used tool.
So what I've done here is I've gone ahead
and created a little column of isCats and
isDogs, and a column of possible predictions.
And then I've gone in and I've typed in the
formula from that Kaggle page.
And so here it is.
It's the truthLabel times logOfThePrediction
minus (1-truthLabel) times log(1-prediction).
Now if you think about it, the truth label
is always 1 or 0, so this is probably more
understood using an if function.
It's exactly the same thing.
Rather than multiplying by 1 and 0, let's
use an if function.
If it's a cat, then take the log of the prediction.
Otherwise, take log of (1-prediction).
Now this is hopefully pretty intuitive.
If it's the cat and your prediction is really
high, we're taking the log of that and getting
a small number.
If it's not a cat, and our prediction is really
low, then we will take the log of 1 minus
that.
So you can kind of get a sense of it by looking
here.
Here's like a non-cat, which we thought was
a non-cat, and therefore we end up with 1
minus that, it's a low number.
Here's a cat which we're pretty confident
isn't a cat, so here is log of that.
Notice this is all with a negative sign in
the front just to make it so that smaller
numbers are better.
So this is LogLoss or binary or categorical
crossentropy.
And this is where we find out what's going
on because I'm now going to go and say well
hat did I submit.
I submitted predictions that were all 1's
and 0's.
What if I submit 1's and 0's.
Ouch.
We're taking logs of 1's and 0's.
That's no good.
So Kaggle's been pretty nice not to return
just an error.
I actually know why this happens because I
wrote this functionality on Kaggle.
Kaggle modifies it by a tiny bit, like .0001,
just to make sure it doesn't die.
So if you say 1, it actually treats it as
.999.
If you say 0, it treats it as .0001.
So our incredibly over-confident model is
getting massively penalized for that over-confidence.
So what would be better to do would be, instead
of sending off 1's and 0's, why not send across
actual probabilities you think are reasonable.
[Time: 35 minute mark]
So in my case, what I did was I added a line
which was Numpy clip (np.clip) and clip it
to .05 and .95.
So anything less than .05 becomes .05 and
anything greater than .95 becomes .95.
And then I tried submitting that, and that
moved me from 100th place to 40th place.
Suddenly I was in the top half.
So the goal of this week was to try and get
in the top half of the competition and that's
all you had to do, run a single epoch and
realize with this evalution function you need
to be submitting things that aren't 1's and
0's.
So
probably I should have used (and I'd be interested
to try this tomorrow) for resubmission, I
probably should have done .025 and .975 because
I know that my accuracy on the validation
set was .975.
So that's probably the probability that I
should have used.
I would need to think about it more though.
Because it's a non-linear loss function, is
it better to under-estimate how confident
you are, or over-estimate how confident you
are?
In the end, I said, it's about 97.5 and I
have a feeling that being over-confident might
be a bad thing because the shape of the function,
so I'll just be a little bit on the tame side.
I then tried .02 and .98 and I did actually
get a slightly better answer.
I actually got a little bit better than that
in the end.
This afternoon, I ran a couple more epochs
just to see what would happen and that got
me to 24th.
So I'll show you how you can get to 24th position,
and it's incredibly simple.
You take these two lines here vgg.fit and
vgg.model.save_weights, and copy and paste
them a bunch of times.
And you can see I saved the weights under
a different filename each time, just so that
I could always go back and use a model that
I created earlier.
Something that we'll talk about more in the
class later is that after 2 epochs, I changed
my learning rate from .1 to .01, just because
I happen to know that this is often a good
idea.
I haen't tried it without doing that.
I suspect it might be just as good or even
better, but that was just something I tried.
So interestingly by the time I run 4 epochs,
my accuracy is 98.3%.
That would have been 2nd place in the original
Cats and Dogs competition.
So you can see it doesn't take much to get
really good results.
And each one of these took 10 minutes to run
on my AWS P2 instance.
The original Cats and Dogs used a different
evaluation function which was just accuracy.
They changed it for the Redux one to use LogLoss,
which makes it a bit more interesting.
The reason I just didn't say nb_epoch=4 is
that I really wanted to save the results after
each epoch under a different weights filename.
Just in case at some point it overfit a bit,
I could always go back and use one that I
got in the middle.A
In this case, we have added a single linear
layer to the end (we're going to learn a lot
about this).
And so we actually are not training very many
parameters.
My guess would be that in this case we could
run as many epochs as we like and it would
probably keep getting better and better until
it eventually levels off.
That would be my guess.
[Time: 40 minute mark]
So I wanted to talk about what are these probabilities.
One way to do that, and also to talk about
how can you make this model better, is anytime
I build a model and I think about how to make
it better, my first step is to draw a picture.
Data scientists don't draw enough pictures.
Everything from printing out the first 5 lines
of your array to see what it looks like to
drawing complex plots.
For computer vision, you can draw lots of
pictures because we're classifying pictures.
I've given you some tips here about what I
think are super-useful things to visualize.
So when I want to find out why my Kaggle submission
is 110th place
Every time I build a model and think about
how to make it better, I run my standard 5
steps.
The steps are lets look at a few examples
of images we got right; let's look at a few
examples of images we got wrong; let's look
at some of the cats we felt were the most
cat-like, some of the dogs we felt were the
most dog-like, and vice-versa; some of the
cats we were most wrong about, some of the
dogs we were most wrong about; and then finally
some of the most cats and dogs that are model
is most unsure about.
This little bit of code I suggest you keep
around somewhere because this is a super useful
thing to do any time you do image recognition.
So the first thing I did was I loaded my weights
back up (just to make sure they were there)
just to make sure they were there from my
very first epoch.
And I used my vgg.test method I showed you
that I created.
This time I passed in my validation set, not
the test set, because the validation set I
know the correct answer.
So then from the batches I can get the correct
labels and I can get the filenames.
I then grab the probabilities and the class
predictions, and that then allowed me to do
the 5 things I just mentioned.
So here's #1 - a few correct labels at random.
np.where(preds==labels)[0], numpy where the
predictions are equal to the labels.
permutation(correct[:n_view], a random permutation
and grab the first 4, and then plot them by
index.
So here are 4 examples of things that we got
right.
Not suprisingly this cat looks like a cat
and this dog looks like a dog.
Here are four things we got wrong.
It's kind of interesting.
You can see here a very black underexposed
thing on a bright background.
Here is something that is on a totally unusual
angle.
Here is somethign that is so curled up you
can't see its face.
Here is something you can't see its face either.
So this gives me a sense of the things it's
getting wrong, it's reasonable to get those
things wrong.
If you looked at this and they were really
obvious cats and dogs, you would think there's
something wrong with your model.
But in this case, the things it's finding
hard are genuinely hard.
Here are some cats that we felt very sure
are cats.
Here are some dogs we felt very sure were
dogs.
Question: The weights you're saving, are those
ImageNet weights or the ones we trained on
Cats and Dogs?
Answer: So these weights, "results/ft1.h5",
the "ft" stands for fine-tune.
As you can see here, I saved my weights after
I did my fine-tuning, so these are for Cats
and Dogs.
Question: In the fine-tuning are you just
training the last layer?
Answer: Yes, I'm just trainng the last layer.
We're not talking about that yet.
We just used the finetune command, and later
today we're going to learn about what that
does.
These, I think, are the most interesting.
Here are the images we were most confident
were cats, but they're actually dogs.
And you can see, well here's one that is only
50x60 pixels, that's very difficult.
Here's one that is almost totally in front
of a person and is also standing upright,
that's difficult because it's unusual.
This one is very white and is totally from
the front, that's quite difficult.
This one, I'm guessing the color of the floor
and the color of the fur are nearly identical.
So again, this makes senses.
These do look genuinely difficult and so if
we want to do really well in this competition,
we want to think about should we start building
some models of very very small images, because
we now know that sometimes Kaggle gives us
50x50 images, which are going to be very difficult
for us to deal with.
[Time: 45 minute mark]
Here are some pictures that we were actually
very confident were dogs, but they're actually
cats.
Again, not being able to see the face seems
like a common problem.
And then finally, here's some examples that
we were most uncertain about.
Notice that the most uncertain are still not
very uncertain, they're still nearly 1 or
nearly 0.
So why is that?
We will learn in a moment about exactly what
is going on from a mathematical point of view
when we calculate these things, but the short
answer is the probabilities that come out
of a deep learning network are not probabilities
in any statistical sense of the term.
So this is not actually saying that there
is 1 chance out of a 100,000 that this is
a dog.
It's only a probability from a mathe mathematical
point of view.
In math, a probability means between 0 and
1, and all of the possibilities add up to
1.
It's not a probability in a sense that this
actually tells you how often this is going
to be right, this is going to be wrong.
So for now, just be aware of that.
When we talk about these probabilities that
come out of neural network training, you can't
interpret them in any kind of intuitive way.
We will learn about how to create better probabilities
down the track.
Every time you do another epoch, your network
is going to get more and more confident.
This is why when I loaded the weights, I loaded
the weights from the very first epoch.
If I'd loaded the weights from the last epoch,
they all would have been 1's and 0's.
So this is just something to be aware of.
So hopefully you can all go back and get great
results on the Kaggle competition.
Even though I'm going to share all this, you
will learn a lot more by trying to do it yourself,
and only referring to this when and if you're
stuck.
If you do get stuck, rather than copying and
pasting my code, find out what I used and
then go to the Keras documentation and read
about it, and then try and write that line
of code without looking at mine.
The more you can do that, the more you'll
think I can do this, I understand how to do
this myself.
Just some suggestions, it's entirely up to
you.
Okay, let's move on.
I wanted to show you one other thing, which
is the last part of the homework was redo
this on a different dataset.
And so, I decided to grab the State Farm Distracted
Driving competition.
The Kaggle State Farm Distracted Driving competition
has pictures of people in 10 different types
of distracted driving, ranging from drinking
coffee to changing the radio station.
I wanted to show you how I entered this competition.
It took me 1/4 hour to enter the competition.
All I did was I duplicated my Dogs and Cats
redux notebook and then I started re-running
everything.
But in this case, it was even easier because
when you download the State Farm competition
data, they have already put it into directories,
one for each type of distracted driving, which
I was delighted to discover.
If I type "tree -d" that shows you my directory
structure.
You can see in the directory train, it already
had
the 10 directories, so I can skip that whole
section.
So I only had to create the validation and
sample set.
If all I wanted to do was enter the competition,
I wouldn't have even had to have done that.
I won't go through it, it's basically exactly
the same code I had before to create my validation
set and sample.
I deleted all of the bits which moved things
into separate sub-folders.
I then used exactly the same 7 lines of code
as before, and that was basically done.
I'm not getting good accuracy yet, I don't
know why.
So I'm going to have to actually figure out
what's going on with this.
But as you can see, this general approach
works for any kind of image classification.
There's nothing specific about Cats and Dogs.
So you now have a very general tool in your
toolbox.
And all of the stuff I showed you about visualizing
the errors and stuff, you can use all that
as well.
So maybe when you're done you can try this
[Time: 50 minute mark]
Question: Would this work for CT scans and
cancer?
Answer: I can tell you that the answer is
yes because I've done it.
My previous company I created was something
called Enlitic, which was the first deep-learning
for medical diagnostics company.
And the first thing I did with 4 of my staff
was we downloaded the National Lung Screening
Trial Data, which is 1000 examples of people
with cancer, CT scans of their lungs; and
5000 people without cancer, CT scans of their
lungs.
We did the same thing, we took ImageNet, we
fine-tuned ImageNet, but in this case instead
of Cats and Dogs we had malignant tumor vs
non-malignant tumor.
We then took the result of that and saw how
accurate it was, and we discovered it was
more accurate than a panel of 4 of the world's
best radiologists.
Tat ended up getting covered on TV, on CNN.
So making major breakthroughs in domains is
not necessarily technically that challenging.
The technical challenges in this case were
really about dealing with the fact that CT
scans are pretty big, so we've got some resource
issues.
Also they're black and white, so we had to
think about how we would change ImageNet pre-training
to black and white, and stuff like that.
But the basic example was not much more or
different code than you see here.
Question: Earlier you had a learning rate
of .01, is that the right rate????
Answer: The State Farm data is 4 gigabytes
and I only downloaded it about 1/2 hour before
class started, so I only ran a small fraction
of an epoch just ot make sure it works.
If I ran a whole epoch it probably would have
taken overnight.
So let's go back to Lesson 1, and there was
a little bit at the end that we didn't look
at.
How many of you have watched this video?
Some of you haven't; you need to.
Because I mentioned a couple of times in emails,
the last 2/3 of it was a surprise Lesson 0
of this class and it's where I teach what
convolutions are.
So if you haven't watched it, please do.
Rachel will add it to the in-class Slack channel
and also to the Lesson 2 resources wiki page.
Really, really important that you watch this
video.
The first 20 minutes or so is more of a general
background of it.
The rest is a discussion of exactly what convolutions
are.
For now, I'll try not to assume too much that
you know what they are.
The rest of it hopefully will be reasonably
stand-alone anyway.
But I want to talk about fine-tuning, and
I
want to talk about why we do fine-tuning.
Why do we start with an ImageNet network and
then fine-tune it, rather than just train
our own network.
And the reason why is that an ImageNet network
has learned a whole lot of stuff about what
the world looks like.
A guy called Matt Zeiler wrote this fantastic
paper a few years ago in which he showed us
what these networks learn.
And in fact the year after he wrote this paper,
he went on to win ImageNet so this is a powerful
example of why spending time thinking about
visualizations are helpful.
By spending time thinking about visualizing
networks, he then realized what was wrong
with the networks at the time.
He then made them better and won the next
year's ImageNet.
[Time: 55 minute mark]
We're not going to talk about that, we're
going to talk about some of these pictures
that he drew.
Here are 9 examples of what the very first
layer of an ImageNet convolutional neural
network looks like, what do the filters look
like.
And you can see here that here is a filter
that learns to find a diagonal edge, a diagonal
line.
So you can see, it's saying look for something
where there's no pixels, then there's bright
pixels and then there's no pixels, so that's
finding a diagonal line.
Here's something that finds a diagnoal line
in the other direction.
Here's something that finds a gradient, horizontal
from orange to blue, here's one diagonal from
orange to blue.
As I said, these are just 9.
There are 60 or so of these filters in Layer
1 of this ImageNet trained network.
So what happens (those of you who have watched
the video I just mentioned will be aware of
this) is that each of these filters gets placed
pixel by pixel, or group of pixels by group
of pixels, over a photo, over an image, to
find which parts of an image get matches.
So which parts have a diagonal line.
And over here, it shows 9 examples of little
bits of actual ImageNet images which match
this first filter.
As you can see they all are little diagonal
lines.
So here are 9 examples which match the next
filter with diagonal lines in the opposite
direction, and so forth.
The filters in the very first layer of a deep-learning
network are very easy to display.
This has happened for a long time and we've
also known for a long time that this is what
they look like.
We also know that the human vision system
is very similar.
The human vision system has filters that look
much the same.
To really answer the question of what are
we doing back here, I would say watch the
video.
The short answer is this is a 7x7 pixel patch
which is slid over the image one group of
7 pixels at a time to find which 7x7 patches
look like that.
Here is one example of a 7x7 patch which looks
like that.
So for example, this gradient.
Here are some examples of 7x7 patches that
look like that.
So we know that the human vision system actually
looks for very similar kinds of things.
The kind of things they look for are called
Gabor Filters.
If you want to google for Gabor Filters, you
can see some examples.
It's a little bit harder to visualize what
the second layer of a neural net looks like,
but Zeiler figured out a way to do it, and
in his paper he shows us a number of examples
of the second layer of his Internet trained
neural network.
Because we can't directly visualize them,
instead we have to show examples of what the
filter can look like.
So here is an example of a filter which clearly
tends to pick up corners.
So in other words, it's taking the straight
lines from the previous layer and combining
them to find corners.
There's another one which is learning to find
circles, and another one learning to find
curves.
And so you can see, here are 9 examples from
actual pictures on ImageNet which actually
did get heavily activated by this corner filter.
And here are some which got activated by this
circle filter.
The third layer then can take these filters
and combine them (remember this is 16 out
of 100) in the ImageNet architecture.
In Layer 3, we can combine all of those to
create even more sophisticated filters.
And so in Layer 3, there's a filter which
can find repeating gemetrical patterns.
[Time: 1 hour mark]
Here's a filter, what is it finding?
Let's go look at the examples.
Well, that's interesting.
It's finding pieces of text.
And here's something which is finding edges
of natural things, like fur and plants.
Layer 4 is finding certain kind of dog face,
Layer 5 is finding the eyeballs of birds and
reptiles, and so forth.
So there are 16 layers in our VGG network.
What we do when we fine-tune is we say, let's
keep all of these learnt filters and use them
and just learn how to combine the most complex,
subtle nuanced filters to find Cats vs Dogs
rather than combine them to learn 1000 categories
of ImageNet.
This is why we do fine-tuning.
So when I answered Annette's earlier question
does this work for CT scans and lung cancer
and the answer was yes, these kinds of filters
that find dog faces are not very helpful for
looking at a CT scan and looking for cancer.
But these earlier ones that can recognize
repeating images, or corners, or curves, certainly
are.
So really regardless of what computer vision
work you're doing, starting with some kind
of pre-trained network is almost certainly
a good idea.
Because at some level that pre-trained network
has learned to find some kinds of features
that are going to be useful for you.
And so if you start from scratch, you have
to learn them from scratch.
In Cats vs Dogs, we only had 25,000 pictures.
And so from 25,000 pictures to learn this
whole hierarchy of geometric and semantic
structures would have been very difficult.
So let's not learn it, let's use one that's
already been learnt on ImageNet, which is
1.5 million images.
So that's the short answer to the question
why do fine-tuning.
The longer answer really requires answering
the question, what exactly is fine-tuning?
And to answer the question what exactly is
fine-tuning, we have to answer the question
what exactly is a neural network.
Question: Which layer should you fine-tune
from?
Answer: We'll learn more about this shortly,
but the short answer is if you're not sure,
try all of them.
Generally speaking, if you're doing something
with natural images, the second-to-the-last
layer is very likely to be the best.
But I just tend to try a few things.
And we're going to see, today or next week,
ways that we can actually experiment with
it.
So as per usual, in order to learn about something
we will use Excel.
And here is a deep neural network in Excel.
Rather than having a picture with a bunch
of pixels, I just have 3 inputs.
A single row with 3 inputs, x1, x2, x3, and
the numbers are 2, 3, 1.
Rather than trying to pick out whether it's
a dog or a cat, we're going to assume there
are 2 outputs, 5 and 6.
So here's a single row that we're feeding
into a deep neural network.
So what is a deep neural network?
A deep neural network basically is a bunch
of matrix products.
So what I've done here is I've created a bunch
of random numbers.
They are normally distributed random numbers,
and this is the standard deviation that I'm
using for my normal distribution, and I'm
using 0 as the mean.
So here's a bunch of random numbers.
What if I then take my input vector and matrix
multiply them by my random weights, and here
it is.
Matrix multiply that by that, and here is
the answer I get.
So for example, 24.03=2*11.07 + 3*(-2.81)
+ 1*10.31, and so forth.
[Time: 1.05 hour mark]
Any of you who are either not familiar with
or are a little shakey on your matrix vector
products, tomorrow please go to the Kahn Academy
website and look for linear algebra and watch
the videos about matrix vector products.
They are very, very simple, but you also need
to understand them very, very intuitively,
comfortably.
Just like you understand plus and times in
regular algebra; I really want you to get
to that level of comfort with linear algebra
because this is the basic operation we're
doing again and again.
Question: Can you increase the font size of
the formula?
Answer: I don't think I can.
But instead what I will do is I will select
it Matrix multiply and the blue thing is find
derivatives.
So that is a single layer.
How do we turn that into multi-layers?
Not surprisingly, we create another bunch
of weights.
And now we take the new bunch of weights times
the previous activations with our matrix multiply,
and get a new set of activations.
And then we do it again.
We create another bunch of weights and multiply
them by our previous activations to get another
set of activations.
Note that the number of columns in your weight
matrix, you can make it as big or as small
as you like, as long as the last one has the
same number of columns as your output.
We had two outputs, 5 and 6, so our final
weight matrix had to have two columns so that
our final activations has two things.
With our random numbers, our activations are
not very close to what we hoped they would
be, not surprisingly.
So the basic idea here is that we now have
to use some kind of optimization algorithm
to make the weights a little bit better, and
a little bit better.
We'll see how to do that in a moment.
But for now, hopfully you are all familiar
that there is such a thing as an optimization
algorithm.
An optimization algorithm is something that
takes some kind of output to some kind of
mathematical function and finds the inputs
to that function that makes the outputs as
low as possible.
In this case, the thing we would like to make
as small as possible would be like the sum-of-squares
errors between the activations and the outputs.
I want to point out something here, which
is that when we stuck in these random numbers;
the activations that came out, not only are
they wrong, they're not even in the same general
scale as the activations that we want.
So that's a bad problem.
The reason it's a bad problem is that they're
so much bigger than the scale that we were
looking for.
As we change these weights just a little bit,
it's going to change the activations by a
lot, and this makes it very hard to train.
In general, you want your neural network (even
with random weights) to start off with activations
which are all of similar scale to each other,
and the output activations would be of similar
scale to the output.
For a very long time, nobody really knew how
to do this.
So for a very long time, people could not
really train deep neural networks.
It turns out that it was incredibly easy to
do, and there is a whole body of work talking
about neural network initializations.
It turns out that a really simple and really
effective neural network initialization is
called Xavier Initialization (named after
it's founder, Xavier Gloret) and it is 2 divided
by (in+out).
Like many things in deep-learning, you will
find this complex looking thing, Xavier Weight
Initialization Scheme, and when you look into
it you will find it is something about this
easy.
This is about as complex as deep learning
gets.
So I am now going to go ahead and implement
Xavier Deep Learning Weight Initialization
Schemes in Excel.
So I'm going to go up here and in this cell
put in equals 2 divided by (3 in + 4 out),
and press enter.
So now my first set of weights have that as
its standard deviation.
[Time: 1.10 hour mark]
My second set of weights I also have pointing
to the same place because they also have 4
in and 3 out.
And then my third, equals 2 dividided by (3
in + 2 out).
Done.
So I have now implemented it in Excel.
You can see that my activations are indeed
of the right general scale.
Generally speaking, you would normalize your
inputs and outputs to be mean 0 and standard
deviation 1.
We want them to be of the same kind of scale.
Obviously they're not going to be in 5 and
6 because we haven't done any optimization
yet, but we don't want them to be 100,000.
We want them to be somewhere around 5 and
6.
If we start off with them really, really high
or really, really low, an optimization is
going to be really hard to do.
For decades, when people tried to train deep-learning
networks, the training took forever or was
so incredibly unresiliant that it was useless.
This one thing, a better weight initialization
was a huge step.
It was like 3 years ago that this was invented.
It's not like we're going back a long time,
this is relatively recent.
Now the good news is Keras (and pretty much
any decent neural network library) will handle
your initialization for you.
Until recently, they pretty much all used
this.
There are some even more recent, slightly
better approaches, but they'll give you a
set of weights where your outputs will generally
have a reasonable scale.
Question: Is it arbitrary what dimensions
we're using here?
Answer: So what's not arbitrary is you are
given your input dimensionalities.
In our case, for example, it would be 224x224
pixels, 3 things.
You are given your output dimensionality,
in our case, for example, for Cats vs Dogs
it's 2.
The thing in the middle about how many columns
does each of your weight matrices have is
entirely up to you.
The more columns you add, the more complex
your model, and we're going to learn a lot
about that.
As Rachel said, this is all about your choice
of architecture.
So in my first one here I had 4 columns, and
therefore I had 4 outputs.
In my next one, I had 3 columns, and therefore
I had 3 outputs.
In my final one I had 2 columns and therefore
I had 2 outputs, and that is the number of
outputs that I want.
This thing of how many columns do you have
in your weight matrix is where you get to
decide how complex your model is, so we're
going to see that.
So let's go ahead and create a linear model.
So
we're going to learn how to create a linear
model.
Let's first of all learn how to create a linear
model from scratch (and this is something
that we did in that original USF Data Institute
launch video).
Without using Keras at all, I can define a
line as being a*x+b, I can then create some
synthetic data, I can assume a=3 and b=8,
create some random x's, and my y will be a*x+b.
So here's some x's and some y's, and not surprisingly
the scatterplot looks like so.
[Time: 1.15 hour mark]
The job of somebody creating a linear model
is to say I don't know what a and b is, how
can we calculate it.
Forget that we know they're 3 and 8, let's
guess that they are -1 and 1.
How can we make our guess better?
To make our guess better, we need a loss function.
A loss function is a mathematical function
that will be high if your guess is bad, and
it's low if it's good.
The loss function I'm using here is just sum-of-square
errors, which is my actual minus my prediction
squared, and add them up.
So if I define my loss function like that
and I say my guess is -1 and 1, I can calculate
my average loss and it is 9.
So my average loss with my random guesses
is not very good.
In order to create an optimizer, I need something
that can make my weights a little bit better.
If I have something that can make my weights
better, I can just call it again and again
and again.
That's actually very easy to do.
If you know the derivative of your loss function
with respect to your weights, then all you
need to do is update your weights by the opposite
of that.
So remember, the derivative is the thing that
says as your weight changes, your output changes
by this amount.
That's what the derivative is.
Question: So you start with something random
and by iterating you're going to get something
that works?
Answer: Yes.
Let's try it.
In this case we y=a+b and we have our loss
function is actual - predicted, squared and
add it up.
We're now going to create a function update
(upd), which is going to take our "a" guess
and our "b" guess and make them a little bit
better.
And to make them a little bit better, we calculate
the derivative of our loss function with respect
to "b" and the derivative of our loss function
with respect to "a".
How do we calculate those?
We go to Wolfram Alpha and we enter in "d"
along with our formula and the thing we want
to get the derivative of, and it tells us
the anwer.
So that's all I did.
I went to Wolfram Alpha, found the correct
derivative, pasted them in here.
What this means then is that this formula
here tells me as I increase "b" by 1, my sum-of-square
errors will change by this amount (dydb).
And this says that as I change "a" by 1, my
sum-of-square error will change by this amount
(dyda).
So if I know that dyda=3, if I know that my
loss function gets higher by 3 if I increase
"a" by 1, then clearly I need to make "a"
a little bit smaller.
If I make it a little bit smaller, my loss
function will go down.
So that's why our final step is to say take
our guess and subtract from it our derivative
times a little bit.
"lr" stands for learning rate.
As you can see, I'm setting it to .01.
How much is a little bit is something that
people spend a lot of time thinking about
and studying and we will spend time talking
about.
But you can always trial-and-error to find
a good learning rate.
When you use Keras, you will always need to
tell it what learning rate to use.
That's something that you want the highest
number you can get away with; you'll see more
of this next week.
The important thing to realize here is if
we update our guess minus-equals our derivative,
our guess is going to be a little bit better
because we know going in the opposite direction
makes the loss function a little bit lower.
So let's run those two things.
We've now got a function called update (upd)
which every time you run it makes our predictions
a little bit better . Finally now I'm basically
doing a little animation here that says every
time you calculate an animation, call my animate
function which 10 times will call my update
function.
So let's see what happens when I animate that.
There it is.
So it starts with a really bad line (my -1,1)
and it gets better and better.
So this is how stochastic gradient descent
works.
Stochastic gradient descent is the most important
algorithm in deep learning.
Stochastic gradient descent is the thing that
starts with random weights (like this) and
ends with weights that do what you want to
do.
[Time: 1.20 hour mark]
As you can see, stochastic gradient descent
is incredibly simple and yet incredibly powerful
because it can take any function and find
the set of parameters that does exactly what
we want to do with that function.
And when that function is a big learning neural
network, that becomes particularly powerful.
Just to remind ourselves about the setup for
this, we started out by saying this spreadsheet
is showing up a deep neural network with a
bunch of random parameters.
Can we come up with a way to replace the random
parameters with parameters that actually give
us the right answer.
So we need to come up with a way to do mathematical
optimization.
So rather than showing how to do that wit
a deep neural network, let's see how to do
it with a line.
So we start out by saying let's have a line,
a*x+b, where a=3 and b=8.
Pretend we didn't know that "a" is 3 and "b"
is 8.
Make a wild guess as to what "a" and "b" might
be.
Come up with an update function where every
time we call it, it makes "a" and "b" a little
bit better.
Call that update function lots of times and
confirm that eventually our line fits our
data.
Conceptually take that exact same idea and
apply it to these weight matrices.
Question: Shouldn't there be a random element
to avoid local minimums?
Answer: The question is there a problem here
that as we run this update function, might
be get to a point where our function looks
like this.
Currently we're trying to optimize the sum-of-square
errors and the sum-of-square errors looks
like this.
A more
complex function would kind of look like this.
So if we started here and gradually tried
to make it better and better, we might get
to a point where the derivative is 0, and
we then can't get any better, this would be
called a local minimum.
The question was suggesting a particula approach
to avoiding that.
Here's the good news, in deep-learning you
don't have local mimimum.
Why not?
The reason is that in an actual deep-learning
network, you don't hae one or two parameters,
you have hundreds of millions of parameters.
So rather than looking like this, over even
like a 3D version, it's a 600 million dimensional
space.
And for something to be a local minimum, it
means that the stochastic gradient descent
has wandered around and got to a point where
in every one of those 600 million directions
it can't get any better.
And the probability of that happening is 2
to the poer of 600 million.
So for actual deep-learning in practice, there's
always enough parameters that it's basically
unheard of to get to a point where there's
no direction to go to get better.
So the answer is, no.
For deep-learning, stochastic gradient descent
is just as simple as this, it's exactly as
simple as this.
We will learn some tweaks to allow us to get
faster, but this basic approach works just
fine.
Question: So what if you don't know the derivative?
[Time: 1.25 hour mark]
Answer: That's a great question.
For a long time, this was a royal GD pain.
Anybody who wanted to create stochastic gradient
descent in a neural network had to go through
and calculate all the derivatives.
And if you've got 600 million parameters,
that's a lot of trips to Wolfram Alpha.
So nowadays we don't have to worry about that
because all the modern neural network libraries
do symbolic differentiation.
In other words, it's like they have their
own little copy of Wolfram Alpha inside them
and they calculate the derivatives for you.
So you're never going to be the situation
where you don't know the derivatives.
You just tell it your architecture and it
will automatically calculate the derivatives.
So let's take a look.
Let's take this linear example and see what
it looks like in Keras.
In Keras, we can do exactly the same thing.
So let's start by creating some random numbers,
but this time let's make it a bit more complex,
we're going to have a random matrix with 2
columns.
And so to craft out our y values, we'll do
a little matrix multiply with our x, vit a
vector of [2,3] and then we'll add in a constant
of 1.
Here's our x's, and here's the first few y's.
So here 3.2 = (.56 * 2) + (.37 * 3) + 1.
Hopefully this looks very familiar, because
it's exactly what we did in Excel.
How do we create a linear model in Keras?
Keras calls a linear model Dense, it's also
known in our other libraries as fully_connected.
So when we go Dense with an input of 2 columns
and an output of 1 column, we have defined
a linear model that can go from this 2 column
array to this 1 column output.
The second thing we have in Keras is we have
some way to build multiple layer networks,
and Keras calls this Sequential.
Sequential takes an array that contains all
of the layers that you have in your neural
network.
So for example, in Excel here, I would have
had 3 layers.
In a linear model, we have just 1 layer.
So to create a linear model in Keras, you
say Sequential, pass in an array with a single
layer, that is a dense layer.
A dense layer is just a simple linear layer.
We tell it that there are two inputs and one
output.
This will automatically initialize the weights
in a sensible way, it will automatically calculate
the derivatives, so all we have to tell it
is how do we want to optimize the weights.
And we will say, please use stochastic gradient
descent with a learning rate of .1, and we're
attempting to minimize our loss of a mean-square-error.
So if I do that, that does everything except
the last solving step that we saw in the previous
notebook.
To do the solving, we just type fit (lm.fit).
Before we start, we can say evaluate (lm.evaluate)
to find out our loss function with random
weights, which is pretty krappy.
And then we run 5 epochs and the loss function
gets better and better and better using the
stochastic gradient descent update rule we
just learned.
So at the end, we can evaulate and it's better.
And then let's take a look at the weights.
They should be (2, 3, 1) and they're actually
(1.8, 2.7, 1.2).
That's not bad.
So why don't we run another 5 epochs.
Loss function keeps getting better.
We evaluate it now and it's better, and the
weights are now closer again to (2, 3, 1).
So we now know everything that Keras is doing
behind the scenes, exactly.
Not like hand-waving over details, that is
it.
We now know what it's doing.
So if we now say to Keras, don't just create
a single layer, but create multiple layers
by passing multiple layers to the sequential,
we can start to build and optimize deep neural
networks.
But before we do that, we can actually use
this to create a pretty decent entry to our
Cats vs Dogs competition.
So forget all the fine-tuning stuff because
I haven't told you how fine-tuning works yet.
How do we take the output of an ImageNet network
and as simply as possible create an entry
to our Cats vs Dogs competetion:
[Time: 1.30 hour mark]
So the basic problem here is that our current
ImageNet network returns 1000 probabilities
in a lot of detail.
It returns not just cat vs dog, but it returns
Animals->DomesticAnimals.
Ideally, it would be Cat and Dog here, but
it's not.
It keeps going - Egyptian cat, Persian cat,
and so forth.
So one thing we could do is we could write
code to take this hierarchy and roll it up
into cats vs dogs.
I've got a couple of ideas here as to how
we could do that.
For instance, we could find the largest probability
that's either a cat or a dog (from the 1000)
and use that, or we could average all of the
cat categories and all of the dog categories
and use that.
But the downsides here is that would require
manual coding for something we should be learning
from data, and more importantly, it's ignoring
information.
So let's say out of those 1000 categories,
the category for a bone was very high.
It's more likely a dog is with a bone than
a cat is with a bone.
So therefore, it out to take advantage, it
should learn to recognize environments that
cats are in versus environments that dogs
are in.
Or even recognize things that look like cats
from things that look like dogs.
So what we could do is learn a linear model
that takes the output of the ImageNet model,
the 1000 predictions and uses that as the
input, and uses the dog-cat label as the target.
And that linear model would solve our problem.
We have everything we need to know to create
this model now.
So let me show you how that works.
Let's again import our VGG model, and we're
going to try to do 3 things.
1) For every image, we'll get the True labels,
isCat or isDog.
2) We going to get the 1000 ImageNet category
predictions, so that will be 1000 floats for
every image.
Then we're going to use the output of 2) as
the input of our linear model and we're going
to use the output of 1) as the target for
our linear model, and create this linear model
and build some predictions.
So as per usual, we start by creating our
validation batches and our batches, just like
before.
I'll show you a trick.
Because one of the steps here is get the 1000
ImageNet category predictions for every image,
that takes a few minutes.
There's no need to do that again and again.
Once we've done it once, let's save the result.
Let me show you how you can save Numpy arrays.
Unfortunately most of the stuff you'll find
online about saving Numpy arrays takes a very,
very long time to run and it takes a shitload
of space.
There's a really cool library called bcolz
that almost nobody knows about that can save
Numpy arrays very, very quickly and in very
little space.
So I've created these two little things here
called save_array and load_array, which you
should definitely add to your toolbox.
They're actually in the utils.py, so you can
use them in the future.
And once you grab the predictions, you can
use these to just save the predictions and
load them back later, rather than recalculating
them each time.
I'll show you something else we've got.
Before we even worry about calculating the
predictions, we just need to load up the images.
When we load the images, there's a few things
we have to do, we have to decode the jpg images
and we have to convert them to 224x224 pixel
images (because that's what VGG expects).
That's kind of slow too.
So let's also save the result of that.
So I've created this little function called
get_data, which basically grabs all of the
validation images and all of the training
images and sticks them in a Numpy array.
Here's a cool trick.
In iPython notebook, if you put "??" before
something, it shows you the source of it.
So if you want to know what is get_data doing,
go "??get_data" and you can see exactly what
it's doing, it's concatenating all of the
different batches together.
Anytime you're using one of my little convenience
functions, I strongly suggest you look at
the source code to see what it's doing.
They are all super super small.
[Time: 1.35 hour mark]
So I can grab the data (the validation data,
the training data) and then I can just save
it so that in the future I can, rather than
having to watch and wait for that to pre-process,
I can just go load_array and that goes ahead
and loads it off disk.
It still takes a few seconds, but this will
be way faster than having to calculate it
directly.
So what that does is it creates a numpy array
with my 23,000 images, each of which has 3
colors and is 224x224 in size.
If you remember (from Lesson 1) the labels
that Keras expects are in a very particular
format.
Let's look at the format and see what it looks
like.
Here they are, the format of the labels is
each one has two things - it has the probability
that it's a cat and the probability that it's
a dog, and it's always just 0's and 1's.
So here is [0.
1.] is a dog, [1.
0.] is a cat, [1.
0.] is a cat, [0.
1.] is a dog.
This approach where you have a vector where
every element of it is a 0 except for a single
1 for the class you want is called one-hot
encoding and this is used for nearly all deep-learning.
So that's why I created a little function
called onehot that makes it very easy for
you to one-hot encode your data.
So for example if your data was just like
0,1,2,1,0, one-hot encoding that would look
like this (1,0,0), (0,1,0), (0,0,1), (0,1,0),
(1,0,0).
So that would be the kind of raw form, and
that is the one-hot encoded form.
The reason that we use one-hot encoding a
lot is that if you take this and you do a
matrix multiply by a bunch of weights, [w1,w2,w3],
you can calculate a matrix multiply, these
two are compatible.
So this is what makes you do deep-learning
easily with categorical variables.
So the next thing I want to do is I want to
grab my labels and I want to one-hot encode
them by using this onehot function.
And so you can take a look at that.
You can see here that the first few classes
look like so [array([[1.,0.],[1.,0.],[1.,0.],[1.,0.]]),
but the first few labels are one-hot encoded
like so [array([[1.,0.],[1.,0.],[1.,0.],[1.,0.]]).
So we're now at a point where we can finally
do Step #2.
So to remind you, Step #2 was get the 1000
ImageNet category predictions for every image.
So Keras makes that really easy for us.
We can just say model.predict and pass in
our data.
So model.predict with train data is going
to give us the 1000 predictions from ImageNet
for our train data, and this will give it
for our validation data.
And again, running this takes a few minutes.
So I save it and then I will load it.
So you can see we now have
the 23000x3x224x224, it is now 23000x1000.
So for every image we have 1000 probabilities.
So let's look at one of them (trn_features[0]).
Not surprisingly if we look at just one of
these, nearly all of them are 0.
So for the 1000 categories, only one of these
numbers should be big.
It can't be lots of different things, it can't
be a cat and a dog and a jet airplane.
Not surprisingly nearly all of these things
are very close to 0, hopefully just one of
them is very close to 1.
So that's exactly what we expect.
[Time: 1.40 hour mark]
So now that we've got our 1000 features for
each of our training images and for each of
our validation images, we can go ahead and
create a linear model.
So here it is, here's our linear model.
The input is 1000 columns, every one of those
ImageNet predictions.
The output is two columns, it's a dog or it's
a cat.
We will optimize it with, I'm actually not
going to use SGD, I'm going to use a slightly
better thing called RMSprop which I will teach
you about next week.
It's a very minor tweak on SGD that tends
to be a lot faster.
So I suggest in practice we use RMSprop, not
SGD, it's almost the same thing.
Now that we know how to fit a model once it's
defined, we can just go model.fit and it runs
basically instantly because all it has to
do ... Let's take a look at our model [lm.summary()],
it's just one layer with 2000 weights.
So running 3 epochs took 0 seconds and we
got an accuracy of .9735.
After another 3 epochs an accuracy of .9770,
even better.
So you can see this is like the simplest possible
model.
I haven't done any fine-tuning.
All I've done is I've taken the ImageNet predictions
for every image and built a linear model that
maps from those predictions to Cat or Dog.
A lot of the amateur deep-learning papers
that you see, one was classifying leaves by
whether they're sick, one was classifying
skin lesions by type of lesion.
Often this is all people do, they take a pre-trained
model, they grab the outputs and they stick
it into a linear model and then they use it.
As you can see, it actually works often pretty
well.
So I just wanted to point out here that in
getting this .9770 result, we have not used
any magic libraries at all.
It's more code than it looks like because
we're saving stuff as we go.
We grabbed our batches, we grabbed the data.
We turned our images into a Numpy array.
We took the Numpy array and ran model.predict
on them.
We grabbed our labels and we one-hot encoded
them.
And then finally, we took the one-hot encoded
labels and the 1000 probabilities and we fed
them to a linear model with 1000 inputs and
2 outputs.
And then we trained it and we ended up with
a validation accuracy of .9770.
So what we're doing is we're digging right
deep into the details.
We know exactly how SGD works, we know exactly
how the layers are being calculated.
And we know exactly therefore what Keras is
doing behind the scenes.
So we started way up high with something that
was totally obscure as to what was going on
(we were just using it like you might use
Excel) and we've gone all the way down to
see exactly what's going on and we've got
a pretty good result.
So the last thing we're going to do is take
this and turn it into a fine-tuning model
to get a slightly better result.
What is fine-tuning?
In order to understand fine-tuning, we're
going to have to understand one more piece
of a deep-learning model, and this is activation
functions.
This is our last major piece.
I want to point something out to you.
In this view of the deep-learning model we
went matrix multiply, matrix multiply, matrix
multiply.
Who wants to tell me how can you simplify
a matrix multiply on top of a matrix multipy
on top of a matrix multiply?
What's that actually doing?
A linear model on a linear model on a linear
model is itself a linear model.
So in fact, this whole thing could be turned
into a single matrix multiply because it's
just doing linear on top of linear on top
of linear.
[Time: 1.45 hour mark]
So this clearly cannot be what deep-learning
is really doing, because deep-learning is
doing a lot more than a linear model.
So what is deep-learning actually doing?
What deep-learning is actually doing is at
every one of these points where it says activations,
with deep-learning we do one more thing, which
is we put each of these activations through
a non-linearity of some sort.
There are various things we can use.
Sometimes we'll use tanh, sometimes people
use sigmoid, but most commonly these days
people use max(0,x), which is called ReLU,
or Rectified Linear.
So when you see rectified linear activation
function, people actually mean max(0,x).
So if we took is Excel spreadsheet and added
max(0,x) and we
replaced the activation with this for each
layer, we now have a genuine modern deep-learning
network.
Interestingly it turns out that this kind
of neural network is capable of approximating
any given function.
In the lesson, you'll see that there is a
link to a fantastic tutorial by Michael Nielson
on this topic.
What he does is he shows you how, with exactly
this kind of approach, where you put functions
on top of functions, he actually let's you
drag them up and down to see how you can change
the parameters and see what they do.
He gradually builds up so that once you have
a function of a function of a function of
this type, he shows you how you can create
arbitrarily complex shapes.
So using this incredibly simple approach where
you have a matrix multiplication followed
by a rectified linear (like max(0,x)) and
stick that on top of each other on top of
each other, that's actually what's going on
in a deep learning neural network.
And you will see in all of the deep neural
networks we have created so far, we have always
had this extra parameter "activation=" and
generally you'll see "activation='relu'".
That's what it's doing, it's saying after
you do the matrix product, do a max(0,x).
So what we need to do is we need to take our
final layer, which has both a matrix multiplication
and an activation function, and what we're
going to do is we are going to remove it.
And I'll show you why.
If we look at our model, our VGG model, let's
take a look at
it (vgg.model.summary()).
What does the input look like?
The very last layer is a dense layer, the
very last layer is a linear layer.
It seems weird therefore that in that previous
section where we added an extra dense layer.
Why would we add a dense layer on top of a
dense layer, given that this dense layer has
been tuned to find the 1000 ImageNet categories.
Why you would you want to take that and add
on top of it something that has been fine-tuned
to find cats and dogs?
How about we remove this and instead use the
previous dense layer with its 4096 activations
and use that to find our cats and dogs?
So to do that, it's as simple as saying model.pop
(that will remove the very last layer), and
then we can go model.add and add in our new
linear layer with 2 outputs, cat and dog.
[Time 1.50 minute mark]
So when we said "??vgg.finetune" earlier,
here is the sourcecode - model.pop, model.add
a dense layer with the correct number of classes.
So it's basically doing a model.pop and model.add(Dense,..).
So once we've done that we will now have a
new model which is designed to calculate Cats
vs Dogs, rather than designed to calculate
ImageNet categories and then calculate Cats
vs Dogs.
So when we use that approach, everything else
is exactly the same.
We then compile it, giving it an optimizer.
And then we can call model.fit.
Anything where we want to use batches by the
way we have to use something underscore generator.
So model.fit_generator and we pass it in batches,
and if we run it for 2 epochs, you can see
we get 97.35.
If we run it for a little bit longer, eventually
we will get something quite a bit better than
our previous linear model on top of ImageNet
approach.
In fact, we know we can.
We got 98.3 with fine-tuning earlier.
So that's the only difference between fine-tuning
and adding an additional linear layer; we
just do a pop first before we add.
Once we calculate it, I would then go ahead
and save the weights and then we can use that
again in the future.
So from here on in, you'll often find that
after I get my fine-tuned model I will often
go model.load_weights with 'finetune1.h5'
because this is now something that we can
use as a pretty good starting point for all
of our future Dogs and Cats models.
Okay, I think that's about everything that
I wanted to show you for now.
For anybody who is interested in going futher
during the week there is one more section
here in this lesson showing you how you can
train more than just the last layer.
But we'll look at that next week as well.
So during this week, the assignment is very
similar to last week's assignment, but just
take it further.
Now that you actually know what's going on
with fine-tuning and with linear layers, there's
a couple things you can do.
One is, for those of you who have not yet
entered the Cats vs Dogs competition, get
your entry in.
And then have a think about everything you
know about the evaluation function, the categorical
cross-entropy loss function, fine-tuning and
see if you can find ways to make your model
better.
And see how high up the leaderboard you can
get using this information.
Maybe you can push yourself a little further,
read some of the other forum threads on Kaggle,
on our forums and see if you can get the best
result you can.
If you really want to push yourself then,
see if you can do the same thing by writing
all of the code yourself, don't use our fine-tune
at all, don't use our notebooks at all.
See if you can build it from scratch so that
you really understand how it works.
And then, of course, if you want to go further,
see if you can enter not just the Dogs vs
Cats competition but see if you can enter
one of the other competitions we talk about
on our website, such as Galaxy Zoo, or The
Plankton competition, or the State Farm Distracted
Driver competition.