We talked about pseudo-labeling several weeks
ago as a way of dealing with semi-supervised
learning.
Remember how in the State Farm competition,
we had far more unlabeled images in the test
set than we had in the training set and the
question was how do we take advantage of knowing
something about the structure even though
they don't have labels.
And we learned this crazy technique called
pseudo-labeling, or a combination of pseudo-labeling
and knowledge distillation, which is where
you predict the outputs of the test set and
then you act as if those outputs were true
labels, ind of add them in to your training.
The reason I wasn't able to actually implement
that and see how it works because we needed
a way of combining two different sets of batches.
In particular, the advice I saw from Jeff
Hinton when he wrote about pseudo-labeling
is thatyou want 1-in-3 or 1-in-4 of your training
data to come from your pseudo-labeled data,
and the rest to come from your real data.
So the good news is I built that thing and
it was ridiculously easy. This is the entire
code, I call it the MixIterator, and it will
be in our utils class.
All it does is it's something where you create
your generators or whatever batches you like
and then you pass an array of those iterators
to this constructor and then you pass an array
of those iterators to this constructor. Every
time the Keras system calls next on it, it
grabs the next batch from all of those sets
of batches and concatenates themall together.
I tried doing pseudo-labeling on Nmist (remember
on Nmist we already had a pretty close to
state-of-the-art result, 99.69). So I thought,
can we improve it any more if we use pseudo-labeling
on the test set.
So to do so, just do this -- you grab your
training batches as usual, using data augmentation
if you want. Then you create your pseudo-batches
by saying my labels are my test set [X_test]
and my labels are my predictions [avg_preds].
So now this is the second set of batches,
my pseudo-batches. Then passing an array of
those two things to the MixIterator, which
is going to give us a few images from here
(batches) and a few images from here (ps_batches).
How many? However many you asked for. In this
case I was getting 64 from my training set
and 64/4 from my test set (Come to think of
it, that's probably less than Hinton recommends).
Now I can use that like any other generator.
Just call model.fit_generator, pass in that
thing I just created. So what it's going to
do is create a bunch of batches that will
be 64 items from my regular training set and
a quarter of that for my pseudo-labeled set.
And lo and behold, it gave me a slightly better
score. There's only so much better we can
do at this point, but that took us up to 99.72.
It's worth mentioning that every .01% is just
one image, so we're really on the edges at
this point, but this is getting even closer
to the state-of-the-art, despite the fact
that we're not doing any handwriting-specific
techniques.
I also tried it on the Fish dataset. I realized
at that point that this allows us to do something
else.
Normally when we train on the training set,
we set aside a validation set.
If we don't want to submit to Kaggle, we only
train on a subset of the data they gave us,
we don't train on the validation set as well
(which is not great, right).
So what you can do is create 3 sets of batches
- you can have your regular training batches,
you can have your pseudo-labeled test batches.
If you think about it, you could also add
in some validation batches using the true
labels for the validation set.
[Time: 5 minute mark]
This is something you do right at the end.
Once you say this is the model I'm happy with,
you can fine-tune it using some of the validation
data.
As you can see out my batch size of 64, I'm
putting 44 in the training set, 4 from the
validation set and 16 from the pseudo-labeled
test set.
This worked pretty well. It got me from about
110 to 60 on the leaderboard.
Question: In the Keras implementation, there
is something called SampleWeight. I was wondering
if you could just set the sample weight lower?
Answer: Yes, you can use the sample weight
but you would still still have to construct
the consolidated dataset. This is a more convenient
way where you don't have to append it all
together.
I will mention that I've found the way I'm
doing it seems a little slow. There's some
obvious ways I can speed it up. It might be
that this concatention each time is having
to create new memory and that takes time.
There's some obvious things I can do to try
to speed it up, but it's good enough - it
does the job.
I'm pleased that we know have a convenient
way to do pseudo-labeling in Keras that seems
to do a pretty good job.
The other thing I wanted to talk about today
(before we move on to new material) was embeddings.
I think for at least some of you some additional
explanations could be helpful.
So I wanted to start out by reminding you
that when I introduced embeddings to you,
the data we had was in this cross-tab form.
In this cross-tab form, it's very easy to
visualize what embeddings look like -- for
movieId 27 and userId 28, here is that movieId's
embedding right here, and here is that userId's
embedding right here, so here is the product
of the two right here. That was all pretty
straight-forward.
All we had to do to optimize our embeddings
was utilize the gradient descent solver built
in to MS Excel, Solver. We just told it was
our objective is ... minimize this cell by
changing these cells.
Now the data that we are given, the MovieLens
data, requires some manipulation to get into
a cross-tab form.
We're actually given data in this form, and
we wouldn't want to create a cross-tab with
all of this data because it would be way too
big -- it would be every single user times
every single movie.
That's not how Keras works. Keras uses this
data in exactly this format.
Let me show you how that works and what an
embedding is actually doing. Here is the exact
same thing, but I'm going to show you the
data in the format that Keras uses it.
So this is our input data. Every rating is
a row, it has a userId, a movieId and a rating.
And this is what an embedding matrix looks
like for 15 users.
These are the userIds. This is userId 14's
embeddings, this is userId 29's embedding,
this is userId 72's embedding. At this stage,
they're just random -- I initialized them
to random numbers.
And here is the movie embedding matrix. So
the embedding matrix for movieId 27 are these
5 numbers.
So what happens when we look at userId 14
and movieId 17 rating number 2?
The first thing is that we have to find userId
14. Here it is -- userId 14 is the first thing
in this array, so the index of userId 14 is
1.
So then here is the first row from the user
embeddings embedding matrix.
[Time: 10 minute mark]
Similarly, here is movieId 417, the 14th row
of this table, so you want to return the 14th
row.
You can see here, it has looked up and found
the 14th row and then indexed it to the table's
14th row.
So then to calculate the dot product, we simply
take the dot product of the user embedding
with the movie embedding.
To calculate the loss, we simply take the
rating and subtract prediction and square
it
To calculate total loss function, we just
add that all up and take the square root.
The orange background cells are the cells
whcih we want our SGD solver to change.
In order to minize this cell here (rmse),
all of the orange cells will be calculated.
We were saying last week that an embedding
is simply looking up an array by an index.
You can see why I was saying that, right?
It's essentially taking an index, looks it
up in an array and returns that row. That's
literally all it's doing.
You might want to convince yourself during
the week (if you haven't done so already),
that this is identical to taking a one-hot
encoded matrix and multiplying it by an embedding
matrix.
So we can do exactly the same thing this way.
We can say, Data->Solver and we want to set
this cell to a minimum by changing these cells.
If I say Solve, then Excel will go away and
try to improve our objective.
What it's doing here is using gradient descent
to try to find ways to increase or decrease
all of these numbers such that the rmse becomes
as low as possible.
That's literally all that's going on in our
Keras example here, this dot product. So this
thing here where we said create an embedding
for a user, u=Embedding(n_users,n)factors,input_length=1,W_regularizer=12(1e-4))(user_in)
That's just saying create something where
I can look up a userId and find their row,
look up a movieId and find its row, take the
dot product, train a model (model.fit), try
to predit a rating and use SGD to make it
better and better.
So you can see here that it's got the mean
square error down to .4.
For example, the first one predicted 3 and
it's actually 2; the second one predicted
4.5 and it's actually 4; the third one predicted
4.6 and it's actually 5 ... you get the idea.
Word embeddings work exactly the same way.
One of the students talked about it this week.
I grabbed the text of Green Eggs
and Ham. I've turned this column of words
into a matrix. The way I did that was to take
every unique word in that column (here is
the wordId of each of thos words).
So then I just randomly generated an embedding
matrix.
matrix. I equally could have used downloaded
GloVe embeddings as well.
And so then for each word, I look up each
word in the list. "I" is wordId 8, and here
is the 8th row of the embedding matrix.
So you see we've started with a poem and we've
turned it into a matrix of floats. The reason
we do this is our machine learning tools support
a matrix of floats.
All of the questions like, "Does it matter
what the wordIds are?" You can see it doesn't
matter at all. All we're doing is we're looking
them up in this matrix and returning the floats.
[Time: 15 minute mark]
Once we've done that, we never use it again.
We just use this matrix of floats. So that's
what embedding does.
I hope that's helpful. Feel free to ask if
you have any questions because we're going
to be using embeddings throught this class.
Hopefully that helped a few people clarify
what's going on.
Let's get back to Recurrent Neural Networks.
To remind you, we talked about the purpose
of recurrent neural networks as being really
all about memory.
If we're going to handle something like recognizing
a comment start and a comment end, and being
able to keep track of the fact that we're
in a comment through all of this time so that
we can do modeling on this kind of structured
language, we're really going to need memory.
That allows us to handle long-term dependencies
and provides a stateful represention. In general,
the stuff we're going to be looking at will
be particularly needing these three things
(long-term dependency, stateful representation,
and memory). And it's also helpful when you
have a variable length sequence.
Question: How does the size of my embedding
depend on the number of unique words? Mapping
Green Eggs and Ham, real numbers seem sufficient,
but wouldn't be for all of J.R.R. Tolkien.
Answer: So your choice of how big to make
your embedding matrix, as in how many latent
factors to create is on of these architectural
decisions which we don't really have an answer
to.
My best suggestion would be to read the word
to vec paper (which kind of introduced a lot
of this, or at least took it a lot further)
and look at the difference between a 50-dimensional,
100-dimensional, 200, 300, 600 dimensional
and see what are the different levels of accuracies
that these different sized embedding matrices
created when the authors of that paper provided
this information. So that's a quick shortcut
because other people have experiemented and
provided this information for you.
The other is to do your own experiments. Try
a few different sizes. It's not really about
the length of the wordlist. It's really about
the complexity of the language or the type
of problem you're trying to solve.
That's really problem dependent and will require
intuition developed through reading, experimenting,
and also your own experience.
Question: What would be the range of root
mean square values to say that a model is
good?
Answer: To say that a model is good is another
model-specific issue. A root mean square error
is very interpretable - it's basically how
far out is it on average. So if we found out
we were getting in the range of .4 on average,
it sounds like it's
good enough to be useful to help people find
movies they might like.
There's really no one solution. I actually
wrote a whole paper about this, "Designing
Great Data Products". This is based on ten
years of work I did at a company I created
called Optimal Decisions Group. Optimal Decisions
Group was all about how to use predictive
modeling not just to make predictions but
to optimize actions. This whole paper is about
that.
In the end, it's really about coming up with
a way to measure the benefit to your organization,
or to your project, of getting that extra
0.1% accuracy. There are some suggestions
on how to do that in this paper.
[Time: 20 minute mark]
Okay, so we looked at kind of a visual vocabulary
we developed for writing down neural nets.
Any colored box represents a matrix of activations.
That's a really important point. A colored
box represents a matrix of activations. It
could be the input matrix, it could be the
output matrix, it could be the matrix that
comes from taking an input matrix and putting
it through a matrix product.
The rectangle boxes represent inputs, the
circular ones represent hidden or intermediate
activations, and triangles represent outputs.
Arrows, very importantly, represent layer
operations. A layer operation is anything
you can do to one colored box to create another
colored box.
In general, it's going to almost always involve
some kind of a linear function, like a matrix
product, or a convolution, and it will probably
include an activation function like relu.
Because the activation functions are unimportant
in terms of detail, I started removing those
from the pictures.
Because the layer operations are pretty consistent
(we probably know what they are), I started
removing those as well just to keep things
simple.
So we're simplifying these diagrams to try
and keep the main pieces. As we did so, we
can start to create more complex diagrams.
We talked about a kind of a language model
where we would take inputs character #1 and
character #2 and we would try and predict
character #3.
We thought one way to do that would be to
create a deep neural network with two layers.
The character #1 input would go through a
layer operation to create our first fully
connected layer.
That would go through another layer operation
to create the second fully connected layer,
and we would also add our second character
input going through its own fully connected
layer at this point.
The last important thing you have to learn
is that 2 arrows going in to a single shape
means that we are adding the results of those
2 layer operations together. So 2 arrows going
in to a shape represents summing up, element-wise,
the results of these two layer operations.
This was the little visual vocabulary we set
up last week and I kind of kept track of it
down here (in the lower right corner) as to
what things are.
So now I wanted to point out something really
interesting - there's three kinds of layer
operations going on. We've got predicting
the 4th character using characters 1, 2, and
3.
There are layer operations that turn a character
input into a hidden activation matrix, here
and here.
There are layer operations that turn one hidden
layer activation matrix into a new hidden
layer activation matrix.
And there there's layer operations that takes
hidden activations and turns them into output
activations.
You can see here that I've colored them in,
and here I've got a little legend. Green are
the input->hidden, blue is the hidden->output,
and orange is the hidden->hidden.
So I claim that the dimensions of the weight
matrices -- all of them connected by the green
arrows have the same dimensions. All of the
green ones have the sime dimensions because
they're taking an input of vocab size and
turning it into an output with size # of activations.
So all of the green arrows represent weight
matrices of the same dimensionality. Ditto
the orange arrows, the orange arrows all represent
weight matrices of the same dimensionality.
I would go further than that and say that
the green arrows represent semantically the
same thing -- they're all saying how do you
take a character and convert it to a hidden
state.
The orange arrows are all saying how do you
take hidden state from a previous character
and turn it into a hidden state for a new
character.
The blue arrows are how do you take a hidden
state and turn it into outputs.
When you look at it that way, all of these
circles are basically the same thing. They're
just representing this hidden state at a different
point in time.
[Time: 25 minute mark]
I'm going to use this word "time" in a fairly
general way. I'm not really talking about
time, I'm just talking about the sequence
in which we're presenting additional pieces
of information to this model.
We first present the first character, then
the second character, then the third character.
So we could redraw this whole thing in a simpler
way, in a more general way.
Before we do, I'm actually going to show you
in Keras how to build this model, and in doing
so we're going to learn a bit more about functional
API.
To do that, we are going to use this corpus
of all of the collected words of Nietzsche.
So we load in those works and we find all
the unique characters (of which there are
86). Here they are, joined up all together.
And then we create a mapping from the character
to the index at which it appears in the list,
and the mapping from the index to the character.
So this is basically creating the equivalent
of these tables, or more specifically, this
table. But rather than using words, we'll
use characters.
So that allows us to take the text of Nietzsche
and convert it into a list of numbers, where
the numbers represent the number at which
the character appears in this list (idx=[char_indices[c]
for c in text]). So here are the first 10
(idx[:10]), that's called idx.
So at any point we can turn our poll text
into the equivalent indices. At any point
we can turn it back into text by simply taking
those indexes and looking them up in our index-to-character
mapping. So here you see we turn it back into
the start of the text again.
So that's the data we're working with. The
data we're working with is a list of character
ids and those character ids represent the
works of Nietzsche.
So we're going to build a model
which attempts to predict the 4th character
from the previous 3. To do that, we're going
to go through our whole list of indexes, from
0 to the end minus three.
We're going to create a whole list of the
0th, 4th, 8th, 12th, etc. characters. And
a list of the 1st, 5th, 9th, etc. And a list
of the 2nd, 6th, 10th and so forth.
So this is going to represent the first character
in each sequence, the second character in
each sequence, the third character in each
sequence. And this is the one we want to predict,
the 4th character.
We can now turn these in to numpy arrays just
by stacking them up together.
Now we've got our input for our 1st characters,
our 2nd characters, our 3rd characters for
every 4 character piece of this collected
works.
And then our y's - our labels - will simply
be the 4th characters.
Here you can see them. For example, if we
took x1, x2, and x3 - this is the first character
of the text, the second character of the text,
the third character of the text and the fourth
character of the text. So we're trying to
predict this, based on these three. And then
we're trying to predict this, based on these
three. So that's our data point.
So you see we've got about 200,000 of these
inputs for each of x1, x2, and x3 for y.
We're going to first turn them into embeddings
by creating an embedding matrix. I have to
mention that this is not normal, I have not
actually seen anybody else do this.
Most people just treat them as one-hot encodings.
So for example the most widely used blog post
about CAR RNNs was Andrej Karpathy's (which
was quite fantastic), "The Unreasonable Effectiveness
of Recurrent Neural Networks".
You can see in his version he shows them as
being one-hot encoded.
[Time: 30 minute mark]
We're not going to do that - we're going to
turn them into embeddings.
I think it makes a lot of sense. Capital "A"
and lower-case "a" have some similarities
that embeddings can understand.
Different types of things that have to be
opened and closed, like parentheses and quotes
have things that can be captured in embeddings.
There's all kinds of things that we can expect
embeddings can capture. My hypothesis is that
an
embedding is going to do a better job than
just a one-hot encoding. In my experiments
over the last couple of weeks, that generally
seems to be true.
So we're going to take each character, 1 through
3, and turn them into embeddings by first
of all creating an input layer for them and
then creating an embedding layer for that
input. So we're going to return the input
layer and a flattened version of the embedding
layer.
So this is the input to an output of each
of our three embedding layers for our three
input characters. So that's basically our
inputs.
We
now have to decide how many activations do
we want. That's something we can just pick.
I've decided to go with 256 as something that
seems reasonable - seems to work okay.
We now have to somehow construction something
where each of our green arrows ends up as
the same weight matrix. Keras makes this really
easy with the Keras functional API.
When you call Dense like this [dense_in=Dense(n_hidden,activation='relu')],
what it's actually doing is it's creating
a layer with a specific weight matrix. Notice
I haven't passed it anything to say what it's
connected to, so it's not part of a model
yet. This is just saying I'm going to have
something which is a dense layer which creates
256 activations and I'm going to call it dense_in.
It doesn't actually do anything until I connect
it to something.
Here I'm going to say character 1's hidden
state comes from character #1, which is the
output of our first embedding and putting
it through this dense_in layer [c1_hidden=dense_in(c1)].
So this is the thing which creates our first
circle. So the embedding is the thing that
creates the output of the first rectangle
and this creates our first circle.
So dense_in is the green arrow. So what that
means is that now in order to create the next
set of activations, we need to create the
orange arrow. Since the orange arrow is a
different weight matrix than the green arrow,
we have to create a new dense layer.
So here it is, a new dense layer, and again,
with n hidden outputs. So with a new dense
layer, this is a whole separate weight matrix.
So now that I've done that, I can create my
character 2 hidden state, which is here. And
I'm going to have to sum up two separate things.
I'm going to take my character 2 embedding,
put it through my green arrow, that's going
to be there.
I'm going to take the output of my character
1's hidden state and run it through my orange
arrow, and then we're going to merge the two
together.
And merge, by default, does a sum. This is
adding together these two outputs, it's adding
together these two layer operation outputs.
And that gives us this circle.
So the 3rd character output is done in exactly
the same way. We take the 3rd characters embedding,
run it through out green arrow, take it through
the results of our previous hidden activations
and run it through our orange arrow and then
merge the two together.
Question: Is the first output the size of
the latent field's embeddings?
Answer: The size of the latent embeddings
we defined when we created the embeddings
up here, and we defined them as having n_fac
size. And n_fac we defined as 42.
[Time: 35 minute mark]
So c1, c2, and c3 represent the result of
putting in each character through this embedding
and getting out 42 latent vectors. Those are
then the things that we put in to our green
arrow.
So after doing this three times, we now have
c3 hidden (which is here). So we now need
a new set of weights, we need another dense
layer, blue arrow. We'll call that dense_out.
And this needs to create an output of size
86, vocab size. It needs to create something
which can match to the one-hot encoded list
of the possible characters, which is 86 long.
So now that we've got this orange arrow, we
can apply that to our final hidden state to
get our output.
In Keras, all we need to do now is call Model,
passing in the three inputs which were returned
to us way back here. Each time we created
an embedding, we returned the input layer
(c1_in, c2_in, c3_in).
Passing in the three inputs and passing in
out output. So that's our model. So we can
now compile it, set a learning rate, fit it.
As you can see, its losses are actually decreasing.
We can then test that out very easily by creating
a little function. We're going to pass 3 letters.
We're going to take those 3 letters and turn
them in to character indices (just look them
up by their indexes). Turn each of these into
a numpy array. Call model.predict on those
3 arrays. That gives us 86 outputs. We're
then going to do argmax to find out which
index into those 86 is the highest and that's
the character number that we want to return.
So if we pass in "phi", "l" is most likely
next. If we pass in " th", "e" is mot likely
next. Pass in " an" and it thinks that "d"
is most likely next.
So you can see that it seems to be doing a
pretty reasonable job of taking 3 characters
and returning a 4th character that seems pretty
sensible.
Not the world's most powerful model, but a
good example of how we construct pretty arbitrary
architectures using Keras and then letting
SGD do the work.
Question: This model, how would it predict
the context in which we're trying to predict
the next?
Answer: It knows nothing about the context.
All it has at any point in time are the previous
3 characters. So it's not a great model. We're
going to improve it though. Gotta start somewhere.
Question: If we're at the stage where we're
doing predictions on real data, how would
the context ...
Answer: We're getting there. So, in order
to answer your question, let's build this
up a little further.
Rather than trying to predict character 4
from the previous 3 characters, let's try
and predict character n from the previous
n-1 characters.
Since all of these circles basically mean
the same thing, which is the hidden state
at this point. And since all of these orange
arrows are literally the same thing - it's
a dense layer with exactly the same weight
matrix, let's stick all of the circles on
top of each other, which means all of these
orange arrows just become one arrow pointing
to itself. And this is the definition of a
Recurrent Neural Network.
When we see it in this form, we say that we
are looking at it in its recurrent form. When
we see it in this form, we say that we are
looking at it in its unrolled form, or unfolded
form.
They're both very common. This is obviously
neater, so for quickly sketching out an RNN
architecture this is much more convenient.
But actually this unrolled form is really
important. For example, when Keras uses TensorFlow
as a backend, it actually always unrolls it
in this way in order to compute it.
That obviously takes up a lot more memory,
so it's quite nice to use the Theano backend
in Keras which can actually directly implement
it as this kind of loop. And that's what we'll
be doing today.
[Time: 40 minute mark]
In general, we've got the same idea. We're
going to have character 1 input come in, go
through the first green arrow, go through
the first orange arrow. From then on we can
just say take the second character and repeat,
take the third character and repeat. At each
time period, we're getting a new character
going through a layer operation as well as
taking the previous hidden state and taking
it through its layer operation.
At the very end, we will put it through a
different layer operation (blue arrow) to
get an output. So I'm going to show you this
in Keras now.
Question: Does every fully connected layer
have to have the same activation function?
Answer: In general, in all of the models we've
seen so far we've construted them in a way
where you can write anything you want as the
activation function.
In general though, I haven't seen any examples
of any successful architetures that mix activation
functions - other than of course, at the output
layer would pretty much always be a softMax.
I'm not sure it's not something that might
become a good idea. It's just not something
that anybody's done successfully so far.
I will mention something importation about
activation functions, though. You can use
pretty much any non-linear function as an
activation function and get pretty reasonable
results. I've seen some papers that people
have written where they've tried all kinds
of weird activation functions and they pretty
much all work. So it's not something to get
hung up about.
It's just that certain activation functions
will train more quickly and more resiliantly.
In particular, relu and relu variations tend
to work particularly well.
Let's implement this. We're going to use a
very similar approach to what we've used before
and we're going to create our first RNN. We're
going to create it from scratch, using nothing
but standard Keras dense layers.
In this case, the inputs will not be c1, c2,
c3. We're going to have to create an array
of inputs. We're going to have to decide what
n we're going to use.
For this one, I've decided to use 8. I'm going
to use 8 characters to create the 9th character.
So I'm going to create an array with 8 elements
in it and each element will contain a list
of the 0th, 8th, 16th, 24th character, the
1, 9, 17, 25 character, the 2, 10, 18, 26
charater, etc. Just like before.
We're going to have a sequence of inputs where
each one is offset by 1 from the previous
one. And then our output will be exactly the
same thing, except we're going to look at
the indexed across by cs, so 8. So this will
be the 8th thing in each sequence, predicted
by the previous ones.
So now we can go through every one of those
data items, lists and turn them into a numpy
array. Here you can see that we have 8 inputs
and each one is of length 75 thousand or so
(75110).
We can take our y and make a numpy array out
of it. Here we can visualize it. Here are
the first 8 elements of x.
Looking at the first 8 elements of x, let's
look at the first element of each one -- 40,
42, 29 ....
So this column is the first 8 characters of
our test. And here is the 9th character.
So the first thing that this model will try
to do is to look at these 8 to predict this.
Then it will look at these 8 to predict this
and so forth.
You can see that this list here is exactly
the same as this list here; the final character
of each sequence is the same as the first
charater of this sequence.
So it's almost exactly the same as our previous
data, we've just done it in a more flexible
way.
We'll create 42 latent factors as before.
[Time: 45 minute mark]
We'll use exactly the same embedding input
functions as before. Again, we're going to
have to use lists to store everything.
So in this case all of our embeddings are
going to be in the list, so we go through
each of our characters and create an embedding
input and output for each one, and store each.
Here we're going to define all at once - green
arrow, orange arrow, blue arrow. Here we're
basically saying we've got three different
weight matrices that we want Keras to keep
track of for us.
So the very first hidden state here is going
to take the list of all of our inputs and
that's a tuple of two things -- first an input
to it and second is the ouptput of the embedding,
the very first character, pass that into our
green arrow and that's going to give us our
initial hidden state.
And then this looks exactly the same as we
saw before, but rather than listing separately
we're just going to loop through all of our
1-8 characters, and go ahead and create the
green arrow, the orange arrow, and add the
two together.
So finally, we can take that final hidden
state and put it through our blue arrow to
create our final output.
We can then tell Keras that our model is all
of the embedding inputs for that list we created
together, that's our inputs and our output
that we just created is the output. And we
can go ahead and fit that model.
We would expect this to be more accurate because
it's now got 8 pieces of context in all to
predict.
So previously we were getting 2, and this
time we get down to 1.8. So it's still not
great, but it's an improvement.
We can create the exact same kind of test
as before, so now we can pass 8 characters.
That is our first RNN, now built from scratch.
This kind of RNN, where we're taking a list
and predicting a single thing is most likely
to be useful for things like sentiment analysis.
Remember our sentiment analysis example using
IMDb?
So in this case, we were taking a sequence,
a list of words in a sentence and predicting
whether something is positive sentiment or
negative sentiment. So that would seem like
an appropriate type of use case for this style
of RNN.
So
I wanted to show you something kind of interesting
which you may have noticed, which is when
we created our hidden dense layer (that is
our orange arrow), I did not initialize it
in the default way, but instead I said init="identity".
You may have also noticed that the equivalent
thing was shown in our Keras RNN. Here where
it says inner_init='identity' is referring
to the same thing. It's referring to what
is the initialization that is used for this
orange arrow. How are those weights originally
initialized.
Rather than initializing them randomly, we're
going to initialize them with an identity
matrix. An identity matrix, you may recall
from your linear algebra, is a matrix which
is all 0's, except it is 1's down the diagonal.
So if you multiply any matrix by the identity
matrix, it doesn't change the original matrix
at all. You get back exactly what you started
with.
So in other words, we're going to start off
by initializing our orange arrow, not with
a random matrix, but with a matrix that causes
the hidden state not to change at all. That
makes some intuitive sense.
[Time: 50 minute mark]
It seems reasonable to say, in the absence
of other evidence to the contrary, why don't
we start off by having the hidden state stay
the same until the SGD has a chance to update
that.
But it turns out that it also makes sense
based on an empirical analysis. Since we always
do things taht Geoffrey Hinton tells us to
do, that's good news because this is a paper
by Geoffrey Hinton in which he points out
this rather neat trick, which is if you initialize
an RNN with the hidden weight matrix initialized
to an identity matrix and used rectified linear
units (as we are here), you actually get an
architecture which can get fantastic results
on some reasonably significant problems, including
speech recognition and language modeling.
I don't see this paper referred to or discussed
very often, even though it is well over a
year old now. So I'm not sure if people forgot
about it, or haven't noticed it, or what.
This is a good trick to remember, that you
can get quite a long way doing nothing but
an identity matrix initialization and rectified
linear units just as we have done here to
set up our architecture. That's a nice ittle
trick to remember.
The next thing we're going to do is to make
a couple of minor changes to this diagram.
The first change we're going to make is we're
going to take this rectangle here -- this
rectangle is referring to what is it that
we repeat. And so since in this case we're
predicting character n from characters 1 through
n-1, then this whole area here we're looping
from 2 to n-1 before we generate our output.
So what we're going to do is we're going to
take this triangle and we're going to put
it inside the loop, put it inside the rectangle.
What that means is that every time we loop
through this we're going to generate another
output.
Rather than generating one output at the end
we're going to predict characters 2 through
n using characters 1 through n-1. So it's
going to predict character 2 using character
1, and character 3 using characters 1 and
2, and character 4 using characters 1, 2,
and 3. And so forth.
And so that's what this model will do. It's
nearly exactly the same as the previous model,
except after every single step, after creating
the hidden state on every step, we're going
to create an output every time.
So this is not going to create a single output,
like this does, which predicted a single character,
the last character, the next after the last
character in the sequence, the character n,
these are characters n through n-1.
This is going to create a sequence of characters,
2 through n, using characters 1 through n-1.
Let's now talk about how we would implement
this sequence where we're going to predict
characters 2 through n using characters 1
through n-1.
Why would this be a good idea? There's a few
reasons. One obvious reason is if we're only
predicting one output for every n inputs,
then the number of times that our model has
the the opportunity to backpropagate through
those gradients and improe those weights is
just once for each sequence of characters.
Whereas if we predict characts 2 through n
using characters 1 through characters n-1
we're actually getting a whole lot of feedback
on how the model is coming. So we can backpropogate
n times, or n-1 times every time we do another
sequence.
So there's a lot more learning going on for
the same amount, or nearly the same amount,
of computation.
The other reason this is handy is, as you'll
see in a moment, it's very helpful for creating
RNNs which can do truly long-term dependencies,
or context.
So we're going to start here before look at
how we do context.
Really any time you're doing a sequence to
sequence exercise, you probably want to construct
something of this format, where your triangle
is inside the square rather than outside the
square.
[Time: 55 minute mark]
It's going to look very, very similar. I'm
calling this Returning Sequences because rather
than returning a single character, I'm going
to return a sequence.
And really, most things are the same. Our
character in data (c_in_dat) is identical
to before, so I just commented it out.
And now our character out output (c_out_dat)
isn't just a single character, but it's actually
a list of 8 sequences. In fact, it's exactly
the same as the input except that I have removed
the -1. So it's just shifted over by 1.
So in each sequence, the first character will
be used to predict the second, the first and
second will predict the third character, the
third, second, and first character will predict
the fourth, and so forth.
So you've got a lot more predictions going
on and a lot more opportunity for the model
to learn.
So then we will create our y's just as before
with our x's. And so now our y dataset looks
exactly like our x dataset did, but everything's
just shifted across by one character.
And the models are going to look almost identical
as well. We've got our three dense layers
as before, but we're going to do one other
thing different. Rather than treating the
first character as special, I'm going to move
the character into here. So rather than repeating
from 2 to n-1, I'm going to repeat from 1
to n-1. So I've moved my first character in
to here.
The only thing I have to be careful of is
that we somehow have to initialize our hidden
state to something. So we're going to initialize
our hidden state to a vector of 0's.
So here we do that. We say we're going to
have to have something to initialize our hidden
state (we're going to feed it a vector of
0's shortly). So our initial hidden state
is just going to be the result of that.
And our loop is identical to before, but at
the end of every loop, we're going to append
this output. So we're now going to have 8
outputs for ever sequence instead of just
1.
And so now our model has two changes. The
first is it's got an array of outputs, and
we have to add the thing that we're going
to use to store our vector of 0's somewhere,
so we're going to put this into our input
as well.
Question: Back up the diagram, could you say
what the box is again?
Answer: The box refers to the area that we
repeat.
So initially we repeated the character n input
going in to here, and the hidden state going
back onto itself, from 2 through n-1. So the
box is the thing which I'm looping through
all those times.
This time I'm looping through this whole thing.
Character input coming in, generating a hidden
state and creating an output. Repeating that
whole thing every time.
And so now you can see, creating the output
is inside the loop, rather than outside the
loop -- so we end up with an array of outputs.
So our model is nearly exactly the same as
before, it's just got two changes.
So now when we fit our model, we're going
to add an array of 0's to the start of our
inputs. Our outputs are going to be those
lists of 8, offset by 1.
We can go ahead and train this. You can see
as as we train it we don't just have 1 loss,
we have 8 losses. And that's because every
one of those 8 outputs has its own loss.
As you would expect, our ability to predict
the first character, using nothing but a vector
of 0's is pretty limited. So that very quickly
flattens out.
Whereas our ability to predict the 8th character,
well it has a lot more context. It has 7 characters
of context. So you can see that the 8th character's
loss keeps on improving.
By a few epochs, we have a significantly better
loss than we did before. So this is what a
sequence model looks like.
You can see a sequence model, when we test
it we pass in a sequence like this, and after
every character it returns its guess.
After seeing a space, it guesses the next
will be a "t".
[Time: 1 hour mark]
After seeing a space "t", the next thing will
be an "h". After seeing a space "t" "h", the
next thing will be an "e" and so forth.
And so you can see it's predicting some pretty
reasonable things here.
After seeing space "p" "a" "r" "t", it expect
that will be the end of the word. And it was.
After seeing "p" "a" "r" "t" space, it's guessing
that the next word is going to be "o" "f".
So it's able to use sequences of 8 to create
a context, which isn't really it, but it's
an improvement.
How do we do this same thing with Keras? With
Keras, it's identical to our previous model
except that we have to use the different input
and oputput arrays, just like I just showed
you, so the whole sequence of labels and the
whole sequence of inputs.
And the second thing we have to do is return
one parameter, which is return_sequences=True.
return_sequences=True simply says rather than
putting the triangle outside the loop, put
the triangle inside the loop. And so return
an output every time you go to another time-step
rather than returning just a single output
at the end.
So it's that easy in Keras. I add this return_sequences=True.
I don't have to change my data at all, other
than some very minor dimensionality changes,
and I can just fit it.
As you can see, I get a pretty similar loss
function to what I did before. And I can build
something that looks pretty much like we had
before and generate some pretty similar results.
So that's how we create this sequence model
with Keras.
Then how do you create all state. How do you
generate a model which is able to handle long-term
dependencies.
To generate model that understands long-term
dependencies, we can't any more present our
pieces of data at random. So far, we've always
been using the default when we do model.fit,
which is shuffle=True. So it's passing across
these sequences of 8 in a random order.
If we're going to do something which understands
long-term dependencies, the first thing we're
going to have to do is use shuffle=False.
The second thing we're going to have to do
is we're going to have to stop passing in
an array of 0's as my starting point every
time around. So effectively what I want to
do is I want to pass in my array of 0's at
the very start, right as I start training,
but then at the end of myt sequence of 8,
rather than going back to initialize to 0's,
I actualy want to keep this hidden state.
So then I just start my next sequence of 8
with this hidden state exactly where it was
before. And that's going to allow it to build
up arbitrarily long dependencies.
So in Keras, that's actually as simple as
adding one additional parameter. And the additional
parameter is called stateful.
So when you say stateful=True, what that tells
Keras is that at the end of each sequence,
don't reset the hidden activations to 0, but
leave them as they are.
And that means that we have to make sure that
we pass shuffle=False when we train it.
So it's now going to pass the first 8 characters,
the second 8 characters of the book, the third
8 characters of the book, leaving the hidden
state untouched between each one. And therefore,
it's allowing it to continue to build up as
much state as it wants to.
Training these stateful models is a lot harder
than training the models that we've seen so
far. The reason is this: in these stateful
models, this orange arrow, this single weight
matrix it's being applied to the hidden matrix
not 8 times, but 100,000 times (or more, depending
on how big your text is).
[Time: 1.05 hour mark]
And just imagine - if this weight matrix was
even slightly poorly scaled, like if there
was just one number in it which was a bit
too high, then effectively that number is
going to be to the power of 100,000. It's
being multiplied again and again and again.
So what can happen is you get this problem
called exploding gradients. In some ways,
it's better described as exploding activations.
Because we're multipying this by almost the
same weight matrix each time, if that weight
matrix is anything less than perfectly scaled,
then it's going to make our hidden matrix
disappear off into infinity.
So we have to be very careful how to train
these. Indeed these kind of long-term dependency
models were thought of as impossible to train
for a while. Until some folks in the '90's,
I guess, came up with a model called the LSTM
model. Long Short Term Memory model.
In the Long Short Term Memory model (we'll
learn more about it next week, we're actually
going to create it ourselves from scratch)
we replaced this loop here with a loop where
there's a neural network inside the loop that
decides how much of this state matrix to keep,
and how much to use at each activation.
So by having a neural network that actually
controls how much state is kept and how much
is used, it can actually learn how to avoid
those gradient explosions. It can actually
learn how to ceate an effective sequence.
So we're going ot look at that a lot more
next week, but for now I will tell you that
when I try to run this using a simple RNN,
even with an identity matrix initialization
and relu's, I had not luck at all.
So I had to replace it with an LSTM. Even
that wasn't enough. I had to have well-scaled
inputs, so I added a batch noralization layer
after my emeddings. After I did those things,
then I could fit it.
It still ran pretty slowly. Before I was getting
4 seconds per epoch, now it's 13 seconds per
epoch. The reason is that it's much harder
to parallelize this, it has to do this sequence
in order. So it's going to be slower. But
over time, it does eventually get substantially
better loss than I had before, and that's
because it's able to keep track of and use
this state.
Question: Doesn't it make sense to use batchnorm
in the loop as well?
Answer: That's a good question. Definitely
maybe. There's been a lot of discussion and
papers about this recently. There's a method
called layer normalization, which is a method
specifically designed to work well with RNNs.
Standard batchnorm doesn't.
It turns out it's actually very easy to do
layer normalization with Keras using a couple
of simple parameters you can provide to the
normal batchnorm constructor. In my experiments,
that hasn't worked so well. I will show you
a lot more about that in just a few minutes.
Stateful models are great. We're going to
look at some very successful stateful models
in just a moment. Just be aware that they
are more challenging to train. You'll see
another thing I had to do here, I had to reduce
the learning rate in the middle. You just
have to be so careful of these exploding gradient
problems.
So let me show you what I did with this. I
tried to create a stateful model which worked
as well as I could.
So I took the same Nietzsche data as before,
and I tried splitting it into chunks of 40,
rather than 8 so each one could do more work.
So here are some examples of those chunks
of 40.
I built a model that was slightly more sophisticated
than the previous one in two ways:
The first is, it has an RNN feeding in to
an RNN. That's kind of a crazy idea, so I
brought a picture.
So an RNN feeding in to an RNN means that
the output is actually no longer going to
an output. Actually the output of the first
RNN is becoming the input to the second RNN.
[Time: 1.10 hour mark]
So the character input goes in to our first
RNN, and the state updates as per usual. And
then each time we go through the sequence,
it feeds the result to the state of the second
RNN.
Why is this useful? Because it means that
this output is now coming from not just a
single dense matrix with a single dense matrix
here, it's actually going through 3 dense
matrices and activation functions. So I now
have a deep neural network (assuming two layers
count as deep) between my first character
and my first output.
And then indeed between every hidden state
and every output, I now have multiple inputs.
So effectively what this is allowing us to
do is to create a deep neural net for all
of our activations. And that turns out to
work really well because the structure of
language is pretty complex and so it's nice
to be able to give it a more flexible function.
That's the first thing I do. And it's easy
to create that. Just copy and paste whatever
your RNN line is. You can see I've now added
dropout inside my RNN.
As I talked about before, adding dropout inside
your RNN turns out to be a really good idea.
There's a really great paper about that recently
showing this is a great way to regularize
an RNN.
And then the second change I made ... rather
than going straight from the RNN to our output,
I went through a dense layer.
Now there's something you might have noticed
here, our dense layers have this extra word
in the front. Why would they have this extra
word in the front -- TimeDistributed.
It might be easier to understand by looking
at this earlier sequence model with Keras.
Note that the the output of our RNN is not
just a vector of length 256, but 8 vectors
of length 256, because it's actually predicting
8 outputs.
So we can't just have a normal dense layer
because a normal dense layer needs a single
dimension that it can squish down.
So in this case, what we actually want to
do is we want to create 8 separate dense layers
in the output, one for every one of the outputs.
And so what TimeDistributed does is it says
whatever the layer in the middle, I want you
to create 8 copies of it (or however many
this dimension is). And every one of those
copies is going to share the same weight matrix,
which is exactly what we want.
So the short version here is, in Keras every
time you say return_sequences=True, any dense
layers after that will have to have TimeDistributed
wrapped around them, because we want to create
not just one dense layer, but 8 dense layers.
So in this case, since we're saying return_sequence=True,
we then have a TimeDistributed dense layer,
dropout, and then another TimeDistributed
dense layer.
Question: Does the first RNN complete before
it passes to the second, or is it layer by
layer?
Answer: No, it's operating exactly like this.
My initialization starts, this character comes
in. At the output of that is the hidden state
for my next hidden state and the output that
goes into my second LSTM.
The best way to think about this actually
would probably be to draw it in the unrolled
form. Then you'll realize there's nothing
magical about this at all. In the unrolled
form, it just looks like a pretty standard
neural network.
Question: What's dropout_U and droput_W?
Answer: We'll talk about that more next week.
In an LSTM, there's kind of like little neural
nets that control how the state updates work.
And this is talking about how the dropout
works in these little neural nets.
Question: And when stateful=False, can you
explain again what is reset after each training
example?
Answer: The best way to describe that is to
show us doing it.
[Time: 1.15 hour mark]
Remember that the RNNs that we built are identical
to what Keras does, or close enough to identical.
So let's go and have a look at our version
of return sequences. You can see that what
we did was we created a matrix of 0's that
we stuck on to the front of our inputs. So
every set of 8 characters now starts with
a vector of 0's.
So in other words, this initialize to zeros
happens every time we finish a sequence. So
in other words, this hidden state gets initialized
to 0 at the end of every sequence.
And it's this hidden state which is where
all these dependencies and state is kept.
So doing that is resetting the state every
time we look at a new sequence.
So when we say stateful=False, it only does
this initialize to zero step once at the very
start, or when we explicitly ask it to.
So when I actually run this model .. the way
I do it is wrote a little thing called run_epochs
that goes model.reset_states and then does
a fit on one epoch, which is what you really
want. At the end of your entire works of Nietzsche,
you reset your state because you're going
to go back to the very start and start again.
So with this multi-layer LTSM going into a
neural net, I then tried seeing how that goes.
And remember with our simpler versions, we
were getting 1.6, this was the best we could
do.
After one epoch, instead of just printing
out one letter, I'm starting with a whole
sequence of letters and asking it to generate
a sequence.
You can see it starts out by generating a
pretty rubbishy sequence.
Question: In a double LSTM layer model, what
is the input to the second LSTM in addition
to the output of the first LSTM?
Answer. In addition to the output of the first
LSTM is the previous output of its own hidden
state.
After a few more epochs, it's starting to
create some actually proper English words,
although the English words are not necessarily
making a lot of sense.
So I keep running epochs. At this point, it's
starting to generate chapters. In this book,
the chapters always start with a number and
then an equals sign.
It hasn't learned how to close quotes, it's
not really saying anything useful. A
So anyway, I kind of ran this overnight. I
then seeded it with a larger amount of data
and I started getting some pretty reasonable
resuls. "Shreds into one's own suffering"
sounds exactly like the kind of thing Nietzsche
might say.
"Religions have acts done by man ..." It's
not all perfect, but it's not all bad.
Interestingly, this sequence here (SACRIFIZIA
DELL' INTELLETO) when I looked it up, it actually
appears in his book. And this makes sense,
right?
It's a kind of over-fitting in a sense. He
loves talking in all caps. He only does it
from time to time. And so once it starts writing
something in all caps that looks like this
phrase that only appeared once, and it's very
unique, there was kind of no other way that
it could have finished it.
So sometimes you get like this little rare
phrases that basically it's plagiarized directly
from Nietzsche.
So I didn't stop there because I started thinking
about how could we improve this. It was at
this point that I started thinking about batch
normalization, fiddling around with all different
types of batch normalization and layer normalization,
and discovered this interesting insight which
is the very best approach was when I simply
applied batch normalization to the embedding
layer.
[Time: 1.20 hour mark]
So I wanted to show you what happened when
I applied batch normalization to the embedding
layer, this is the training curve I got - over
epochs, this is my loss. With no batch normalization
on the embedding layer, this was my loss.
So you can see, this one's starting to flatten
out, this one really wasn't and this one was
training a lot quicker.
So then I tried training it with batchnorm
on the embedding layer overnight and I was
pretty stunned by the results. This was my
seeding text, and after 1,000 epochs, this
is what it came up with. It's got all kind
of actually pretty interesting little things.
"perhaps some m...orality equals self-glorification".
This is really cool - "For there are holy
eyes to Schopenhauer's blind", "in reality
we must step above it". You can see that it's
led to closed quotes, even when those quotes
were open a long time ago.
If we weren't using stateful, it would have
never learned how to do this. And I've looked
up these words in the original text and pretty
much none of these phrases appear. This is
actually a genuine novely produced piece of
text.
It's not perfect by any means, but considering
that this is only doing it character by character,
using nothing but a 42 long embedding matrix
for each character. There's no pre-trained
vectors or anything. It's just a pretty short
600,000 character epoch, I think it's done
a pretty amazing job of creating a pretty
good model.
So there's all kinds of things you can do
with a model like this. The most obvious one
would be if you were producing a software
keyboard for a mobile phone, for example,
you could use this to have a pretty accurate
guess as to what they're going to type next
and correct it for them. You could do something
similar on a word basis.
But more generally, you could do something
like anomoly detection. You could generate
a sequence which is predicting what the rest
of the sequence is going to look like for
the next hour, and then recognize if something
falls outside of what your prediction was
- then you know there's been some kind of
anomoly. There's all kinds of things you can
do with these kinds of models.
I think that's pretty fun and I want to show
you something else that's pretty fun, which
is to build an RNN from scratch in Theano.
And what we're going to do is we're going
to try to work up to next week where we're
going to build an RNN from scratch in numpy.
And we're also going to build an LSTM from
scratch in Theano.
The reason we're doing this is next week is
our last class in this part of the course
and I want us to leave feeling like we really
understand the detail of what's going on behind
the scenes.
The main thing I wanted to teach in this class
was the applied stuff. Practical tips on how
you build a sequence model, but I know that
to debug and build your models and architecutre
and stuff, it really helps to understand what's
going on.
Particularly in the current situation where
the libraries and the tools are available,
but are not that mature. They still require
a whole lot of manual stuff, so I do want
to explain a bit more about what's going on
behind the scenes.
So in order to build an RNN in Theano, I'm
going to first of all make a small change
to our Keras model, which is that I'm going
to use one-hot encoding.
I don't know if you noticed this, but we did
something pretty cool in all of our models
so far, which is that we never actually one-hot
encoded our output.
Question: Will TimeDistributedDense take longer
to train than dense, and is it really that
important to use time-distributed dense?
[Time: 1.25 hour mark]
Answer: So if you don't add TimeDistributedDense
to a model where return_sequences=True, it
literally won't work. It won't compile, because
you're trying to predict 8 things and the
dense layer is going to stick that all into
1 thing and say there is a mismatch in your
dimensions. But no, it doesn't really add
much time because that's something that can
be very easily parallelized. And since a lot
of things in RNNs can't be easily parallelized,
there generally is plenty of room in your
GPU to do work, so that should be fine.
But the short answer is you have to use it
otherwise it won't compile.
I wanted to point out something which is that
in all of our models so far, we did not one-hot
encode our outputs. So our outputs look like
this, they were sequences of numbers.
Always before we've had to one-hot encode
our outputs to use them. It turns out that
Keras has a very cool loss function called
sparse-categorical_crossentropy. This is identical
to categorical_crossentropy, but rather than
taking a one-hot encoded target, it takes
an integer target. Basically it acts as if
you had one-hot encoded it. So basically it
does the indexing into it diretly.
So this is a really helpful thing to know
about because when you have a lot of output
categories, like for example, you're doing
a word model, you could have 100,000 output
categories. There's no way you want to create
a matrix that's 100,000 long. Nearly all 0's
for every single word in your output. So by
using sparce_categorical_crossentropy, you
can just forget the whole one-hot encoding.
You don't have to do it; Keras implicitly
does it for you without ever explcitly doing
it, it just does it a direct lookup matrix.
However, because I want to make things simpler
for us to understand, I'm going to recreate
our Keras model using one-hot encoding. So
I'm going to take exactly the same model we
had before, with return_sequences=True, but
this time I'm going to use normal categorical_crossentropy,
and the other thing I'm doing is I don't have
an embedding layer.
So since I don't have an embedding layer,
I have to one-hot encode my inputs. So you
can see I'm calling to_categorical on all
of my input and to_categorical on all of my
outputs.
So now the shape is 75,000x8x86, so this is
the one-hot encoding direction - there's eighty-five
0's and one 1. So we fit this in exactly the
same way and we get exactly the same answer.
The only reason I'm doing that is I want to
use one-hot encoding for the version we're
going to create ourselves from scratch.
So we haven't really looked at Theano before,
but particularly if you come back next year,
as we start to try to add more and more stuff
on top of Keras, or in to Keras, increasingly
you'll find yourself wanting to use Theano
because Theano is the language that Keras
is using behind the scenes, and therefore
it's kind of the language which you can use
to extend it.
Of course, you can use TensorFlow as well,
but we're using Theano in this course because
it's much easier for this kind of application.
So let's learn to use Theano. In the process
of doing it in Theano, we're going to have
to force ourselves to think through a lot
more of the details than we have before because
Theano doesn't have any of the conveniences
that Keras has. There's no such thing as a
layer. We're going to have to think about
all of the weight matrices and activation
functions ourself.
So let me show you how it works. In Theano,
there's this concept of a variable, and a
variable is something that we basically define
like so.
[Time: 1.30 hour mark]
We can say there is a variable which is a
matrix, which I will call t_inp. There is
a variable which is a matrix, which I will
call t_outp. There is a variable which is
a vector that we will call t_h0. Now what
these are all saying is that these are things
that we will give values to later.
Programming in Theano is very different to
programmming in normal python. The reason
for this is Theano's job in life is to provide
a way for you to describe a computation that
you want to do and then it's going to compile
it to the GPU, and then it's going to run
it on the GPU.
So, it's going to be a little more complex
to work in Theano because Theano isn't going
to be something where we say "do this" and
then it does this. Instead we're going to
build up a computation graph. It's going to
be a series of steps. We're going to say in
the future, I'm going to give you some data,
and when I do I want you to do these steps.
Rather than actually starting off by giving
it data, we start off by describing the types
of data that when we do give it data, we're
going to give it.
So eventually we're going to give it some
input data, we're going to give it some output
data, and we're going to give it some way
of initializing the first hidden state. Also,
we'll give it a learning rate.
So then we can create a list of those - this
is all of the arguments - that we're going
to have to provide to Theano later on. There's
no data here, nothing's been computed. We're
just telling Theano that these things are
going to be used in the future.
The next thing that we're going to do (because
we're going to build this) is we're going
to build all of the pieces in all of these
layer operations. Specifically, we're going
to have to create the weight matrix and the
bias matrix for the orange arrow, the weight
matrix and the bias matrix for the green arrow,
the weight matrix and the bias matrix for
the blue arrow. Because that's what these
layer operations are, they're matrix multiply
followed by an activation function.
So I've created some functions to do that.
W_h is what I'm going to call the weights
and biases of my hidden layer, W_x will be
my weights and biases of my input, and W_y
will be my weights and biases of my outputs.
So to create them I have this function called
wgts_and_bias, which I tell it the size of
the matrix that I want to create. So the matrix
that goes from input to hidden [W_x=wgts_and_biases(n_input,
n_hidden)] therefore has n input rows, and
n hidden columns.
So weights_and_bias is here, and it's going
to return a tuple. It's going to return our
weights and it's going to return our bias.
So how do we create the weights? To create
the weights, we first of all calculate the
scale of the random numbers we're going to
use, the square root of 2 over n, the number
of rows. We then create those numbers using
the normal numpy random number function, and
then we use a special Theano keyword, shared.
What shared does is it says to Theano, this
data is something I'm going to want you to
pass off to the GPU later and keep track of.
So as soon as you wrap something in shared,
it kind of belongs to Theano now.
So here is a weight matrix that belongs to
Theano. Here is a vector of 0's that belongs
to Theano, and that's our initial bias.
So we're initialized our weights and our bias.
So we can do that for our inputs and we can
do that for our outputs.
And then for our hidden (which is the orange
arrow, remember), we're going to do something
slightly different, which is we will initialize
it using an identity matrix.
Rather amuzingly in numpy, it is "eye" for
identity [np.eye].
So this is the identity matrix of n x n [np.eye(n,dtype=np.float32))].
So that's our initial weights, and our initial
bias is exactly as before, it's a vector of
zeros.
[Time: 1.35 hour mark]
So you can see we had to manually construct
each of these 3 weight matrices and bias vectors.
It's nice to now stick them all into a single
list. Python has thing thing, chain.from_iterable,
which basically takes all these tuples and
dumps them altogether into a single list.
So this now has all 6 weight matrices and
bias vectors.
Now we have defined initial contents of each
of these arrows, and we've also defined kind
of symbolically the concept that we're going
to have something to initialize it with here,
something to initialize it with here, and
some target we have to initialize it with
here.
And the next thing we have to do is to tell
Theano what happens each time we take a single
step of this RNN.
On the GPU, you can't use a for loop. The
reason you can't use a for loop is the GPU
wants to be able to parallelize things. It
wants to do things at the same time. And a
for loop, by definition, can't do the second
part of the loop until it's done the first
part of the loop.
I don't know if we'll have time to do it in
this course or not, but there's a very neat
result which shows there's something very
similar to a for loop that you can parallelizie,
and it's called a scan operation.
A scan operation is something that is defined
in a very particular way. A scan operation
is something where you call some function
for every element of some sequence, and at
every point the function returns some output.
And the next time that function is called,
it's going to get the output of the previous
time you called it, along with the next element
of the sequence.
So I've got an example of it
in python. Here is the definition of scan,
and here is an example.
Let's start with the example. I'm going to
do a scan and the function I'm going to use
is to add two things together. I'm going to
start off with 0, and I'm going to pass in
a range of numbers from 1-4.
So what scan does, it starts out the first
time through it's going to call this function,
with that argument, and the first element
of this. It's going to be 0+0=0.
The second time it's going to call this function
with the second element of this, along with
the result of the previous call. It will be
0+1=1.
The next time through it's going to call this
function with the result of the previous call,
plus the next element of this range. So 1+2=3.
So you can see this scan operation defines
a cumulative sum, you can see the definition
of scan here. We're going to be returning
an array of results.
Initially we take our starting point, 0, and
that's our inital value for previous answer
from scan. Then we're going to go through
everything in the sequence (which is 0-4),
we're going to apply this function (which
was in this case add things up), we're going
to apply it to the previous result along with
the next element in the sequence, stick the
result at the end of our list, set the previous
result to what we just got, and then go back
to the next element in the sequence.
So it may be very suprising (hopefully it
is very surprising because it's an extraordinary
result), but it is possible to write a parallel
version of this. If you can turn your algorithm
into a scan, you can reun it on a CPU.
So our job is to turn this RNN into something
that we can put in this kind of form. So let's
do that.
So the function we're going to call on each
step though is the function called step. And
the function called step is going to be something
which hopefully will not be very surprising
to you. It's going to be something which takes
our input, x, and does a dot product by the
weight matrix we saw earlier, W_x, and adds
on that bias that we calculated earlier, b_x.
[Time: 1.40 hour mark]
And then we do the same thing, taking our
previous hidden state and multipying it by
the weight matrix - so the hidden state, and
adding the biases of the hidden state - and
puts the whole thing through an activation
function, relu.
So
we had one bit which was calculating our previous
hidden state and putting it through the hidden
state weight matrix.
It was taking our next input and putting it
through the input one and then adding the
two together.
So that's what we have here -- [h=nnet.relu(T.dot(x,W_x)+b_x+T.dot(h,W_h)+h_h)]
-- the x by W_x, the h by W_h, then adding
the two together along with the biases, and
then put that through an activation function.
So once we've done that, we now want to create
an output every single time. And so our output
is going to be exactly the same thing -- it's
going to take the result of our hidden state
(which we call h), multiply it by the output's
weight vector and adding on the bias. This
time we're going to use softmax [y=nnet.softmax(T.dot(h,W_y)+b_y)].
So you can see that this sequence here is
describing how to do one of these things.
This, therefore, defines what we want to do
each step through. At the end of that we're
going to return the hidden state we have so
far and our output. That's what's going to
happen each step.
So the sequence that we're going to pass in
to it ... well, we're not going to give it
any data yet because remember all we're doing
is we're describing a computation. So for
now, we're just telling it that it will be
a matrix, we're saying we're going to pass
you a matrix.
It also needs a starting point. The starting
point again, we're going to provide to you
an initial value for our hidden state, but
we haven't done it yet. And then finally in
Theano you have to tell it what are all the
other things ared passed in a function, and
we're going to pass it that whole list of
weights. That's what we have here. The x,
the hidden, and then all of the weights and
biases.
So let's now describe how to execute a whole
sequence of steps for an RNN. We've now just
described how to do this, to Theano. We haven't
given it any data to do it, we've just set
up the computation.
And so when that computation is run, it's
going to return two things because step returns
two things. It's going to return the hidden
state and it's going to return our output
activations.
So now we need to calculate our error.
So our error will be the categorical_crossentropy
(these things are all part of Theano, using
some Theano functions here). We're going to
compare our output that came out of our scan
and we're going to compare it to what? ... we
don't know yet, but it will be a matrix. Then
once you do that, add it all together.
Now here's the amazing thing, every step we're
going to want to apply SGD. Which means every
step we're going to want to take the derivative
of this whole thing with respect to all of
the weights, and use that, along with the
learning rate, to update all the weights.
In Theano, that's how you do it. You just
say please tell me the gradient of this function
with repect to the inputs and Theano will
symbolically automatically calculate all of
your derivatives for you. So that's very nearly
magic. We don't have to worry about derivatives
because it's going to calculate them all for
us.
So at this point, I now have a function that
calculates our loss and that calculates all
of the gradients that we need with respect
to all of the different weights and parameters
that we have.
So we're now ready to build our final function.
Our final function as input takes all of our
outputs, that is these four things, [t_h0,t_inp,t_outp,lr],
which is the four things we told it we're
going to need later.
[Time: 1.45 hour mark]
The thing that's going to create the output
is this error, which was this output.
And then at each step it's going to do some
updates. What are the updates it's going to
do? The updates it's going to do is the result
of this function, OrderedDict. This little
function is something that is going to map
every one of our weights to that weight minus
each one of our gradients times the learning
rate.
So it's going to update every weight to itself
minus its gradient times the learning rate.
So basically what Theano does (it's got thing
thing called updates), it says every time
you calculate the next step, I want you to
change your shared variables as follows, so
there's our list of changes to make. So that's
it.
So we use our one-hot encoded x's and our
one-hot encoded y's and we have to now manually
create our own loop. Theano doesn't have any
built-in stuff for us. So we're going to go
through every element of our input and we're
going to say that function that we just created
and now we have to pass in all of these inputs.
So we finally have to pass in a value for
the initial hidden state (t_h0), the input
(t_inp), the target (t_outp) and the learning
rate (lr). So this is where we get to do it,
when we finally call it here.
So here's our initial hidden state (just a
bunch of zeros), our input, our output, and
our learning rate (which we set to .01). And
then I have something here that says every
1,000 times, print our the error. As you can
see, over time it works.
At the end of learning, I create a new Theano
function, which takes some piece of input
along with some initial hidden state, and
it produces, not the loss, but the output.
Question: Are we using gradient_descent and
not stochastic_gradient_descent here?
Answer: We're using stochastic_gradient_descent
with a minibatch size of 1. So gradient_descent
without stochastic acutally means your using
gradient_descent with a minibatch size of
the whole dataset. This is kind of the opposite
of that. I think this is called online gradient
descent. That's a good question, thank you.
So remember earlier on we had this thing to
calculate the vector of outputs. So now to
do our testing, we're going to create a new
function which goes from our input to a vector
of outputs. So our prediction will be to take
that function, pass it in our initial hidden
state and some input, and that's going to
give us our predictions.
So if we call it, we can now say let's now
grab some sequence of text, pass it to our
function to get some predictions and let's
see what it does. After "t" it expected "h",
after "t" "h", it expected "e". After "t"
"h" "e", it expected space. After "t" "h"
"e" "n" "?" it wanted a space. After "t" "he"
"e" "n" "?" " " it wanted a "T". And so forth.
You can see here that we have successfully
built an RNN from scratch using Theano.
That's been a very, very quick runthough.
My goal tonight is to get to a point where
you can start to look at this during the week
and kind of see all the pieces, because next
week we're going to try and build an LSTN
in Theano. Which is going to mean that I want
you to, by next week, kind of feel like you've
got a good understanding of what's going on.
So please ask. Post questions on the forum,
look at the documentation and so forth.
The next thing we're going to do after that
is we're going to build an RNN without using
Theano. We're going to use pure numpy, and
that means we're not going to be able to use
T.grad, we're going to have to calculate the
gradients by hand.
Hopefully that will be a useful exercise in
really understanding what's going on in back-propogation.
[Time: 1.50 hour mark]
So I kind of want to make sure you feel like
you've got information to get started with
Theano this week. Does anybody want to ask
any questions about this?
Question: So maybe this is a bit too far away
from what we did today but how would you apply
an RNN to imaging something other than text?
Is that something that's worth doing? If so,
what changes about it?
Answer: Yes, sure. The main way an RNN is
applied to images is what we looked at last
week, attentional models, which is where you
basically say - given the part of the image
you're currently looking at, which part does
it make sense to look at next? This is most
useful on
really big images where you can't really look
at the whole thing at once, you can only look
at a little bit at a time.
Another way that RNNs are very useful for
images is for captioning images. We'll talk
a lot more about this in next year's course,
but think about this in the meantime.
If we've got an image, then a CNN can turn
that into a vector representation of that
image. For example, we can chuck it through
VGG and take the penultimate layer's activations.
There's a lot of things we can do. In some
way, we can take an image and turn it into
some vector representation of that.
We can do the same thing to a sentence. We
can take a sentence consisting of a number
of words and we can stick that through an
RNN and at the end of it, we will get some
state. And that state is also just a vector.
What we can then do is learn a neural network
which maps the picture to the text, assuming
that this sentence was originally a caption
that had been created for this image.
And so in that way if we can learn a mapping
from some representation of an image that
came out of a CNN to some representation of
a sentence
that came out of an RNN, then we could basically
reverse that to generate captions for an image.
So basically what we could then do is we could
take some new image that we'd never seen before,
send it through the CNN to get our state out,
then we could figure out what RNN state we
would expect would be attached to that based
on this neural net that we had to learn and
then we can basically do a sequence generation
like we have been today and generate a sequence
of words. And this is roughly how these image
captioning systems work.
Finally, the only other way in which I've
seen RNNs applied to images is for like really
big 3D images for example, like in medical
imaging. So if you have some MRI that is basically
a series of layers, it's too big to look at
the whole thing.
Instead you can use an RNN to start in the
top corner, then look one pixel to the left
and one pixel across and then one pixel back
and then go down to the next layer. You can
gradually look one pixel at a time. It can
do that and gradually cover the whole thing.
That way it's gradually able to generate state
about what is contained in this 3D volume.
[Time: 1.55 hour mark]
This is not something which is very widely
used, at least at this point. But I think
it's worth thinking about. You could combine
this with a CNN. Maybe you could have a CNN
that looks at large chunks of this MRI at
a time and generate state for each of these
chunks and then maybe you could use an RNN
to go through the chunks.
There's all kinds of ways that you can combine
CNNs and RNNs.
Question: Can you build a custom layer in
Theano and mix it with Keras.
Answer: For sure. In fact, it's incredibly
easy.
So if you do a google search for "Keras custom
theano layer", there's lots of examples of
them.
They're generally in the github for Keras
where people will kind of show, I was trying
to build this layer and I had this problem.
But it's kindf a good way to see how to build
them.
The other thing I find really useful to
do is to actually look at the definition of
the layers in Keras.
One of the things I actually did was I created
this little thing called py_path, which allow
me to put in any python module, and it returns
the directory that that module is defined
in.
So I can go have a look at how any particular
layer is defined. So let's say I want to look
at pooling -- here is a MaxPooling1D layer,
and it's defined in 9 lines of code. Generally
speaking, you can see that layers don't take
very much code at all.
Question: Could we, given a caption, create
an image?
Answer: Yes, you can absolutely create an
image from a caption. There's a lot of image
generation stuff going on at the moment. It's
not at a point that it's useful for anything
in practice; it's more like an interesting
research journey.
Generally speaking this is in the area called
generative models. And we'll be looking at
generative models next year because they're
very important for us in semi-supervised learning.
Question: What would give the best performance
on a document classification - a CNN, an RNN,
or both?
Answer: That's a great, great question.
So let's go back to sentiment analysis. To
remind ourselves, when we looked at sentiment
analysis for IMDb, the best result we got
came from a multi-sized convolutional neural
network, where we took a bunch of convolutional
neural networks of various sizes. A simple
convolutional neural network was nearly as
good - just this simple convolutional neural
network was nearly as good.
I actually tried an LSTM for this and I found
the accuracy that I got was less good than
the accuracy of a CNN. And I think the reason
for this is when you have a whole movie review
(which is a few paragraphs) the information
that you can get just by looking at a few
words at a time is enough to tell you if this
is a positive review or a negative review.
If you see a sequence of 5 words like "This
is totally shit", then you probably learn
that's not a good thing. If they put "This
is totally awesome", that's a good thing.
[Time: 2 hour mark]
The amount of nuance built into reading word
by word the entire review, it just doesn't
seem there's any need for that in practice.
Once you get to a certain sized piece of text
(like a paragraph or two) there doesn't seem
to be any sign that RNNs are helpful, at least
at this stage.
So before I close off, I just want to show
you 2 little tricks. I don't spend enough
time showing you cool little tricks, so when
I was working with Brad today, I realized
that there were two little tricks that I realized
other people might like to learn about.
The first trick I want to point out to you
is if you want to learn about how a function
works, what would be a quick way to figure
it out? If you've got a function and you hit
[SHIFT][TAB], all of the parameters to it
will pop up.
If you hit [SHIFT][TAB] twice, the documentation
That was one little tip I wanted you guys
to know about because I think it's pretty
handy.
The second little tip that you might not be
aware of is that you can actually run the
python debugger inside your JuPyteR notebook.
Today we were trying to do that when we were
trying to debug our pure python RNN.
So you can see an example of that ...
let's say we were having some problem inside
our loop here. Type in "import pdb", the python
debugger. Then you can set a breakpoint anywhere,
pdb.set_trace() sets a breakpoint.
So now if I run that, as soon as it gets to
here, it pops up a little dialog box. At this
point, I can look at anything. For example,
I can say what's the value of err at this
point. I can say what are the lines I'm about
to execute, I can say execute the next one
line.
If you want to learn about the python debugger,
just google python debugger. Learning to use
the debugger is one of the most helpful things
because it lets you step through each step,
see the values for your variables, and do
all kinds of stuff like that.
So those were two little tips that I will
leave you with ... and leave you on a high
note.