So I guess I've noticed during the week from
some of the questions that I've been seeing
that the idea of a convolution is still a
little counter-intuitive or surprising to
some people. I feel like the only way I know
to teach things effectively is by creating
a spreadsheet, so here we are.
This is the famous number 7 from Lesson 0,
and I just copied and pasted the numbers into
a spreadsheet. They're not all exactly 0,
they're actually floats just rounded off.
As you can see, I'm using conditional coloring
and you can see the shape of the number 7
here.
So I wanted to show you exactly what a convolution
does, and specifically what a convolution
does in a deep-learning neural network. So
we are generally using modern convolutions,
and that means a 3x3 convolution.
So here is a 3x3 convolution and I have just
randomly generated 9 random numbers, so that
is a filter. Here is my second filter, 9 more
random numbers. So this is what we do in Keras,
when we ask for a convolutonal layer the first
thing we pass it is how many filters we want,
that is how many of these little random matrices
do we want it to build for us. So in this
cass if I pass convolution2D, the first parameter
would be 2 and the second parameter would
be 3,3.
So what happens to this little random matrix?
In order to calculate the very first item
it takes the sum of the blue stuff (those
9) times the red stuff (those 9) all added
together.
So let's go down here where it gets darker.
How does this get calculated? This is equal
to these 9 times these 9. And when I say "times"
I mean element-wise times -- the top left
by the top left, the middle by the middle
and so forth, and all them all together.
That's all a convolution is. It's just as
you go through, we take the corresponding
3x3 area in the image and we multiply each
of these 9 things by these 9 things, and then
we add those 9 products together. That's it
-- that's a convolution. So there's really
nothing particularly weird or confusing about
it. And I'll make this available in class
so that you can have a look.
You can see that when I get to the top left
corner, I can't move further left and up because
I've reached the edge. And this is why when
you do a 3x3 convolution without zero padding,
you lose one pixel on each edge, because you
can't push this 3x3 any further.
So if we go down to the bottom left, we can
see again the same thing - gets stuck in the
corner. So that's why you can see that my
resulting matrix is one row less than my starting
matrix.
So I did this for two different filters. So
here's my second filter and you can see when
I calculate this one it's exactly the same
thing, it's these 9 times each of these 9
added together. And these are just 9 other
random numbers.
That's how we start with our 2 convolutional
filters. And this is the output of those two
convolutional filters, they're just random
at this point.
Now my second layer, it's no longer enough
to have a 3x3 matrix, I now need a 3x3x2 tensor
because to calculate my top left of my second
convolutional layer, I need these 9 by these
9 added together, plus these 9 by these 9
added together because at this point my previous
layer is not just one thing, but it is two
things.
Now indeed if our original picture was a 3-channel
color picture, our very fist convolutional
layer would have had to have been 3x3x3 tensors.
[Time: 5 minute mark]
So all of the convolutional layers from now
on are going to be 3 by 3 by number-of-filters-in-the-previous-layer
convolution matrices. So here is my first
3x3x2 tensor -- and you can see it is taking
9 from here, 9 from here, and adding those
two together. So then for my second filter
in my second layer, exactly the same thing.
I've created two more random matrices or one
more random 3x3x2 tensor. And here again,
I have these 9 by these 9 sum, plus those
9 by those 9 sum. And that gives me that one.
So that gives me my first two layers of my
convolutional network. Then I do max polling.
Max pooling is slightly more awkward to do
in Ecel, but that's fine, we can still handle
it.
So here's max pooling. Now max pooling is
going to decrease the resolution of my image
by a factor of two on each axis. So how do
we calculate that number? That number is simply
the maximum of those 4. And then that number
is the maximum of those four, and so forth.
So with max polling, we started with 2 filters
in each layers and we still have two filters
in each layer, but now each filter has half
the resolution in each of the x axis and y
axis.
Question: How did you go from one matrix to
two matrices in the second layer?
Answer: How did I just go from just this 1
thing to these 2 things? The answer to that
is I just created two random 3x3 filters.
This is my first random 3x3 filter, this is
my second random 3x3 filter. Each output then
is simply equal to each corresponding 9-element
section multiplied by each other and added
together. Because I had two random 3x3 matrices,
I ended up with two outputs. Two filters means
two sets of outputs.
So now that we've got our max polling layer,
let's use a dense layer to turn it into our
output. A dense layer means that every single
one of our activations from our max polling
layer needs a random weight. So these are
a whole bunch of random numbers. What I do
is take every one of these random numbers
and multiply each one by a corresponding input
and add them all together, the sumproduct
of this and this.
In MNIST we would have 10 activations because
we need an activation for 0, 1, 2, 3, .. 9.
So for MNIST we would need 10 sets of these
dense weight matrices so that we could calculate
the 10 outputs.
If we were only calculating one output, this
would be a perfectly reasonable way to do
it. So for 1 output, it's just the sumproduct
of everything from our final layer with a
weight for everything in that final layer,
added together. That's all a dense layer is.
So really both dense layers and convolutional
layers couldn't be easier mathematically.
I think the surprising thing is what happens
when you then say, OK, rather than using random
weights, let's calulate the derivative of
what happens if we were to change that weight
up by a bit or down by a bit and how would
it impact our loss. In this case, I haven't
actually gotten as far as calculating a loss
function, but we could add it over here, we
could add a sigmoid loss, for example.
[Time: 10 minute mark]
So we can calculate the derivative with respect
to every single weight in the dense layer,
and every single weight in all of our filters
in that layer, and every single weight in
all of our filters in this layer, and with
all of these derivatives we can calculate
how to optimize all of these weights. And
the surprising thing is when we optimize all
of these weights, we end up with these incredibly
powerful models, like those visualizations
that we saw.
I'm not quite sure where the disconnect between
the incredibly simple math and the outcome
is. I think it might be that it's so easy,
it's hard to believe that's all it is. I'm
not skipping over anything, that really is
it. So to help you really understand this,
I'm going to talk more about SGD.
Question: Why would you use a sigmoid function
here?
Answer: The loss function we generally use
is the SoftMax -- e^x.i/(sum of e^x.i). If
it's just binary, that's the equivalent of
1/(1 + e^x.i). So SoftMax in the binary case
simplifies into a sigmoid function. Thank
you for clarifying that question.
So I think this is super-fun. We're going
to talk not just about SGD but every variant
of SGD, including the one invented just a
week ago.
Question: Does SGD happen for all layers at
once?
Answer: Yes. SGD happens for all layers at
once. We calculate the derivative of all the
weights with respect to the loss.
Question: When have a max pool after convolution,
versus when not to?
Answer: Who knows? This is a very controversial
question and some people are now saying never
use max pool. Instead of using max pool when
you're doing the convolutions, don't do a
convolution over every set of 9 pixels, but
instead skip a pixel each time -- that's another
way of down-sampling.
Geoffrey Hinton, who's kind of the father
of deep learning has gone as far as saying
the extremely great success of max pooling
has been the greatest problem deep learning
has faced. To him, it really stops us from
going further. I don't know whether that's
true or not. I assume it is because he's Geoffrey
Hinton and I'm not.
For now, we use max pooling every time we're
doing fine-tuning because we need to make
sure that our architecture is identical to
the original vgg author's architecture and
we're going to use max pooling wherever they
did.
Question: Why do we want max pooling or down-sampling
or anything like that? Are we just trying
to look at bigger features of the input?
Answer: Why use max pooling at all? There's
a couple of reasons. The first is that max
pooling helps with translation invariance.
So it basically says that if this feature
is here, or here, or here -- I don't care,
it's kind of roughly in the right spot. So
that seems to work well.
And the second is exactly what you said. Every
time we max pool, we end up with a smaller
grid. Which means that our 3x3 convolutions
are effectively covering a larger part of
the original image, which means that our convolutions
can find larger, more complex features. I
think these would be the two main reasons.
Question: So is Geoffrey Hinton cool with
the idea of skipping a pixel each time?
Answer: Geoffrey Hinton is not cool with that
either, he thinks we should be using a capsule
architecture. The problem is that he hasn't
invented it yet. So we don't have an answer
to this yet.
If you google for "Geoffrey Hinton capsule"
you can learn all about the thing that he
thinks we ought to have but don't yet. He
did point out that one of the key pieces of
deep-learning that he invented took 17 years
from conception to working, so he is one of
those people who sticks with things and makes
it work.
Question: Is max pooling unique to image processing?
[Time: 15 minute mark]
Answer: Max pooling is not unique to image
processing, it is likely to be useful for
any kind of convolutional neural network.
And a convolutional neural network can be
used for any type of data that has some kind
of consistent ordering. Things like speech,
or any kind of audio, or some kind of consistent
time series -- all of these things have some
kind of ordering to them and therefore you
can use a CNN and therefore you can use max
pooling.
As we look at NLP, we will be looking more
at CNN for other data types. Interestingly,
the author of Keras, last week or maybe the
week before made the contention that perhaps
it will turn out that CNNs are the architecture
that will be used for every type of ordered
data. This was just after one of the leading
NLP researchers released a paper basically
showing a state of the art result in NLP using
CNN. Although we'll start learning about recurrent
neural networks next week, I have to be open
to the possibility that they'll become redundant
by the end of the year.
So, SGD. We looked at the SGD intro notebook,
but I think sometimes things are a little
more clear when you can see it all in front
of you. So here is the identical thing that
we saw in the SGD notebook in Excel.
We are going to start by creating a line.
We created 29 random numbers and they we say
let's create something that is equal to (2
* x) + 30. So here is 2 * x + 30, that's my
input data.
I'm trying to create something that can find
the parameters of a line. The important thing,
this is the link which requires not thinking
too hard lest you realize how surprising and
amazing this is. Everything we learned about
how to fit a line is identical to how to fit
filters and weights in a convolutional neural
network.
So everything we've learned about calculating
the slope and the intercept, we will then
use to let computers see. And so the answer
to any question which is basically "Why?"
is "Why not?" This is a function that takes
some inputs and calculates some output, this
is a function that take some inputs and calculates
some output, so why not?
The only reason it wouldn't work would be
it was too slow, for example. We know it's
not too slow, because we tried it and it works
pretty well. Everything we are about to learn
works for any kind of function which has the
appropriate types of gradients, and we can
talk more about that later. But neural nets
have the appropriate kind of gradients.
So, SGD. We start with a guess, what do we
think the parameters of our function are.
In this case, the intercept and the slope.
With Keras, they will be randomized using
the floor initiation procedure we learned
about, which is 6/(N-in + N-out) random numbers.
Let's assume they're both 1.
We are going to use very, very small mini-batches
here. Our mini-batches will be of size 1,
basically because it is easier to do in Excel
and it is easier to see. Everything we're
going to see would work equally well for a
mini-batch of size 4 or of size 64, 128, or
whatever.kk
So here's our first row, or our first mini-batch.
Our input is 14 and our desired output is
58, and our guess as to our parameters are
1 and 1. And therefore our predicted y value
is equal to 1 + 1*14 (which = 15). We're doing
RMS, so our error squaed is (prediction - actual)^2.
[Time: 20 minute mark]
The next thing we want todo is calculate the
derivative with respect to each of our two
inputs. One really easy way to do this is
to add a tiny amount to each of the two inputs
and see how the output varies. So let's start
by doing that -- let's add 0.01 to our intercept
and calculate the line and calculate the loss
squared, the error. So this is the error if
y is increased by 0.01, and let's calculate
the difference between that error and the
actual error and then divide that by our change
(which is 0.01), and that gives us our estimated
gradient (I'm using de/db for d-error/db,
should have probably been dl/db for d-loss/db
for the error. So the change in loss with
respect to b is -85.99. We can do the same
thing for a.
We can add 0.01 to a, then calculate our line,
subtract our actual, take the square, and
so there is our value for the estimated d-loss/da,
subtract it from the actual loss divided by
0.01. And so there are two estimates of the
derivative.
This approach to estimating the derivative
is called finite differencing. Any time you
calculate a derivate by hand, you should use
finite differecing to make sure your calculation
is correct.
You're not very likely to ever have to do
that, however, because all of the libraries
do derivatives for you. And they do them analytically,
not using finite derivatives. And so here
are the derivatives calculated analytically,
which you can do by going to WolframAlpha
and typing in your formula and getting the
derivative back. So this is the analytical
derivative of the loss with respect to b and
the analytical derivative with the loss with
respect to a. And you can see that our analytical
and our finite difference are very similar
for b, and they are very simiilar for a, so
that makes me feel comforable that we got
the calculation correct.
So all SGD does is it says this tells us that
if we change our weights by a litle bit, this
is the change in our loss function. We know
that increasing our value of b by a little
bit will decrease our loss function and increasing
the value of a by a little bit will decrease
the loss funtion. So therefore let's decrease
both of them by a little bit. And the way
we do that is to multiply the derivative times
our learning rate (that's the value of our
little bit), and subtract that from our previous
guess. So we do that for a and we do that
for b and here are our new guesses. Now we're
at 1.12 and 1.01. And so let's copy them over
here. And we do the same thing, and this gives
us a new a and a new b. And we keep doing
that again and again and again, until we've
gone through the entire data set, at the end
of which we have a guess of 2.61 for a and
a guess of 1.07 for b. So that's one epoch.
In real life, we would be having shuffle=true,
which means that these would be randomized,
so this isn't quite perfect. But apart from
that, this is SGD with a mini-batch size of
1.
So at the end of the epoch, you say this is
our new slope, let's copy 2.61 over here.
And this is our new intercept, so let's copy
1.06 over here. So now, it starts again. So
we can keep doing that again and again and
again - copy this stuff from the bottom, stick
it back at the top, and each one of these
is going to be an epoch.
So I recorded a macro with me copying this
from the bottom and pasting it at the top
and added something that says for i=1 to 5
around it. So now if I click run, it would
copy and paste it 5 times. So you can see
it's gradually getting closer. And we know
that our goal is that it should be a=2 and
b=30. So we've got as far as a=2.5 and b=1.3,
so it's better than our starting point. And
you can see our gradually improving loss function.
But it's going to take a long time.
Question: Can we still do analytic derivatives
when we are using non-linear activation functions?
Answer: Yes, we can use analytical derivatives
as long as we're using a function that has
an analytical derivative, which is pretty
much every useful function you can think of.
Except, you can't have something that has
like an if-then statement in it because it
jumps from here to here. But even those you
can approximate.
[Time: 25 minute mark]
Like a good example would be ReLU. ReLU, which
is max(0,x) strictly speaking does not have
a derivative at every point, or at least not
a well-defined one, because this is what ReLU
looks like. So, it's derivative here is 0,
and its derivative is 1 if x > 0. What is
its derivative exactly here, when x=0 ? Who
knows. The thing is mathematicians care about
that kind of thing but we don't. Like in real
life, this is a computer and computers are
never exactly anything. We can either assume
it's an infinte amount to this side, or an
infinite amount to this side. Who cares? As
long as it has a derivative that you can calculate
in a meaningful way in practice on a computer,
then you'll be fine.
One thing you might have noticed is that it's
going to take an awfully long time to get
anywhere. So you might think, let's increase
the learning rate. Fine, let's increase the
learning rate, so we get rid of one of these
0's. Oh, dear. Something went crazy. What
went crazy? I'll tell you what went crazy.
The values for a and b go out to like about
11 million, which is not the correct answer.
So how did it go ahead and do that?
Here's the problem. Let's say this was the
shape of our original loss function, and this
was our initial guess. And we figure out the
derivative positive, so we want to go in the
opposite direction, so we step a little bit
to the right, and we step a little bit over
here, and this looks good. Then we increase
the learning rate, so rather than stepping
a little bit, we stepped a long way, and that
put us here. And then we stepped a long way
again. And that put us here. If your learning
rate is too high, you're going to get worse
and worse, and that's what happened here.
So getting your learning rate right is critical
to getting trainable.
Question: Is this sometimes called "exploding
gradients"?
Answer: Yes. Or you could even have gradients
that do the opposite. Exploding gradients
are something a little bit different, but
it is a similar idea.
So it looks like 0.0001 is the best we can
do. And that's a bit sad because this is really
slow. So let's try
and improve it.
Let's say we have a 3-dimensional set of axes
now, and we have a loss function that looks
like this kind of valley. And let's say our
initial guess was somewhere over here, so
over here the gradient is pointing in this
direction, so we might make a step and end
up there, and we might make another step which
would put us there. This is actually the most
common thing that happens in neural networks.
Something that is kind of flat in one dimension
like this is called a saddle point.
It has actually been proved that the vast
majority of the space in the loss function
of a neural network is pretty much all saddle
points. You can also think of it as looking
like a valley.
When you look at this, it's pretty obvious
what should be done -- if you go to here,
and then to here, we can say that on average
we're kind of obviously heading in this direction.
Especially when we do it again, we're obviously
heading in this direction. So let's take the
average of how we've been going so far and
do a bit of that. And that's exactly what
momentum does.
Question: If ReLU isn't the cost function,
why are we concerned with its differentiability?
Answer: We care about the derivate of the
output with respect to the inputs. The inputs
are the filters. And remember the loss function
consists of a function of a function of a
function of a function. So it is Categorical
Cross-Entropy Loss applied to SoftMax applied
to ReLU applied to Dense Layer applied to
MaxPolling applied to ReLU applied to Convolutions,
etc., etc., So in other words, to calculate
the derivative of a loss with respect to the
inputs, you have to calculate them through
that whole function. And this is what's called
back propogation.
[Time: 30 minute mark]
With back propogation, it is easy to calculate
that derivative since we know that from the
chain rule, a derivative of a function of
a function is simply equal to the product
of the derivatives of those functions. So
in practice, what we do is calculate the derivative
of every layer with respect to its inputs
and we just multiply them all together. So
that's why we need to know the derivative
of the activation layers as well as the loss
layer, and everything else.
So here's the trick ... We're going to say
that every time
we take a step, we're going to also calculate
the average of the last few steps. So after
these two steps, the average is this direction.
So the next step, we're going to take our
gradient step as usual and we're going to
add on our average of the last few steps.
And that means that we end up over here. And
then we do the same thing again. We find the
average of the last few steps and it's now
even further in this direction.
Question: What is that surface?
Answer: This is the surface of the loss function
with respect to some of the parameters. In
this case, just a couple of the parameters,
it's an example of what a loss function might
look like. So this is the loss, and this is
some weight W1, and this is some weight W2.
If you can imagine, it's like gravity, we're
trying to get this little ball to travel down
this valley as far down to the bottom as possible.
So the trick is that we're going to keep taking
a step, not just the gradient step, but also
the average of the last few steps. And so
in practice, this is going to end up going
zigzag for a while and then settle down.
To do that in Excel is pretty straightforward.
To make things simpler I have removed the
finite differencing based derivatives here
so we just have the analytical derivatives.
But other than that, this is identical to
the previous spreadsheet, same data, same
predictions, same derivatives. Except we've
done one extra thing, when we calculate our
new b, we say it's our previous b minus our
learning rate times not our gradient, but
times this cell. What is that cell That cell
is equal to our gradient, times .1 plus the
thing just above it times .9. And the thing
just above it is equal to its gradient plus
.1 times -
which is exactly what we want. And we are
going to do that for both of our two parameters.
So this .9 is our momentum parameter. In Keras,
when you use momentum, you say momentum= and
you say how much momentum you want.
Question: Where did that momentum parameter
come from?
Answer: You just pick it. Just like your learning
rate, you pick your momemtum factor. You choose
it by trying a few and finding out what works
best.
So let's try running this. As you can see,
it is still not exactly zipping along. Why
is it not exactly zipping along? The reason
is that when we look at it we know that the
constant term needs to get all the way up
to 30 and it's still way down at 1.5, it's
not moving fast enough. Whereas the slope
term moved very quickly to where we wanted
it to be.
So what we really want is different learning
rates for different parameters, this is called
dynamic learning rates.
The first really effective dynamic learning
rate approaches have just appeared in the
last three years or so. One very popular one
is called AdaGrad.
[Time: 35 minute mark]
All these dynamic learning rate approaches
have the same insight, which is this, if the
parameter that I'm changing, the derivative
of that parameter is consistently of a very
low magnitude, then if the derivative of this
mini-batch is higher than that than what I
really care about is the relative difference
between how much this variable tends to change
and how much it's going to change this time
around. So in other words, we don't just care
about what is the gradient, but is the magnitude
of the gradient much more or a lot less than
it has tended to be recently. So the easy
way to calculate the overall amount of change
of the gradient recently is to keep track
of the square of the gradient.
So what we do with AdaGrad is, as you can
see at the bottom of my epoch here I have
got a sum of squares of all my gradients,
and then I have taken the square root divided
by the count to give me the average. This
is the average of the root sum of squares
of my gradients, so this number here will
be high if the magnitudes of my gradients
are high. And because it's squared, it will
be particularly high if sometimes they are
really high.
Question: So why is it okay to just use a
mini-batch, since the surface is going to
depend on the points in the mini-batch?
Answer: It's not idea to just use a mini-batch
and we will learn about a better approach
in a moment.
But for now, let's look at this. In fact,
there are two approaches that are very related,
AdaGrad and AdaDelta, and one of them does
this for all of the gradients so far and one
of them uses a slightly more sophisticated
approach. The approach on a epoch by epoch
basis is slightly different for either, but
it is similar enough to explain the concept.
Question: For a CNN, does dynamic learning
rates mean that each filter would have its
own learning rate?
Answer: It would mean that every parameter
has its own learning rate. This is
a parameter, that is a parameter.
When you go model.summary in Keras, it shows
you for every layer how many parameters there
are. Any time you're unclear about how many
parameters there are, you can go back and
have a look at these spreadsheets and do a
model.summary in Keras and make sure you understand
how they turn out.
For the first layer it is going to be the
size of your filter times the number of filters,
and after that the number of parameters will
be equal to the size of your filter times
the number of filters coming in times the
number of filters coming out.
For your dense layers, every input goes to
every output, so it would be the number of
inputs times the number of outputs, a parameter
to the function that is calculating whether
it is a cat or a dog.
What we do now is we say this number here,
look at this number here, 1857. This is saying
that the derivative of the loss with respect
to the slope varies a lot, whereas the derviative
of the loss with respect to the intercept
doesn't vary much at all. So at the end of
every epoch, I copy that up to here and I
take my learning rate and I divide it by that.
So now, for each of my parameters, I have
an adjusted learning rate, which is the learning
rate divided by the recent sum-of-squares
average gradient. So you can see that one
of my learning rates is 100X faster than the
other. And so let's see what happens when
I run this.
Question: Is it a relationship with normalizing
the input data?
Answer: No, there's not really a relationship
with normalizing the input data. It can help,
but still if your inputs are of very different
scales, it's still a lot more work for it
to do so. So, yes it helps, but it doesn't
help so much that it makes it useless. In
fact, in turns out that even with dynamic
learning rates having not just normalized
inputs but batch normalized activations is
extremely helpful.
[Time: 40 minute mark]
The thing about when you're using AdaGrad
or any kind of dynamic learning rate is that
generally you'll set the learning rate quite
a lot higher because you're dividing it by
the recent average. So if I set it to .1,
that's too far, no good. So let's try .05
and run that, you can see that after just
5 steps I'm already halfway there. Another
5 steps, getting very close. Another 5 steps,
it explodes.
Now why did that happen? Because as we get
closer and closer to where we want to be,
you need to take smaller and smaller steps.
By keeping the learning rate the same, it
meant eventually we went too far. So this
is still something you have to be very careful
of.
A more elegant (in my opinion) approach to
the same thing that AdaGrad is doing is something
called RMSprop. RMSprop was first introduced
in Geoffrey Hinton's Coursera course. So if
you go to Coursera and search for Geoffrey
Hinton, Neural Networks, you'll find it. In
one of those classes, he introduces RMSprop.
It's quite funny, nowadays because this comes
up in academic papers a lot, when people cite
it they have to cite Coursera Course, Chapter
6, at minute 14 and 30 seconds. But Hinton
has asked that this be the official way that
it is cited, so there you go.
Here's what RMSprop does -- RMSprop does exactly
the same thing as momentum, but instead of
keeping track of the weighted running average
of the gradients, we keep track of the weighted
running average of the square of the gradients.
Here it is -- everything here is the same
as momentum so far except I take my gradient
squared, multiply it by .1 and add it to my
previous cell times .9. So this is keeping
track of the recent running average of the
squares of the gradients. And when I have
that, I thendo exactly the same thing that
I do with AdaGrad, which is to divide the
learning rate by it. So I take my previous
guess as to b, and then I subtract from it
the derivatie times the learning rate, then
divide it by the square root of the recent
running average of the squares of the gradients.
So it's doing basically the same thing as
AdaGrad but it's doing it continuously.
Question: So these are all different types
of learning rate optimization?
Answer: These last two are types of different
types of dynamic learning rate operations.
So let's try this one. If we run it for a
few steps, first we guess what learning rate
to start with - say .1, that's a little slow,
so maybe we try .2, and as you can see this
is going pretty well.
And I'll show you something really nice about
RMSprop, which is what happens as we get very
close. We know the right answer is 2 and 30
(and we are at 1.6569 and 29.8358), are we
about to explode? RMSgrad doesn't explode,
and the reason it doesn't explode is that
it's recalculating that running average every
single mini-batch. And so rather than waiting
til the end of the epoch, at which point it's
gone so far that it can't come back again,
it just jumps a little too far and then it
recalculates the dynamic learning rates and
tries again.
So what happens with RMSprop, is if your learning
rate is too high, it doesn't explode, it just
ends up going around the right answer. So
when you use RMSprop, as soon as you see your
validation scores flatten out, you know this
is what's going on, so therefore you should
probably divide your learning rate by 10.
And you see me doing this all the time. When
I'm running Keras stuff you'll see me run
a few steps then divide the learning rate
by 10, run a few steps. You don't see my loss
function explode, you just see that it flattens
out.
Question: Do you want your learning rates
to get smaller and smaller?
[Time: 45 minute mark]
Answer: Yes. Your very first learning rate
often has to start small (and we'll talk about
that in a moment), but once you've kind of
got started, you generally have to gradually
decrease the learning rate. And that's called
learning rate annealing.
Question: Can you repeat what you said earlier
that something does the same thing as AdaGrad?
Answer: RMSprop, which we're looking at now,
does exactly the same thing as AdaGrad, which
is divide the learning rate by the root sum-of-squares
of the gradients, but rather than doing it
since the beginning of time, or every mini-batch
or every epoch, RMSprop does it continuously,
using the same technique that we learned from
momentum, which is take the square of this
gradient, multiply it by .1 and add it to
.9 times the last calculation.
Question: And that's called a moving average?
Answer: It's a weighted moving average, where
we're weighting it such that the more recent
squared gradients are weighted higher. I think
it's an exponentially weighted moving average,
to be more precise.
So there's something pretty obvious we could
do here, which is momentum seems like a good
idea. RMSprop seems like a good idea. Why
not do both? And that is called Adam.
Adam was invented like last year, 18 months
ago. Hopefully one of the things you see from
these spreadsheets is that these recently
invented things are still at the ridiculously
simple end of the spectrum. The stuff that
people are discovering in deep-learning are
a long way from being complex or sophisticated.
Hopefully you'll find this encouraging - if
you want to play at the state-of-the-art of
deep-learning, that's not at all hard to do.
Let's look at Adam. I remember it coming out
12 or 18 months ago and everybody became very
excited because suddenly it became so much
easier and faster to train neural nets. But
once I tried to create an Excel spreadsheet
out of it, I realized that it's just RMSprop
plus momentum. So literally all I did was
I copied my momentum page, and then I copied
across my RMSprop columns and combined them.
So you can see here, I have my exponentially
weighted moving average of the gradients (that's
what these two columns are), here is my exponetially
weighted moving average of the squares of
the gradients, and so then when I calculate
my new parameters, I take my old parameter
and I subtract, not my derivative times the
learning rate, but my momentum factor. So
in other words, the recent weighted moving
average of the gradients, multiplied by the
learning rate, divided by the recent moving
average of the root of the squares of the
derivatives. So it's literally just combining
momentum plus RMSprop.
And so let's see how that goes. Let's run
5 epochs, and we can use a pretty high learning
rate now because it's really handling a lot
of stuff for us. After 5 epochs, we're almost
perfect. And after another 5 epochs, it does
exactly the same thing that RMSprop does,
which is it goes too far and tries to come
back. So we need to do the same thing when
we use Adam. And Adam's what I use all the
time now. I just divide by 10 every time I
see it flatten out.
So, a week ago, somebody came out with something
that they called not Adam, but Eve. And Eve
is an addition to Adam which attempts to deal
with this learning rate annealing automatically.
And so all of this is exactly the same as
my Adam page. But at the bottom, I've added
some extra stuff. I've kept track of the root-mean-squared
error, this is just my loss function, and
then I copy across my loss function from my
previous epoch and from the epoch before that.
And what Eve does is it says, how much has
the loss function changed? And so, it's got
this ratio between the previous loss function
and the loss function before that. So you
can see it's the absolute value of the last
one, minus the one before divided by whichever
one is smaller. And what it says is, okay,
let's then just adjust the learning rate so
that instead of just using the learning rate
we're given, let's
adjust the learning rate that we're given
by taking the exponentially weighted moving
average of these ratios. So you can see this
thing here is equal to our last ratio times
.9 plus our new ratio times .1.
[Time: 50 minute mark]
And so then for our learning rate, we divide
the learning rate from Adam by this [cell-F38].
So what this says if the learning rate is
moving around a lot, it's very bumpy, we should
probably decrease the learning rate because
it's going all over the place. Remember how
we saw before if we've gone past where we
want to get to, it just jumps up and down.
On the other hand, if the loss function is
staying pretty constant, then we probably
want to increase the learning rate.
That all seems like a good idea, so again,
let's try it. Not bad. After 5 epochs, it's
kind of gone a little too far. After a week
of playing with it (I used this on State Farm
a lot during the week - I grabbed the Keras
implementation that somebody wrote like a
day after the paper came out), the problem
is that since it can both decrease and increase
the learning rate, sometimes as it gets down
to the flat bottom point where it's pretty
much optimal, it may often be the case that
the loss gets pretty constant at that point
and so therefore Eve will try to increase
the learning rate. What I tend to find happens
is that you very quickly get close to the
answer, then suddenly it will jump to somewhere
really awful. And then it will start to get
the answer again and then jump to somewhere
really awful.
Question: Could there be an exit condition
delta which would change the gradient, when
we hit a certain delta then we just stop.
Answer: We have not done any such thing, no.
We have always said run for a specific number
of epochs. We have not defined any kind of
stopping criteria. It is possible to define
such a stopping criterion, but nobody has
come up with one that is remotely reliable.
And the reason why is that when you look at
the graph of loss over time, it doesn't tend
to look like that, it tends to look like this,
so in practice it is very hard to know when
to stop. It's kind of still a human judgement
thing.
Question: Can't it also have lots of plateaus?
Answer: Oh, yes that's true. Particularly
with an architecture called ResNet, which
we'll look at next week. The authors show
that it tends to go like this. In practice,
you kind of have to run your training for
as long as you have patience for at the best
learning rate you can come up with.
Something I came up with 6 or 12 months ago
that kind of restimulated my interest after
this Adam paper is something which dynamically
updates learning rates in such a way so that
they only go down. And rather than using the
loss function (which I just said is incredibly
bumpy) there's something which is less bumpy,
which is the average sum-of-square gradients.
So I actually created a spreadsheet of my
idea and I hope to prototype it in Python
either this week or next week. And the idea
is basically this -- keep track of the sum-of-squares
of the derivatives and compare the sum-of-squares
of the derivatives from the last epoch to
the sum-of-squares of the derivatives of this
epoch, and look at the ratio of the two. The
derivatives should keep going down. If they
ever go up by too much, that would strongly
suggest that you jumped out of the good part
of the function. And so any time they go up
too much, you should decrease the learning
rate.
[Time: 55 minute mark]
So I literally added two lines of code to
my simple VBA, Adam with Annealing (adam_ann).
If the gradient ratio is greater than two
(so if it doubles), divide the learning rate
by 4. And here is what happens when I run
that. 5 steps, another 5 steps, and you can
see it is automatically changing it. So I
don't have to do anything, I just keep running.
So I'm pretty interested in this idea, I think
it's going to work super-well. It allows me
to focus on just running stuff without ever
worrying about setting learning rates. So
I'm hopeful that this approach to automatic
learning rate annealing is something that
we can have in our toolbox by the end of this
course.
Question: One thing that happened to me today
was that I tried a lot of different learning
rates and I didn't get anywhere. But I was
working with a whole dataset. If I try with
a sample and I find something, would that
apply to the whole data set, or how would
I go about it?
Answer: Great question. The question was,
it takes a long time to figure out the optimal
learning rate. Can we calculate it using just
a sample?
To answer that question, I'm going to show
you how I entered State Farm. And indeed,
when I started entering State Farm, I started
by using a sample. So Step 1 was to think
what insights can we gain from using a sample
which can still apply when we move to the
wole data set? Running stuff in a sample took
10 or 20 seconds, running stuff on the full
data set took 2-10 minutes per epoch. So after
I created my sample (created randomly), I
first of all wanted to find out what it would
take to create a better than random model
here. So I always start with the simplest
possible model, and so the simplest possible
model has a single dense layer.
Now here's a handy trick. Rather than worry
about calculating the average and standard
deviation of the input and subtracting it
all out in order to normalize your input layer,
you can just start with a batchnorm layer.
If you start with a batchnorm layer, it's
going to do that for you. So anytime you create
a Keras model from scratch, I would recommend
making your first layer a batchnorm layer.
And so this is going to normalize the data
for me. That's a cool little trick which I
haven't actually seen anybody use elsewhere.
And I think it's a good default starting point
all the time.
If I'm going to use a dense layer, then I
have to flatten everything into a single vector
first. So this is really a most minimal model.
I tried fitting it, compiled it, fit it -- and
nothing happened. Not only did nothing happen
to my validation, but nothing happened to
my training. It's only taking 7 seconds per
epoch to find this out, so that's okay.
So what's going on? I look at model.summary
and I see that there's 1.5 million parameters
and that makes me think it's probably not
underfitting. It's unlikely with 1.5 million
parameters that there's really nothing useful
whatsoever. It is a linear model, but I still
think it should be able to do something. So
that makes me think that what must be going
on is it must be doing that thing where it
jumps too far. And it's particularly easy
to jump too far at the very start of training.
[Time: 1 hour mark]
Let me explain why. It turns out that there
are often reasonably good answers that are
way too easy to find. So one reasonably good
answer would be to always predict zero. Because
there are 10 output classes in the State Farm
competion (there's 10 different types of distracted
driving), and you are scored based on the
cross-entropy loss and what that's looking
at is how accurate are each of your 10 predictions?
So rather than trying to predict something
well, what if we always just predict 0, or
0.01. Nine times out of ten you're going to
be right because 9 out of the 10 categories
it is not that, it's only 1 of the 10 categories.
So always predicting .01 would be pretty good.
Turns out it's not possible to do that because
we have a SoftMax layer (and a SoftMax layer
is e^x.i/sumOf(e^x.i) ), so in a SoftMax layer
everything has to add to 1. So therefore it
it makes one of the classes really high and
all of the other ones really low, then 9 times
out of 10 it is going to be right 9 times
out of 10. So in other words, it is a pretty
good answer for it to always predict one random
class (class 8) close to 100% certainty. And
that's what happened -- I saw a lot of people
this week on the forums saying, "I tried to
train it and nothing happened." The folks
who got the interesting insight were those
who went on to say "Then I looked at my predictions,
and it kept predicting the same class with
great confidence again and again and again."
Our next step then is to try decreasing the
learning rate. Here is exactly the same model,
but I'm now using a much lower learning rate,
and when I run that it's actually moving.
Took only 12 seconds of compute time to figure
out that I'm going to have to start with a
low learning rate.
Once we've got to a point where the accuracy
is reasonably better than random, we're well
away from the part of the loss function that
says always predict everything as the same
class, and therefore we can now increase the
learning rate back up again.
Generally speaking for these harder problems,
we need to start (for an epoch or two) at
a generally low learning rate and then you
can increase it back up again. So now you
can see I can put it back up and very quickly
increasing my accuracy.
So you can see here my accuracy on my validation
set is .5 using a linear model. And this is
a good starting point because this says to
me any time that my validation accuracy is
worse than about .5, this is no better than
a linear model, so it is not work spending
any more time on.
One obvious question would be how do you decide
how big of a sample to use? And what I did
was I tried a few different sizes of samples
in my validation set and I then said, evaluate
the model with calculated loss function on
the validation set, but do it with a whole
bunch of randomly sampled batches, do it 10
times. And then I looked and I saw how the
accuracy changed. So with the validation set
set at 1000 images, my accuracy changed from
.48 to .47 to .51. So it's not changing too
much. It's small enough so that I think I
can make valid insights using a sample size
of this size.
So what else can we learn from a sample? One
thing would be, are there any other architectures
that work well? So the obvious thing to do
with a computer vision problem is to try a
convolutional neural network.
Here's one of the most simple convolutional
neural networks -- 2 Convolutional layers,
each with a MaxPooling layer and one Dense
layer, followed by my Dense output layer.
So I tried that and found that very quickly
it got to an accuracy of 100% on the training
set, but only 24% on the validation set. And
that's because I was very careful to make
sure that my validation set included different
drivers from my training set because on Kaggle
it told us that the test set has different
drivers. It is much harder to recognize what
a driver is doing if we've never seen that
driver before.
[Time: 1.05 hour mark]
So I can see that Convolutional Neural Networks
clearly are a great way to model this kind
of data, but I'm going to have to think very
carefully about over-fitting.
So Step 1 to avoid over-fitting is data augmentation.
So here's the exact same model, and I tried
every type of data augmentation. I tried shifting
it left and right a bit, I tried shifting
it up and down a bit, I tried shearing it
a bit, I tried rotating it a bit, I tried
shifting the channels of the colors a bit,
and for each of those I tried 4 different
levels. I found in each case what was the
best and I combined them together. So here
are my best data augmentation amounts.
So on 15,060 images (a very small set, it
was just my sample), I then ran my very simple
two convolutional layer model with the data
augmentation with the optimized parameters,
and it didn't look very good. After 5 epochs,
I only have .1 accuracy on my validation set.
But I can see that my training set is continuing
to improve, so that makes me think don't give
up yet, try decreasing the learning rate and
do a few more. Lo and behold, it started improving.
This is where you've got to be careful not
to jump to conclusions too soon. So I ran
a few more and it's improving well, so I ran
a few more, another 25.
Look at what happened -- it kept getting better
and better and better, until we were getting
67% accuracy. So this 1.15 validation loss
is well within the top 50% in this competition.
So using an incredibly simple model on just
a sample, we can get in the top half of a
Kaggle competition simply by using the right
kind of data augmentation.
So I think this is a very interesting insight
about the power of this incredibly tool.
Question: With 10 classes, would a class imbalance
affect it?
Answer: It is unlikely that there's going
to be a class imbalance in my sample unless
there was an equivalent class imbalance in
the real data because I've got 1000 samples,
so just statistically speaking that's unlikely.
If there's a class imbalance in my original
data then I want my sample to have that class
imbalance too.
At this point, I felt pretty good that I knew
we should be using a convolutional neural
network, which is a obviously a very strong
hypothesis to start with anyway, and also
pretty confident we knew what kind of learning
rate to start with, and how to change it,
and also what kind of data augmentation we
needed to do.
The next thing I wanted to wonder about was
how else do I handle over-fitting, because
although I'm getting pretty good results,
I'm still overfitting hugely - .6 vs .9.
So the next thing on our list to avoid over-fitting,
and I hope you guys all remember that we had
that list in Lesson 3, the 5 steps. Let's
go take a look at it now to remind ourselves.
Approaches to reducing overfitting, these
are the 5 steps. Can't add more data, we've
tried using data augmentation, we're already
using batchnorm and conv nets, so the next
step is to add regularization and drop out
is the favored regularization technique.
Before we do that, I'd like to mention one
more thing about this data augmentation approach.
I have literally never seen anyone write down
a process as to how to figure out what kind
of data augmentation to use and the amount.
The only posts I've seen on it always rely
on intuition, which is basically like look
at the images and think about how much they
should be able to move around or rotate.
[Time: 1.10 hour mark]
I really tried this week to come up with a
rigorous repeatable process that you could
use and that process is go to each data augmentation
type one at a time, try three or four levels
of it on a sample with a big enough validation
set that it's pretty stable to find the best
value of each of the data augmentation parameters
and then try combining them altogether.
So I hope you can come away with this as a
practical message, which probably your colleagues,
even if some of them claim to be deep-learning
experts, I doubt that they're doing this.
So this is something that you can hopefully
get people into the practice of doing.
Regularization, however, we cannot do on a
sample. And the reason why is that Step 1
(Add more data) that step is very correlated
with add regularization. As we add more data,
we need less regularization. So as we move
from a sample to the full dataset, we're going
to need less regularization.
So to figure out how much regularization to
use, we have to use the whole data set. So
at this point, I changed it to use the whole
dataset, not the sample and I started using
dropout. So you can see that I started with
my data augmentation amounts that you've already
seen and I started adding in some dropout,
and ran it for a few epochs to see what would
happen, and you can see it's worked pretty
well. So we're getting up into the 75% now,
and before we were in the 64%.
We haven't added clipping, which is very important
for getting the best cross-entropy loss function.
I haven't checked where that would get us
on the Kaggle leaderboard, but I'm pretty
sure that it would be in at least the top
third, based on this accuracy.
I ran a few more epochs with an even lower
learning rate and got .78% and .79%. So this
is going to be well up into the top third,
maybe even the top quarter of the leaderboard.
So I got to this point by just trying out
a couple of different levels of dropout, and
I just put them in my dense layers.
There's no rule of thumb here. A lot of people
put small amounts of drop out in their convolutional
layers as well.
All I can say is to try these. What VGG does
is to put 50% dropout after each of its dense
layers, and that doesn't seem like a bad rule
of thumb - so that's what I was doing here
-- and then trying out a few different sizes
of dense layers to try and find something
reasonable. I didn't spend a heap of time
on this, so there's probably better architectures,
but so as you can see this is still a pretty
good one. So that was my Step 2.
Now so far we have not used a pre-trained
network at all. So this is getting into the
top third of the leaderboard without even
using any ImageNet features, so that's pretty
damn cool.
But we're pretty sure that ImageNet features
would be helpful. So that is the next step
- to use ImageNet features or VGG features.
Specifically I was reasonably confident tha
all of the convolutional layers of VGG are
probably pretty much good enough. I didn't
expect that I would have to fine-tune them
much, if at all, because the convolutional
layers are the thing which really look at
the shape and the structure of things, rather
than how things fit together, and these are
photos of the real world, just like ImageNet
is photos of the real world.
So I really felt like most of the time, if
not all of it, was likely to be spent on the
dense layers. So therefore because calculating
convolutional layers takes nearly all of the
time because that's where all the computation
is, I pre-computed the output of the convolutional
layers.
[Time: 1.15 hour mark]
And we've done this before, you might remember
when we looked at droput, we did exactly this.
We figured out what was the last convolutional
layer's ID, we grabbed all of the layers up
to that ID, we built a model out of them,
and then we calculated the output of that
model. And that told us the values from those
features, those activations, from VGG's last
convolutional layer. So I did exactly the
same thing. I basically copied and pasted
that code. So I said, okay grab VGG16, find
the last convolutional layer, build a model
that contains everything up to and including
that layer, predict the output of that model.
So predicting the output of that model (that
means calculate the activations of that last
convulational layer) and since that takes
some time, then save that so I don't have
to do it again. So then in the future, I can
just load that array
I'm not going to calculate those, I'm simply
going to load them.
Think about what you would expect the shape
of this to be? And you could figure out what
you expect the shape to be by looking at model.summary
and finding the last convolutional layer.
We can see it is 512 filters by 14 by 14.
So let's have a look. And running conv_val_feat.shape
returns 512 by 14 by 14, as expected.
Question: Is there a reason why you chose
to leave out the MaxPooling and Flatten layers?
Answer: Why did I leave out the MaxPooling
and Flatten layers? Basically because it takes
zero time to calculate them and the MaxPooling
layer loses information. Given that I might
want to play around with other types of pooling
or other types of convolutions, I felt pre-calculating
this layer is the last one that takes a lot
of computation time. Having said that, the
first thing that I did with it in my new model
was to MaxPool it and flatten it.
Now that I have the output of VGG for the
last conv layer, I can now build a model that
has dense layers on top of that. And so the
input to the model will be the output of those
conv layers. And the nice thing is that it
won't take much time to run this, even on
the whole dataset, because the dense layers
don't take much computation time.
So here's my model. By making p a parameter,
I can try a wide range of dropout amounts.
I fit it, and one epoch takes 5 seconds on
the entire dataset, so this is a super good
way to play around. As you can see, one epoch
gets me .65, three epochs gets me .75.
So this is pretty cool. I have something that
in 15 seconds can get me .75 accuracy. And
notice here, I'm not using any data augmentation.
Why aren't not using data augmentation? Because
you cannot pre-compute the output of convolutional
layers if you're using data augmentation.
With data augmentation, your convolutional
layers give you a different output every time.
You can't use data augmentation if you are
pre-computing the output of a layer because
every time it sees the same cat photo it is
rotating it by a different amount, or shearing
it by a different amount, or moving it by
a different amount. So it gives a different
output of the convolutional layer, so you
can't pre-compute it.
There is something you can do (which I played
with a little bit) which is that you could
pre-compute something that's like 10x bigger
than your dataset, consisting of 10 different
data-augmented versions of it.
[Time: 1.20 hour mark]
Which is what I was actually doing here when
I brought in this data generator with augmentations,
and I created something called data augmented
convolutional features, which I calculated
5 times the amount of data. And so that basically
gave me a dataset 5 times bigger, and that
actually worked pretty well. It's not as good
as having a whole new sample every time, but
it's kind of a compromise.
So once I played around with these dense layers
and did some more fine tuning. I then tried
going through all of the layers in my model
from 16 onwards and set them to trainable
and see what happens. So I tried fine-tuning
some of the convolutional layers as well.
It basically didn't help. So I eperimented
with my hypothesis and found it was correct,
which is for this particular model, coming
up with the right set of dense layers is what
it's all about.
Question: If we want rotational invariance,
should we keep the MaxPooling or can another
layer do it as well.
Answer: MaxPooling doesn't really have anything
to do with rotational invariance. MaxPooling
does translation invariance.
So I'm going to show you one more cool trick.
I'm going to show you a little bit of State
Farm every week from now on because there's
so many cool things to try. And I want to
keep reviewing CNNs because Convolutional
Neural Networks are becoming what deep learning
is all about.
I'm going to show you a really cool trick.
The one cool trick is actually two tricks,
called Pseudo Labeling and Knowledge Distillation.
So if you google for "pseudo labeling semi
supervised learning" you can see the original
paper (from 2013), and then "knowledge distillation",
this is a Geoffrey Hinton paper "Distilling
the Knowledge in a Neural Network" from 2015.
There's a couple of realy cool techniques,
we're going to combine them together ... and
they're kind of crazy.
What we are going to do is we are going to
use the test set to give us more information.
In State Farm, the test set has 80,000 images
in it, and the training set has 20,000 images
in it. So what could we do with those 80,000
images which we don't have labels for? It
seems a shame to waste them. It seems like
we ought to be able to do something with them.
There's a great little picture here ... imagine
we only had two points, and we knew their
labels, White and Black. And then somebody
asked how would you label this? And then they
told you that there's a whole lot of other
unlabeled data. Notice this is all grey -- it
is unlabeled. But it has helped us, it's helped
us because it's told us how the data is structured.
This is what semi-supervised learning is all
about, it's about using the unlabeled data
to try and understand something about the
structure of it, and use that to help you,
just like in this picture. Pseudo-labeling
and knowledge distillation are a way to do
this. I'm not going to do it on the test set,
I'm going to do it on the validation set because
it's a little bit easier to see the impact
of it; maybe next week we'll look at on the
test set.
It's this simple. What we do is we take out
our model, some model we'e already built and
we predict the outputs from that model for
our unlabeled set (in this case I'm using
the validation set) as if it were unlabed
- I'm ignoring labels. Those things we call
the pseudo-labels.
Now that we have predictions for the test
set or the validation set, it's not that they're
true, but we can pretend they're true. We
can say they're some labels -- they're not
correct labels, but they're labels nonetheless.
So what we then do is take our training labels
and we concatenate them with our validation
or test set pseudo labels. And so we now have
a bunch of labels for all of our data.
[Time: 1.25 hour mark]
And so we can now concatenate our convolutional
features with the convolutional features of
the test set or validation set, and we now
use these to train a model. So the model we
use is exactly the same model we had before
and we train it in exactly the same way as
before, and our loss goes up from .75 to .82,
so our error has dropped by 25%. And the reason
why is just because we used this additional
unlabeled data to try to figure out the structure
of it.
Question: How do learn how to design a model
and when to stop messing with them. It seems
like you've take a few initial ideas, tweaked
them to get higher accuracy, but unless your
initial guesses are amazing there should be
plenty of architectures that would also work.
Answer: If and when you figure out how to
find an architecture and stop messing with
it, please tell me. We all want to know this.
I look back at these models I'm showing you
and I'm thinking I bet there's something twice
as good, I don't know what it is. There are
all kinds of ways of optimizing other hyperparameters
of deep-learning.
For example, there's somethign called Spearmint,
which is a Bayesian optimization hyperparameter
tuning. In fact, just last week a paper came
out on hyperparameter tuning. This is all
about tuning things like the learning rate
and stuff like that.
There are some people who have tried to come
up with more general architectures, and we're
going to look at one next week called ResNet,
which seem to be pretty encouraging in that
direction.
ResNet (which we're going to look at next
week) is the architecture which won ImageNet
in 2015, and the author of ResNet, Kaiming
He, super smart guy, said the reason ResNet
is so good is that it lets us build very very
deep networks. He showed a network with over
1000 layers, and it was totally state of the
art. Somebody else came along a few months
ago and built wide resnets with like 50 layers
and easily beat Kaiming He's results.
The very author of the ImageNet winner completly
got wrong why his invention was good. The
idea that any of us have any idea how to create
optimal architectures is totally wrong. That's
why I'm trying to show you what we know so
far -- the processes you can use to build
them without waiting forever.
In this case, doing your data augmentation
on a small sample in a rigorous way. Figuring
out that the dense layers are where the action
is at and precomputing the input to them.
These are the kind of things that can keep
you sane. I'm showing you the outcome of my
last week's playing with this. I can tell
you that during this time I continually fell
into the trap of running stuff on the whole
network and playing around with hyperparameters.
I had to stop myself and have a cup of tea
and ask myself is this really a good idea,
is this really a good use of my time. So we
all do it. But not you anymore because you've
been to this class.
Question: Can you run us through this one
more time -- I'm just a little confused, it
feels like we're using our validation set
as part of our training program?
Answer: We're not using the validation labels.
Nowhere here does it say val_labels. So yes,
we are absolutly using our validation set,
but we are using our validation set's inputs.
And for our test set, we have the inputs.
So next week I will show you this page again,
but with using the test set, didn't have enough
time to do it this time around. Hopefully,
we're going to see some great results. And
when we use it on the test set, you'll be
really convinced that we're not using labels
because we don't have any labels. You can
see here, all it's doing is creating pseudo-labels
by calculating what it thinks it ought to
be, based on the model we just built with
75% accuracy. And so then it's then able to
use the input data in an intelligent way and
therefore improve the accuracy.
[Time: 1.30 hour mark]
Question: Are the labels the same as what
they are in the training set? The val_pseudo,
the contents of that would be based on what
the model has learned by training on the training
set?
Answer: val_pseudo uses bn_model and bn_model
is the thing we just fitted by using the training
labels. So this is bn_model, the thing that
is .755 accuracy.
Question: So if we were to look at supervised
and unsupervised learning (and in this case
semi-supervised learning), and semi-supervised
works because you're giving it a model which
already knows about a bunch of labels - unsupervised
wouldn't know, unsupervised has nothing.
Answer: Unsupervised learning is where you're
trying to build a model where you have no
labels at all. How many people here would
be interested to hear about unsupervised learning
during this class? Okay, enough people so
I should do that. I will add it.
During the week, perhaps we can create a forum
thread about unsupervised learning and I can
learn about what you're interested in doing
with it because many things that people think
about as unsupervised learning problems actually
aren't.
Question: Earlier you talked about learning
the structure of the data that you've learned
from the dataset. Could you talk more about
that?
Answer: I don't know. Not really, other than
that picture I showed you before with the
two little spiral-y things.
Comment: And that picture was showing how
they cluster in higher dimension.
Think about that Max Welling paper we saw
or the Jason Yosinski Visualization for Bots
that we saw - the layers learn shapes and
textures and concepts. In that 80,000 test
images we saw about people driving in distracted
ways, there are lots of concepts there to
learn about ways in which people drive in
distracted ways, even though they are not
labeled. So what we're doing is we're trying
to learn better convolutional or dense features.
That's what I mean by learning more.
The structure of the data here is what do
these pictures tend to look like, and more
importantly, in what ways to they differ.
It's the ways that they differ that must be
related to how they are labeled.
Question: Can you use your updated model to
make new labels for the validation set?
Answer: Yes, you can absolutely do pseudo-labeling
on pseduo-labeling. And you should. And if
I don't get sick of running this code, I will
try it next week.
Question: Can that introduce bias towards
your validation set?
Answer: No, because we don't have any validation
labels.
One of the tricky parameters in pseudo-labeling
is in each batch, how much do I make it a
mix of training vs pseudo.
One of the big things that stopped me from
getting the test set in this week is Keras
doesn't have a way of creating batches which
have like 80% of this set and 20% of that
set, which is what I want. Because if I just
pseudo label the whole test set and then concatenated
it, then 80% of my batches are going to be
pseudo labels. And generally speaking, the
rule of thumb I've read is that somewhere
between 1/4 to 1/3 of your min-batches should
be pseduo labels. So I need to write some
code to get Keras to generate batches which
are a mix from two different places before
I can do this properly.
Question: Are your pseudo labels only as good
as the initial model you're beginning from,
or do you need to have a particular accuracy?
[Time: 1.35 hour mark]
Answer: Pseudo-labels are indeed as good as
the model you're starting from. People have
not studied this enough to know how sensitive
it is to those initial labels.
Question: Is there a rule of thumb about what
accuracy level?
Answer: No, it's too new. Just try it. My
guess is that pseudo-labels will be useful
regardless of what accuracy level you're at
because it will make it better, as long as
you're in a semi-supervised learning context,
i.e., you have a lot of unlabeled data that
you want to take advantage of.
It turns out that the path to NLP starts with
collaborative filtering. You will learn why
next week. This week we are going to learn
about collaboraive filtering. Collaborative
filtering is a way of doing recommender systems.
I sent you guys an email today with a link
to more information about collaborative filtering
and recommender systems, so read those links
if you haven't already so that you can get
an idea of what the problem we're solving
here is.
In short, what we're trying to do is to learn
to predict is who is going to like what and
how much. For example, the $1,000,000 Netflix
prize, what rating level will this person
give this movie.
If you're writing Amazon's recommender system
to show you what's on their home page. Which
products is this person likely to rank highly.
If you're trying to figure out what stuff
to show on a newsfeed, which articles is this
person likely to enjoy reading.
There's a lot of different ways of doing this,
but broadly speaking there are two main classifications
of recommender systems.
One is based on meta-data, which is this guy
filled out a survey in which he said he liked
Action Movies and SciFi, and we also have
taken all of our movies and put them into
genres and here are all of our Action/SciFi
movies, so we'll use them. Broadly speaking,
that would be a meta-data based approach.
A collaborative filtering based approach is
very different. It says let's find other people
like you, find out what they liked and assume
that you will like the same stuff. And specifically
when we say people like you, we mean people
who rated the same movies you've watched in
a similar way. And that's called collaborative
filtering.
It turns out that in a large enough dataset
that collaborative filtering is so much bette
than the metadata based approaches, that adding
metadata doesn't even improve it at all. So
when people in the Netflix prize actually
went out to IMDb and sucked in additional
data and tried to use that to make it better,
at a certain point it didn't help.
Once their collaborative filtering models
were good enough it didn't help. And that's
because (something I learned about 20 years
ago when I used to a lot of surveys and consulting),
it turns out that asking people about their
behavior is krap compared to actually looking
at people's behavior.
Let me show you what collaborative filtering
looks like. We're going to use a database
called MovieLens, and you guys will hopefully
be able to play around with this this week.
Unfortunately, Rachel and I could not find
any Kaggle competitions that were about recommender
systems and where the competitions were still
open for entries.
However, there is something called MovieLens
which is a widely studied dataset in academia.
Perhaps surprisingly, beating an academic
state-of-the-art is way easier than winning
a Kaggle competition, because in Kaggle competitions,
lots and lots and lots of people look at tht
data and they try lots and lots of things
and they use a really pragmatic approach,
whereas academic state-of-the-arts are done
by academics.
With that said, the MovieLens benchmarks are
going to be much easier to beat than any Kaggle
competition. You can download the MovieLens
dataset from the MovieLens website (grouplens.org/datasets/movielens),
and you'll see that there's one here recommended
to do research with 20 million items in it.
Also, conveniently, they have a small one
with only 100 thousand ratings. So you don't
have to build a sample, they have already
built a sample for you.
[Time: 1.40 hour mark]
I, of course, am going to use a sample. So
what I do is I read in ratings.csv.
As you can see, I've already started using
Pandas, pd is for Pandas. How many people
here have tried Pandas? Awesome! Hopefully
for those of you that don't, the peer group
pressure is kicking in. Pandas is a great
way of dealing with structured data, and you
should use it. Reading a csv file is this
easy, showing the first few items is this
easy, finding out how big it is, finding out
how many users there are, finding out how
many movies there are, are all this easy.
I want to show you this in Excel, because
that's the only way I know how to teach. What
I did was I grabbed the userID by rating,
grabbed the 15 busiest movie-watching users,
and then I grabbed the 15 most watched movies,
and then I created a crosstab of the two and
then I copied that into Excel.
Here is the table I downloaded from MovieLens
for the 15 busiest movie-watching users and
the 15 most widely watched movies. And here
are the ratings, here is the rating for User14
for Movie27 [rating=3]. Look at these guys
-- these three users have watched every single
one of these movies. I'm probably one of them,
I love movies.
So User14 kind of liked Movie27 [rating=3],
loved Movie49 [rating=5], hated Movie57 [rating=1].
So this guy User623 really liked Movie49 [rating=5],
didn't much like Movie57 [rating=3], so they
may feel the same way about Movie27 as that
user. That's the basic essence of collaborative
filtering.
We're going to try and automate it a little
bit. The way we are going to automate it is
that we are going to pretend for each movie
we had 5 characteristics - is it SciFi, Action,
DialogHeavy, is it new and does it have Bruce
Willis?
We could have those 5 things for every user
as well -- which is is this user someone who
likes SF, Action, Dialog, New, BruceWillis
movies?
What we can then do is
matrix product (or dot product) that set of
user features with that set of movie features.
If this person likes SciFi, and it's SciFi,
if this person likes Action and it is Action,
and so forth, then a high number will appear
here for the dot product of these two vectors.
And so this would be a cool way to build up
a collaborative filtering system if only we
could create these 5 items for every movie
and for every user.
Now because we don't actually know what 5
things are most important to users and what
5 things are most important for movies, we're
going to learn them. And the way we learn
them is the way we learn everything - which
is we randomize them and then use gradient
descent. So here are 5 random numbers for
every movie and 5 random numbers for every
movie, and in the middle is the dot product
of that movie with that user.
Once we have a good set of user factors and
movie factors for each one, then each of these
ratings will be similar to each of the observed
ratings, and therefore this sum-of-square
errors will be low. Currently, it is high.
With our random numbers, we start with a loss
function of 40, and we now want to use gradient
descent, and it turns out that every copy
of Excel has a gradient descent solver (called
Solver) in it, so we're going to go ahead
and use it. We're going to have to tell it
what thing to minimize, which is this, and
we tell it all of the things we are going
to change and we set that to our factors,
and we set it to a minimum, and we say Solve.
And we can see in the bottom left it is trying
to make this better and better and better
using gradient Descent.
[Time: 1.45 hour mark]
Notice I'm not saying Stocastic Gradient Descent.
Stocastic Gradient Descent means that it's
doing it mini-batch by mini-batch at a time.
Gradient Descent means using the whole dataset
every time. Excel using Gradient Descent,
not Stocastic Gradient Descent, but you get
the same answer.
You might wonder why is it so slow? It's slow
because it doesn't know how to calculate analytical
derivates so it's having to calculate the
derivatives with finite differencing, which
is slow.
So here we have a solution - we got it down
to 5, which is pretty good. We can see here
it predicted 5.14 and it was actually 5; it
predicted 3.05 and it was actually 3. So it's
done a really, really good job. It's a little
bit too easy because there are 5 x 14 (the
number of columns of factors) movie factors
and 5 x the number of rows user factors - we've
got nearly as many factors as we've have things
to calculate, but the idea is there.
There's one piece missing. The piece we're
missing is that some users probably just like
movies more than others, and some movies are
more liked than others.
This dot product does not allow us in any
way to say "This is an enthusiastic user"
or "This is a popular movie." To do that,
we have to add bias terms. So here is exactly
the same spreadsheet, but I have added one
more row to the movies part and one more column
to the users part for our biases and I have
updated the formula so as well as the matrix
multiplication, it also is adding the user
bias and the movie bias. So this is saying
"This is a very popular movie" and "This is
a very enthusiastic user".
So now that we have a collaborative filtering
plus bias, we can do gradient descent on that.
Previously our gradient descent loss function
was 5.6. We would expect it to be better with
bias because we could better specify what's
going on. Let's try it. Once again we run
Solver - Solve.
These things we're calculating are called
Latent Factors. A latent factor is some factor
that is implemented in outcome, but we don't
know what it is, we're just assuming it is
there.
What happens when people do collaborative
filtering, then then go back and say here
are the movies that have scored high on this
latent factor and that latent factor, and
in doing so you'll discover the Bruce Willis
Factor, and the SciFi factor, and so forth.
And so if you look at the Netflix prize visualizations,
you'll see these graphs people do. And the
way they do them is they literally do this
(not in Excel, because they're not that cool),
but they calculate these latent factors, and
then they draw pictures of them and then they
write the name of the movie on them.
Solver now came up with 4.6, even better.
That's interesting, in fact, I also have an
error here, I have parantheses in the wrong
place. Anytime that my rating is empty, I
really want to be setting the dot product
to empty as well. So I am going to recalculate
this with my error fixed up and see if we
get a better answer. No, not really - now
it's 4.58.
Question: I may have forgotten or missed this
-- where did the movie factors come from?
Answer: They're random. They're randomly generated
and then optimized with gradient descent.
[Time: 1.50 hour mark]
Question: For some reason this seems even
crazier than what we were doing with CNNs.
I think it is because movies I understand
more than features of images. I just don't
intuitively understand.
Answer: We can look at some pictures next
week, but during the week google for Netflix
prize visualizations and you'll see these
pictures. It really does work the way I described
it.
It figures out what are the most interesting
dimensions on which we can rate a movie, and
things like level of action, and SciFi, and
dialog-driven are very important features,
it turns out.
Rather than pre-specifying those features,
we have definitely learned from this class
that calculating features using gradient descent
is going to give us better features than trying
to engineer them by hand. Tell me next week
if you find some interesting things. If it
still feels crazy we can try to de-crazify
it a little bit.
Now let's do this in Keras. There's really
only one main new concept we have to learn
which is we started out with data not in a
crosstab form, but in this form - we have
userId, movieId, rating, timestamp triplets,
and I cross-tabed them.
Question: So the rows above and the columns
to the side, are they the variations in features
in the movies and features inthe users?
Answer: Yes. Each of these rows is one feature
of a movie and each of these columns is one
feature of a user. So one of these sets of
5 is one set of features for a user, this
user's latent factors.
Comment: I think it's interesting that you
can take random data and generate the features
out of people that you don't know and movies
that you're not looking at.
Answer: Yes. This is the thing I said at the
start of class, there's nothing mathematically
complex about gradient descent. The hard part
is unlearning the idea that this should be
hard. Gradient descent just figures it out.
Comment: You can think of this as a smaller,
more concise way to represent the users and
the movies.
Answer: In math, there's the concept of a
matrix factorization. SVD, for example, is
where you take a big matrix and turn it into
a small narrow one and a small thin one and
multiply the two together. Exactly what we're
doing.
Comment: Instead of having how User14 rated
every single movie, we just have 5 numbers
that represent it, which is pretty cool.
Question: So did you say earlier that both
the user features were random as well as the
movie features. I'm having trouble, usually
we run gradient descent on something that
has inputs that you know. Here, what is it
you know? And what would happen if you flipped
the feature for a user and a movie.
Answer: What we know is the resulting ratings.
If one of the numbers was in the wrong spot,
our loss function would be less good and therefore
there would be a gradient from that weight,
saying we should make this weight a little
higher or a little lower.
So all that gradient descent is doing is saying,
okay for every weight, if we make it a bit
higher does it get better or if we make it
a little lower does it get better? And then
we keep making them higher and lower until
we can't get any better.
We had to decide how to combine the weights
-- this was our architecture. Our architecture
was let's take a dot product of some assumed
user feature and some assumed movie feature.
And let's add (in the second case) some assumed
bias term. So we had to build an architecture
and we built the architecture using common
sense, this seems like a reasonable way of
thinking about this. I'm going to show you
a better architecture in a moment.
[Time: 1.55 hour mark]
I wanted to point out that there is something
new we're going to have to learn here, how
do you start with a numeric userId and look
up to find what is their five-element latent
factor matrix.
Now remember, when we have userIds (like 1,
2, 3), one way to specify them is by using
one-hot encoding.
One way to handle this situation would be
if this was our user matrix which was one-hot
encoded, and then we had a factor matrix containing
a whole bunch of random numbers, one way to
do it would be to take a dot product of the
one-hot encoded matrix and the factor matrix
of random numbers. What that would do is the
first row of the one-hot encoded userId matrix
would grab the first column of the factor
matrix, the second row would grab the second
column, and the third row would grab the third
column of the matrix.
One way to do this in Keras is to represent
our userIds as one-hot encodings and to create
a user factor matrix, and then take a matrix
product. That's horribly slow because if we
have 10,000 users and the one-hot encoded
userId matrix is 10,000 wide then that's a
really big matrix multiplication. All we're
actually saying is for userId #1 take the
first column, for userI #2 take the second
column, for userid #3 take the third column.
Keras has something that does this for us,
called an Embedding Layer. Embedding takes
an integer as an input and looks up and grabs
the corresponding column as output. So it's
doing exactly what we're seeing in this spreadsheet.
Question: How do you deal with missing values?
If a user has not rated a particular movie?
Answer: That's no problem. Missing values
are just ignored. If it's missing, I just
set the loss to 0.
Question: How do you break up a training and
test set?
Answer: I broke up this training and test
set randomly by grabbing random numbers and
just saying are they greater or less than
.8, and split my ratings into groups.
Question: And your choosing that from the
ratings so you have some ratings for all users
and you have some ratings for all movies.
Answer: Yes.
Here it is ... here's our dot product.
I'm going to stop using the sequential model
in Keras and start using the functional model
in Keras. I'll talk more about this next week.
There are two ways of creating models in Keras,
sequential and functional. They do similar
things, but the functional is much more flexible
and it's going to be what we're going to use
from now on. So this is going to look slightly
unfamiliar, but the idea is the same.
So we create an input layer for a user, and
then create an Embedding layer for n-Users
(671), and we want to create how many latent
factors. I decided not to create 5, but to
create 50.
And then I create a movie input and a movie
embedding with 50 factors, and then take the
dot product of those, and that's our model.
So now please compile the model and now train
it, taking the userId and movieId as input,
the rating as the target, and run it for 6
epochs and I get a 1.27 loss (an RMSE loss).
Notice that I'm not doing anything else clever,
it's just that simple dot product.
[Time: 2 hour mark]
Here's how I add the bias. I use exactly the
same kind of embedding inputs as before, and
I've encapsulated them in a function, and
my user and movie inputs are the same. Then
I create bias by just simply creating an embedding
with just a single output. So then my new
model is do a dot product, and add the user
bias, and add the movie bias. And try fitting
that, it takes me to a validation loss of
1.1.
How is that going? There are lots of sites
on the Internet where you can find out benchmarks
for MovieLens. And on the 100 thousand dataset
we're generally looking for a RMSE of .9 - the
best one here is .89. So high .89's, low .9's
would be state-of-the-art according to these
benchmarks. So we're on the right track, but
we're not there yet.
So let's try something better. Let's create
a neural net, and a neural net does the same
thing. We create a movie embedding and a user
embedding, again with 50 factors.
And this time we don't take a dot product,
we just concatenate the vectors together - stick
one on top of hte other. And because we now
have one big vector, we can create a neural
net - create a dense layer, add dropout, create
an activation, compile it, and fit it.
And after 5 epochs, we get something way better
than state-of-the-art (we couldn't find anything
better than about .9). This whole notebook
took me like 1/2 hour to write and I don't
claim to be a collaborative filtering expert.
But I think it's really cool that these things
that were written by people who write collaborative
filters for a living, places like LensKit,
a piece of software recommender systems - we
have just killed their benchmark. It took
us 10 seconds to train, so I think it's pretty
neat.
That was a very quick introduction to embeddings.
As per usual in this class, I kind of stick
the new stuff in at the end and say "Go study
it." Your job this week is to keep improving
State Farm, hopefully win the new fishieries
competition.
By the way, in the last half hour I just created
this notebook where I copied the dogs and
cats redux competition into something which
does the same thing with the fish data and
I quickly submitted it and we have one of
us in 18th place. Hopefully you can beat that
tomorrow. Most importantly, download the MovieLens
data and play with it and we'll talk more
about embeddings next week.