Today I'm going to show you what you can do
with the little set of tools we've learned
already. Part 1 of this lecture is a whirlwind
tour of a bunch of different architectures.
Different architectures -- not just because
some of them will be better at doing what
we're doing and some of them will be doing
different things.
I want to set your expectations and say that
looking at an architecture and understanding
why it does what is does is something that
took me quite a few weeks to get an intuitive
feel for. Don't feel bad because it's like
un-programming. We're going to describe something
that would be great if the model you had would
do it, and we'll say "Hit" and suddently the
model will do it, then we'll look inside of
it and wonder how it did that.
Having said that, everything we're about to
see uses only the things we've done in the
first half. We're only going to use CNNs.
There's going to be no cropping of images,
there's going to be no filtering, nothing
is going to be hand-tuned. It's just going
to be a bunch of convolutional dense layers
with activation functions. But we're going
to put them together in some interesting ways.
Let me start with one of the most important
developments over the last year or two, which
is ResNet. ResNet won the 2015 ImageNet competition.
I was delighted that ResNet won it because
it is an incredibly simple, intuitively understandable
concept and it's very simple to implement.
Let me describe as best as I can how ResNet
works. In fact, before I describe how it works,
I will show you why you should care. Let's
for now just agree that there's another architecture,
called ResNet and it's a lot like VGG. It's
used for image classification and other CNN-type
things. ResNet is actually broader than just
image classification. We use ResNet just the
same way we use the vgg16 class we're familiar
with.
We can just say create something in ResNet
[rn0=Resnet50(include_top=False).model]. There's
different sized ResNets; I'm going to use
50 because it's the smallest one and it works
super well.
I've started to use a parameter to my versions
of these networks; I've included it in the
new vgg16 as well. It's called "include_top".
It's actually the same as the Keras author
has started doing with his models. Basically
the idea is if you say "include_top=False",
you don't have to do a model.pop afterward
to remove the layers that you want to fine-tune.
include_top=False means only include the convolutional
layers and I'm going to stick my own final
classification layers on top of that. When
I do this, it's not going to give me the last
few layers.
Maybe the best way to explain that is to show
you. When I create this network, I've got
this thing at the end that says if include_top,
then we add the last few layers. If include_top
is False, then don't add the last additional
layers.
This just means you can load in a model which
is specifically designed for fine-tuning.
A short-cut. As you'll see shortly, it has
some really helpful properties.
[Time: 5 minute mark]
The winner of the cats and dogs competition
had an accuracy of .985 on the public leader-board.
We use this ResNet model the same way as usual
-- we grab our batches, we can pre-compute
some features. In every single CNN model I'm
going to show you, we're always going to pre-compute
the convolutional features.
Everything we see today will be things you
can do without pre-training any of the convolutional
layers. Pretty much everything I train will
train in a small number of steps.
That's because in my experience, when you're
working with photos it's almost never helpful
to retrain the convolutional layers. So we
can stick something on top of our ResNet in
the usual way. We can go ahead and compile
and fit it and in 48 seconds it has created
a model with .986 accuracy, which is way on
the top of the leaderboard, so that's pretty
impressive.
ResNet is designed to not be used with a standard
bunch of dense layers but is designed to be
used as an input to a glbal average pooling
layer. Let me show you what happens, if instead
of the previous model, instead I use this
model(get_ap_layers) which has 3 layers, compile
it and fit it, I get .9875 in 3 seconds. In
fact, I can even tell it that I don't want
to use 224x224 images, but I want to use 400x400
images. If I do that and create the features,
compile and fit, I get 99.3.
So this is kind of like off-the-charts to
go from somewhere like 98.5 to 99.3 -- we're
reducing the amount of error by somewhere
around 1/3 to 1/2. So this is why you should
be interested in ResNet; it's incredibly accurate.
We're using it for the thing it's best at
since originally ResNet was trained on ImageNet.
And the dogs-and-cats competition looks a
lot like ImageNet images -- they're single
pictures of a single thing that's reasonably
large in the picture. So this is something
which the ResNet approach is particularly
good for.
I do want to show you how it works, because
I think it's fascinating and awesome. I'm
going to stick to the same approach that we've
used so far when we've talked about architectures,
which is any shape represents a matrix of
activations and any arrow represents a layer
operation, so there's a convolution, or dense
layer, with an activation function.
ResNet looks a lot like VGG. So imagine there's
some part of the model down here that we're
not going to worry about too much. We're kind
of like halfway through the model and there's
some hidden activation layer. With VGG, the
approach is basically a 3x3 CONV, some activations,
another 3x3 CONV, some activations, another
3x3 CONV, some activations, and from time-to-time
a maxPooling.
ResNet looks a lot like this. It has exactly
that path, which is a bunch of convolutions
and ReLu's on top of each other. But it does
something else.
There's this bit that comes out ... and remember
when we have two arrows coming in to a shape
that means we're adding things. You'll notice
here that there's no shapes on the way here;
this arrow does not represent a convolution,
it does not represent a dense layer - it actually
represents Identity, in other words we do
nothing at all.
[Time: 10 minute mark]
This whole thing here is called a ResNet Block.
If we represent a ResNet block as a square,
ResNet is just a whole bunch of these blocks
stacked on top of each other. And then the
input (which is the input data) and then the
output.
Another way to look at this is to just look
at the code. I think the code is nice and
intuitive to understand. Let's have a look
at this thing they call and Indentity Block.
So here's the code for what I just described.
You might notice that everything I selected
here looks like a totally standard VGG block.
I've got a Conv-2D a Batch Normalization and
an Activation Function -- looks like our improved
VGG. Another Convolution, another Batch Norm,
another Activation, another Conv2D, another
Batch Norm ... but then this is the magic
that makes it ResNet -- this single line of
code.x = (merge [x,input_tensor], mode=sum).
It does something incredibly simple, it takes
the result of those 3 convolutions and it
adds it to our original input.
So, normally we have the output of some
block is equal to convolutions of convolutions
of convolutions to the inputs to that block
-- y = c(c(c(x))). But we're doing something
different, we're say the output to
the block at time t+1 is equal to the convolutions
of convolutions of convolutions of the hidden
state at time-t plus the hidden state at time-t
... that is the magic of ResNet.
So why is it that that can give us this huge
improvement in the state-of-the-art in such
a short period of time. This is something
that is somewhat controversial. The authors
of the ResNet paper described it in a number
of ways. Basically there are two main reasons:
The first is they claim that you can create
much deeper networks this way because when
you're back-propogating the weights, back-propogating
through an identity is easy -- you're never
going to have an explosion of gradients, or
an explosion of activations. The authors created
a ResNet with over 1000 layers.
But it also turned out to be a bit of a red-herring
because a few months ago some other folks
created a ResNet which was not at all big
(I think it had like 40 or 50 layers), but
instead it was very wide, it had a lot of
activations ... and that did even better.
The second reason why it seems to have stood
the test of time which is if we take this
equation and we rearrange it -- subtract h.t
from both sides. That gives us the hidden
activations at the next time period minus
the hidden activations at the previous time
period equals the ResNet block acting on the
hidden layer at the previous time.
When you write it like that, it might make
you realize something -- we're learing a lot
of weights which make our previous guess as
to the predictions a little bit better -- let's
take the previous predictions we got and try
to build a set of things which makes them
a little bit better.
[Time: 15 minute mark]
In statistics, this is called the residual.
A residual is the difference between the thing
you are trying to predict and your actuals.
So what they did here in ResNet is they designed
an architecture that learns how to model the
residuals and learns how to build a bunch
of layers which continually slightly improve
the answer.
For those of you that have a machine-learning
background you would recognize this as essentially
being boosting. Boosting refers to the idea
of having a bunch of models where each model
tries to predict the errors. If you have a
whole chain of those, you can add them all
together and boosting is a way of getting
a much improved ensemble.
ResNet is not manually doing boosting, it's
not manually doing anything. It's just this
single one extra line of code. It's all in
the architecture.
Question: I have a question about dimensionality.
I would assume that by the time you're close
to output, the dimensions would be so different
that element-wise addition wouldn't be possible
between the last layer and the first layer.
Answer: It's important to know that this imput
tensor is the input tensor to the block. So
you'll see there's no MaxPooling inside here,
there's no strides inside here -- so the dimensionality
remains constant throughout all these lines
of code. So we can add them up. And then we
can do our Strides or MaxPooling and then
we do another Identity Block. So we're essentially
adding it back to the input of the block,
not the input of the original image. And that's
what we want -- we want to say the input to
each block is our best prediction so far.
Question: Qualitatively, how does this compare
to Drop Out?
Answer: In some ways, in most ways, it's unrelated
to Drop Out. Indeed, you can add Drop Out
to the end of a ResNet block after this merge,
you can add Drop Out. ResNet is not a regularization
technique, per se. Having said that, it does
seem to have excellent generalization characteristics.
I just searched the ImageNet codebase and
ImageNet did not use any Drop Out, they didn't
find it necessary. But this is very problem-dependent.
If you have only a small amount of data, you
may need Drop Out.
Another reason you don't need Drop Out ... Remember
what I did here at the end was I created a
model which had a special kind of layer called
a GlobalAveragePolling layer. This is the
next key thing I want to teach you about.
It's a really important concept and it's going
to come up a couple of times during today's
class.
Let's describe what a Global Average Polling
layer is. Here is the output of the pre-computed
ResNet on our 224x224, it's 13x13. The pre-computed
convolutional residual blocks, 13x13 output
is 2048.
One way of thinking about this would be to
say each of these 13x13 blocks could say how
cat-y or how dog-y each one of those 13 blocks.
And so rather than MaxPooling, which is taking
the maximum of the grid, we could take average
pooling. Which is to say across those 13x13
areas, what is the average amount of dog-iness
in each one, what is the average amount of
cat-iness in each one. And that's what Global
Average Pooling does -- whatever the input
to Global Average Pooling is, it will take
all of the x-components and all of the y-components
and take the average for every one of these
2048 filters.
[Time: 20 minute mark]
What this is doing taking an input of 13x13
matrix and return a single output vector of
2048. That vector is on average how much does
this whole image have each of those 2048 features.
ResNet was originally trained with Global
Average Polling 2D (you can see that in the
ResNet code). This was actually written before
Global Average Polling 2D layer existed, so
they just did it manually. Because ResNet
was trained originally with this layer, that
means it was trained such that the last identity
block was creating features that were designed
to be averaged together. That means that when
we used this kind of architecture, we got
the best results because that was how ResNet
was originally designed to be used.
Question: If you had a wider network without
the input fed forward to the output activation,
couldn't you get the same result? The extra
activations in the wider network pass the
input all the way through all the layers.
Answer: Well, you can in theory have convolutional
filters that don't do anything. But the point
is having to learn that is learning lots and
lots of filter design.
Maybe the best way to describe this is everything
I'm telling you about architectures is in
some ways irrelevant. You can create nothing
but dense layers at every level of your model.
Dense layers have every input connected to
every output so every architecture I'm telling
you about is just a simplified version of
that. But it's really helpful to do that.
It's really helpful to help our SGD optimizer
by making it so that the default thing it
can do is the thing we want. So, yes, in theory,
a CONV net or a connected net could learn
to do the same thing that ResNet does. In
practice, it would take a lot of parameters
for it to do so, and time to do so. This is
why we care about architectures. In practice,
having a good architecture makes a huge difference.
That's a good question.
Question: Would it be fair to say that if
VGG were trained with Average Pooling it would
yield better results?
Answer: I'm not sure. One of the reasons,
maybe the main reason that ResNet doesn't
need Drop Out is because we're using Global
Average Pooling. Because we're using Global
Average Pooling, there's a lot less parameters
in the model. Remember the vast majority of
the parameters in a model are in the dense
layer - because you have m inputs and n outputs,
you have m x n connections.
So in VGG, that first dense layer had something
like 300 million parameters because it had
every possible feature of the convolutional
layer, by each of the 300 convolutional layers,
created a lot of features and made it easy
to overfit.
With Global Average Pooling and not having
any dense layers we have a lot less parameters,
so it can generalize better. It also generalizes
better because we're treating each of those
7x7 or 13x13 areas in the same way. We're
saying how dog-y or cat-y are each of these.
It turns out that these Global Average Pooling
models do seem to generalize well.
[Time: 25 minute mark]
Question: Why do we use Global Average Pooling
instead of Max Pooling?
Answer: It depends, you can try both. In this
case, the images in the Dogs and Cats competition
are images where nearly the entire frame is
a dog or a cat. So if you did Max Pooling
you would say which bit of that 7x7 or 13x13
grid down-sampled has the most dog-iness or
cat-iness and I only care about that.
That's unlikely to give you as good a result
as looking at every part of the image and
average them all together. On the other hand
(and I haven't tried this), in the Fishieries
competion, the fish is generally a very small
part of the image. So maybe in the Fishieries
competition we should use a Global Max Pooling
layer. Give it a try and let us know how it
goes. Because in that case you actually don't
care about all the of the other parts of the
image that have nothing to do with fish. Would
be very interesting to try.
ResNet is very powerful but it has not been
studied much at all for transfer learning.
This does not mean that it will not work well
for transfer learning. I just literally haven't
found a single paper yet where someone has
analyzed its effectiveness for transfer learning.
To me, 99.999% of what you will work on will
be transfer learning. If you're not using
transfer learning, it means you're looking
at a dataset that is a little different from
anything that anyone has looked at before,
that none of the features in any model is
remotely applicable. That's going to be rare.
Nearly all of the work I've seen on transfer
learning, both with Kaggle winners and in
terms of papers, uses VGG. I think one of
the reasons for that (as we talked about in
Lesson 1/Lesson 2), the VGG architecture really
is designed to create layers of gradually
increasing complexity. All the work I've seen
on visualizing layers tends to use VGG or
something similar to that as well. Like that
Max Zeiler stuff we saw, or those Jason Yosinski
videos we saw. So we've seen how VGG networks
create gradually more complex representations.
Which is exactly what we want in transfer
learning. We want to ask how different is
this new domain from the previous domain,
and then we can pick a layer far enough back
that the features seem to work well.
For that reason, we're going to go back to
looking at VGG now, and look at the Fishieries
competition. The Fishieries competition is
actually very interesting. The pictures are
from about a dozen boats, and each one of
these boats has a fixed camera, daytime and
nighttime shots. So every picture kind of
has the same basic shape and structure for
each of the 12 boats with fixed cameras. Somewhere
in there, there's one or more fish. Your job
is to say what kind of fish it is. The fish
are pretty small.
One of the things that makes this interesting
is that this is the somewhat wierd, kind of
complex different thing to ImageNet that is
exactly the kind of thing you are going to
be dealing with every time you do a computer
vision problem or any kind of CNN problem.
It's very likely that the thing you're doing
won't be quite the same as what the academics
have been looking at. So trying to figure
out how to do a great job on the Fishieries
competition is a great example.
When I started on the Fisheries competition,
I just did the usual thing, which was create
a VGG model and fine-tuned it to have just
8 outputs (because we have to differentiate
between 8 types of fish). As per usual, I
pre-computed the VGG network, and then everything
after that I just used the pre-computed convolutional
layers. As per usual, the first thing I did
was to stick a few dense layers on top and
see how that goes.
[Time: 30 minute mark]
The nice thing about this is you can see each
epoch takes less than a second to run. When
people talk about needing lots of data or
lots of time, it's not really true because
for most stuff you're going to be doing in
real life, you're going to be using pre-computed
convolutional features.
In our validation set, we get an accuracy
of 96.2%, cross entropy loss of .18. That
seems pretty good, it seems to be classifying
fish pretty well. Here's the problem, there's
all kinds of data leakage going on. This is
one of the most important concepts to understand
when it comes to building any kind of model,
or any kind of machine-learning project. Leakage.
Leakage. There was a paper (I thinik it actually
won the KDD best paper award a couple of years
ago) which studied data leakage. Data leakage
occurs when something about the target you're
trying to predict is encoded in the things
you're predicting with, but that information
is either not going to be available or it
won't be helpful in practice when you're going
to use the model.
For example, in the Fisheries competition,
different boats fish in different parts of
the sea. Different parts of the sea have different
fish in them. So in the Fisheries competition,
if you just use something representing which
boat the image came from, you can get a pretty
good accurate validation set result.
What I mean by that ... this is a list of
the size of each photo, along with how many
times that appeared. You can see that there's
basically a small number of sizes that appear.
It turns out that if you create a simple linear
model that says any image 1192x670 - what
kind of fish is that; any image that's 1280x720,
what kind of fish is that - you get a pretty
accurate model. Because these are the different
ships, the different ships have different
cameras, the different cameras have different
resolutions.
This isn't helpful in practice because what
the Fisheries people actually wanted to do
was to use this to find out when people are
illegally or accidentally over-fishing or
fishing in the wrong way, bringing up dolphins,
they want to know about it. So any model that
says I know what kind of boat this is is entirely
useless. So this is an example of leakage.
In this particular paper I mentioned, the
authors looked at machine-learning competitions
and discovered that over 50% of them had some
kind of data leakage.
I spoke to Claudia after she presented that
paper and I asked her if she thought that
regular machine learning projects inside companies
would have more or less leakage than that.
She said a lot more. In compettions, people
have tried hard to figure out leakage beforehand.
And if there is leakage, you're almost certain
somebody's going to find it (because it's
a competition). Whereas if you have leakage
in your dataset, it's very likely you won't
even know about it until you put the model
in production and find out it doesn't work
as well as expected.
Rachel's Comment: I was going to add that
it might not help you in the competition if
your test set is brand-new boats that weren't
in your training set.
Response: Let's talk about that. Trying to
win a Kaggle competition and trying to do
a good job are somewhat independent. When
I'm working on a Kaggle competition, I'm trying
to win a Kaggle competition. I have a clear
metric and I try to optimize the metric. Sometimes
that means finding leakage and taking advantage
of it. In this case, Step #1 for me in the
Fisheries competion was to say can I take
advantage of this leakage.
I want to be very clear. This is the exact
opposite of what you would want to do if you
were trying to help the Fisheries people create
a good model.
Having said that, there's $150,000 dollars
at stake. I could donate that to the Fred
Hollows Foundation and get lots of people
their sight back, so winning this would be
good.
[Time: 35 minute mark]
Let me show you how I tried to take advantage
of this leakage (which is totally legal in
a Kaggle competition), and see what happens.
Then I'll talk more about Rachel's comment
after that.
So the first thing I did was I made a list
for every file of how big the image dimensions
were. I did that for the validation and training
set. I normalized them by subtracting the
mean and dividing by the standard deviation.
And then I created an almost exact copy of
the previous model I showed you. This time,
rather than using a sequential API, I used
a functional API. Other than that, it's almost
identical.
The only difference is in this line, where
what I've done is I've taken not just the
input which is the output of the last convolutional
layer of my VGG model, but I have a second
input. And the second input is what size image
is it.I should mention that I've one-hot encoded
the image sizes because they're treated like
categories.
So I now have an additional input. One is
the output of my convolutional model, one
is the image size. Then right at the very
last step, I concatenate the two together.
So my model is basically a standard last two
layers VGG model, so three dense layers, and
then I have my input and then I have another
input, concatenated to create the output.
What this can do now is the last dense layer
can learn to combine the image features along
with this meta-data. This is useful for all
kinds of things (other than taking advantage
in a dastardly way of leakage).
For example, if you were doing a collaborative
filtering model, you might have information
about the user. Such as their age, their gender,
their favorite genres. This is how you incorporate
that kind of meta-data into a standard neural
net.
So I merged the two together. Initially it's
looking encouraging. If we go back and look
at the standard model, we have .84, .94, .95.
This multi-input model is a little better,
.86, .95, .96. So that's encouraging.
But interestingly, the model without using
leakage gets somewhere about 96.5, 97.5, 98
-- it's kind of all over the place, which
isn't a great sign.
This multi-input model does not get better
than that. It's best is also around 97.5.
Why is that? This is very very common when
people try to utilze meta-data in deep-learning
models. It often turns out that the main thing
you're looking at (in this case the image)
already encodes everything that your meta-data
has anyway.
In this case, yes, the size of the image tells
us which boat it comes from. But you can also
just look at the picture and see which boat
it comes from.
So by the later epochs, the convolutional
model has figured out already what boat it
came from, so the leakage actually turned
out not to be helpful.
It's amazing how often people find meta-data
and incorporate it into their model and how
often it turns out to be a waste of time because
the raw, real data (the audio, the pictures,
the language) turns out to encode all that
anyway.
Finally, I wanted to go back to what Rachel
was talking about which is what would have
happened if this did work, if this gave us
a much better validation result than the non-leakage
model.
[Time: 40 minute mark]
If I then submitted to Kaggle and my leaderboard
result was great, that would mean that I had
found leakage that the Kaggle administrators
didn't and I'm possibly on the way to winning
the competition. Having said that, the Kaggle
competition administrators first and foremost
try to avoid leakage. Indeed if you do try
and submit this to the leaderboard, you'll
find it doesn't do that great. I haven't looked
into it as to why. I don't know how yet, but
somehow the competition administrators have
made some attempt to address the leakage.
The kind of ways that we did that when I was
at Kaggle would be to do things like stratified
sampling, enforce that every ship has to have
the same number of fish and the same type
of fish, and limit leakage where you could.
Honestly it's a very difficult thing to do,
and this impacts a lot more than machine-learning
competitions. Every one of your real-world
projects, you're going to have to think long
and hard about how you can replicate real-word
conditions without leakage.
Maybe the best example I can come up with
is when you put your model into production
(it will probably be a few months after you've
grabbed the data and trained it), how much
has the world changed? Wouldn't it be great
instead if you could create a test set with
data from a few months later than your training
set. Again, you're really trying to replicate
the situation that you actually have when
you put your model into production.
Note from Rachel: They are releasing another
test set later on in the Fishery competition.
Question: Did you do two classifications,
one for the boats and one for the fish? Is
that a waste of time?
Answer: I have two inputs, not two outputs.
So my input is the one-hot encoded size of
the image, which I assumed is a proxy for
the boat category, and some discussion on
the Kaggle forum that's a reasonable assumption.
Question: Can you find a good way of isolating
the fish on the images and then do the classification
on that?
Answer: Let's do that now, shall we?
Multi-Output. There's a lot of nice things
about how competitions are structured. One
of the things I really like is in most of
them you can create or combine your own data
sources, as long as you share it with the
community. One of the people in the Fisheries
competition has gone through and by hand put
a little square around every fish. That's
called annotating the dataset.
Specifically, this kind of annotation is called
a bounding box. A bounding box is a box in
which your object fits. Because of the rules
of Kaggle, he had to make it available to
everybody in the Kaggle community, and he
provided a link on the Kaggle forum.
So I went ahead and downloaded those -- they're
a bunch of JSON files that basically look
like this.
For each image, for each fish, it had the
height and width in x and y.
The details in the code don't matter too much.
I just went ahead and found the largest fish
in each image and created a list of them.
So I've got now my training bounding boxes
and my validation bounding boxes. For things
that didn't have a fish, I just had zero-zero-zero-zero
-- empty bounding boxes.
So, as always when I want to understand the
data, the first thing to do is to look at
it. In computer vision problems, it's easy
to look at data, so I went ahead and created
this little show bounding box (show_bb) thing.
I'm going to try it on an image -- here's
the fish and here's the bounding box.
[Time: 45 minute mark]
Question: Adding meta-data, is that not useful
for both CNNs and RNNs or just for CNNs?
Answer: It's got nothing to do with the architecture.
It's entirely about the semantics of the data.
If your text, or audio, or other unstructured
data in some way encodes the information in
the meta-data, the meta-data is unlikely to
be helpful.
For example, in the NetFlix prize, in the
early stages of competition, people found
that it was helpful to link to IMDb and bring
in information about the movies. In later
stages, they found it wasn't. The reason why
is that in later stages they had figured out
how to extrapolate from the ratings themselves,
they basically contained all the information.
Question: VGG required images all the same
size in training. In the Fisheries case, are
different size images being used for training?
How do you train a model with different dimensions?
Answer: How do we deal with different size
images? I'm about to show you some tricks,
but throughout this course, we have always
resized everything to 224x224. Whenever you
use get_batches, I default to resizing images
to 224x224 because that's what the Internet
did. With the exception that in my previous
ResNet model, I showed you resizing to 400x400.
So far ... in fact in everything we're doing
this year, we're going to resize everything
to be the same size.
Question: Is the 400x400 image resize in ResNet
because there are two different ResNet models?
Answer: No, it's not. I'll show you how that
happened in a moment, we're going to get to
that.
So, now we've got these bounding boxes, here
is the complexity -- both the practical one
and the Kaggle one. The Kaggle complexity
is the rules say that you're not allowed to
manually edit the test set -- we can't put
bounding boxes in the test set. The practical
complexity is that they are trying to create
an automatic warning system and they don't
want to have somebody drawing a box around
the fish.
So what we're going to do is build a model
that can find these bounding boxes automatically.
How do we do that?
It may surprize you to know that we're going
to use exactly the same techniques we've always
used.
Here is the exact same model again. But this
time instead of having something at the end
which has 8 softmax outputs, we also have
4 linear outputs, i.e., 4 outputs with no
activation function.
When we train this model, we now have 2 outputs,
and when we compile it, we're going to say
this model has 2 outputs -- one is the 4 outputs
with no activation function, and the other
is the 8 softmax.
When I compile it, I want to optimize the
mean square error for the first one, and for
the second one I want to optimized the entropy
function. For the first, I want you to multiply
the loss by .001 because the mean square error
of finding the location of the image is going
to be a lot bigger number than the categorical
cross-entropy. And then when you train it,
I want you to use the bounding boxes as the
labels for the first output, and the fish
types as the labels for the second output.
What this is going to have to do is figure
out how to come up with a bunch of dense layers
capable of doing these two things simultaneously.
In other words, we now have something that
looks like this -- two outputs, one input.
[Time: 50 minute mark]
Both of the two outputs have their own dense
layer. It would be possible to do it like
this instead. That is to say each of the two
outputs could have two dense layers of their
own.
In this case I'm going to talk about the pros
and cons. In this case, both of my last layers
are both going to have to use the same set
of features to generate both the bounding
boxes and the fish classes.
So let's see how this goes. We just go fit
as usual but now that we have two outputs,
we get a lot more information. We get the
bounding box loss, we get the fish classification
loss, we get the total loss (which is equal
to .001 times the bounding box, which you
can see is over 1000 times bigger than this;
you can see why we multiplied by .001), then
we get the validation loss, the total bounding
box validation loss, and the validation classification
loss.
So here is something pretty interesting. The
first thing I wanted to point out is after
I fit it a little bit, we actually get a much
better accuracy.
Maybe this is counter-intuitive. We're now
saying our model has exactly the same capacity
as before, our previous dense layer is of
size 512. Before, that last layer only had
to do one thing, to tell us what kind of fish
it was.
Now it has to do two things: it has to tell
us where the fish is and what kind of fish
it is. Yet it's still done better. Why has
it done better?
The reason it's done better is by telling
it we want to use those features to figure
out where the fish is, we're giving it a hint
about what to look for. We've given it more
information about what to work on.
Interestingly, even if we didn't use a bounding
box for anything else and just threw it away,
we've already found a much better model.
You notice also the model is much more stable,
before our loss was all over the place.
So by having multiple outputs, we've created
a much more stable, resiliant, and accurate
classification model. And we also have bounding
boxes.
The best way to look at how accurate bounding
boxes are is to look at the feature.
So I do a prediction for the first 10 validation
examples (it's important to use a validation
set any time we're looking at how good your
model is).
This time I slightly increased the function
to show the bounding boxes to now include
a yellow box for my prediction and a deep
red box for my actual, and there it is.
So I want to make it very clear here -- we
haven't done anything clever. We didn't do
anything to program this. We just said there
is an output which will have 4 outputs. It
has no activation function, so it's linear.
I want you to use mean square error to find
a set of weights that would optimize those
weights such that the bounding boxes and your
predictions are as close as possible.
And somehow, it has done that. That is to
say, very often if you're trying to get a
neural net to do something, your first step
before you create some complex programming
heuristic thing, is just ask the neural net
to do it. And very often it does.
Question: Why do both in the same fitting,
instead of training the neural net to find
the boxes first and feeding that as imput
to recognize fishes?
Answer: We can. The first thing I want to
point out is getting it. Even then I would
still have the first stage do both at the
same time because the more compatible tasks
we can give it (like where is the fish, and
what kind of fish is it), the more it can
create an internal representation that is
as appropriate as possible.
Now if we want to go away over the next couple
of weeks and drop out these fish and create
a second model, I can almost guarantee you'll
get into the top 10 of this competition.
[Time: 55 minute mark]
And the reason I can almost guarantee that
is there was quite a similar competition on
Kaggle last year, or earlier this year, which
was trying to identify particular whales by
literally saying which individual whale is
it. All of the top 3 in that competition did
some kind of bounding box prediction or some
kind of cropping and then modeled a second
layer on the cropped features.
Question: Are the four bounding box outputs
the vertical and horizontal sides of the box
and the two coordinates of the center?
Answer: It's whatever we were given, which
was not quite that. It was the height, width,
x and y.
Question: So how many people in the Kaggle
competition are using this sort of model?
If you came up with this with a bit of tinkering,
do you think that you would stay in the top
10? Or would this be an obvious sort of thing
that people would tend to do so your ranking
would drop over time as everyone else incorporates
this?
Answer: So I'm going to show you a few techniques
I used this week. They're all very basic,
very normal. We're at a point now where this
is a $150,000 dollar competition where over
500 people have entered. I am currently 20th.
So the stuff that you're learning in this
course is not at all well-known. There's never
been an applied deep-learning course before.
The people who are above me in this competition
are the people who have figured these things
out. They've read a bunch of papers and studied
and whatever else.
I definitely think that the people in this
course, particularly if some of you teamed
up together, would have a very good chance
at winning this competition because it's a
perfect fit for everything we've been talking
about. And particularly collaborate on the
forums and stuff like that.
I should mention that I haven't even done
any cropping yet. This is just using the whole
image, which is clearly not the right way
to tackle this.
I was actually intentionally trying not to
do too well because I'm going to have to release
this notebook to everyone on the Kaggle forum
because it's $150,000 dollars and I didn't
want to say here's a way to get into the top
10 because that's not fair to everyone else.
To answer you question -- by the end of the
competition, to win one of these things, you've
got to do everything right at every point.
Everytime you fail, you have to try again.
Tenacity is part of winning these things.
I know from experience -- being on top of
the leaderboard and waking up the next day
and finding that people have passed you. You
know they have found something that is there
that you haven't found yet.
That's part of what makes competing in the
Kaggle competition so different from looking
at academic papers, or looking at old Kaggle
competitions. It's a really great test of
your own processes, and your own grit.
What you'll probably find yourself doing is
repeatedly playing around with hyper-parameters
and minor architectural details because it's
just so addictive.
I hope some of you will consider seriously
investing -- like putting an hour a day in
to a competition. I learn far more doing that
than anything else I have ever done. It's
totally different than just playing around.
Afterwards, every real-world project that
I've ever done greatly benefited from that
experience.
To give you a sense of this ... Here's #7,
here's #6 -- I can't even see that fish, but
it's done a pretty good job.
I think maybe it knows that people tend to
float around where the fish is or something,
because that fish is pretty hard to see. This
is just a 224x224 image, so this model is
brilliant. The amount of time it took to train
was under 10 seconds.
[Time: 1:00 hour mark]
Question: Is there a way to find the bounding
box without hand-coding it?
Answer: Before we look at finding things without
manually annotating bounding boxes, I want
to talk more about different sized images.
So let's talk about sizes, specifically talk
about in which situations is our model going
to be sensitive to the size of the inputs,
like a pre-trained model.
It's all about what are these layer operations
exactly.
If it's a dense layer, then there's a weight
going from every input to every output. So
if you have a different sized input, then
that's not going to work at all because your
weight matrix of the dense layer is just simply
of the wrong size. Who knows what it should
do.
What if it's a convolutional layer? If it's
a convolutional layer, then we have a little
set of weights for each 3x3 block, for each
different feature. And that 3x3 block is going
to be slid over to create the outputs.
If the image is bigger, it doesn't change
the number of weights. It just means that
this block is going to be slid around more,
and the output will be bigger.
The max pooling layer doesn't have any weights.
A Batch Normalization layer simply cares about
the number of weights of the previous layer.
So when you think about it the only layer
that really cares what size your input is
is the dense layer. And remember that with
VGG, nearly all of the layers are convolutional
layers.
So that's why we can say not only include
top=False, but we can also choose what size
we want.
So if you look at my new version of the VGG
model, I've actually got something here that
says, if size is not equal to 224x224, the
don't try to add the fully-connected blocks
at all -- just return.
So if we cut off whatever our architecture
is before any dense layers happen, then we're
going to be able to use it on any size input
to create those convolutional features. That's
what I'm about to show you now.
Question: For a convolutional layer, shouldn't
the input size be fixed?
Answer: There's no reason it has to be fixed.
A dense layer has to be fixed, because a dense
layer has a specific weight matrix.
And the input to that weight matrix generally
is the flattened out version of the previous
convolutional layer. And the size of that
depends on the size of the image. The convolutional
weight matrix simply depends on the filter
size, not on the image size.
So, let's try it. Specifically, we're going
to try building something called a Fully Convolutional
Net, which is going to have no dense layers
at all.
So the input (as usual) will be the output
of the last convolutional layer. But this
time when we create our VGG16 model, we're
going to tell it we want it to be 640x360
[vgg640 = Vgg16((360,6740)).model]
Be careful here. When we talk about matrices,
we talk about rows by columns. When we talk
about images, we talk about columns by rows.
So a 640x360 image is a 360x640 matrix.
I mention this because I've screwed it up.
But I knew I screwed it up because I always
draw pictures. So when I drew the picture
I saw I had this little squashed boat, I knew
that I screwed it up.
[Time: 1:05 hour mark]
Question: Do the weights you are loading here
for CNN layers also have batch normalization?
Answer: Yes, this is the exact same VGG16
network we've been using since I added BatchNormalization.
Nothing's been changed other than this one
piece of code I just showed you which says
you can use different sizes, and if you do,
don't add fully connected layers.
So now I've got this VGG model which is expecting
a 640x360 input. I can then add to it my top
layers. This time my top layers are going
to get an input of size 22x40.
Normally our VGG's final layer is 14x14, or
if you include the final MaxPooling, it is
7x7.
In this case, though, it's 22x40. That's because
we've told it we're not going to pass a 224x224,
we're going to pass it a 640x360.
So this is what happens -- we end up with
a different output shape.
So if we now try to pass that to the same
dense layer we used before, it wouldn't work,
it would be the wrong size. We're actually
going to do something different anyway. We're
not going to use any pre-trained, fully-connected
weights. We're instead going to have no dense
layers at all.
Instead, we're going to do:
Convolution2D, BatchNormalization, MaxPooling,
Convolution2D, GlobalAveragePooling2D.
The best way to look at this is to see what's
happening to our shape.
It goes from 22x40 until the MaxPooling, then
11x20. Until the next MaxPooling - 5x10.
And because this is rectangular, the last
MaxPooling I did a 1,2 shape; that gives me
a square result - 5x5.
Then I do a convolutional layer, in which
I have just 8 filters. Remember I have just
8 types of fish.
There are no other weights after this. In
fact, even the Dropout is not doing anything
because I've set my p value to zero, so ignore
that Dropout layer.
So we're going straight from a convolutional
layer which is grid size 5x5 and have 8 filters.
And then we're going to average across the
5x5, and that's going to give us something
of size 8.
So if we now say, please train this model
and please try and make these 8 things equal
to the classes of fish.
Now you have to think backwards. How would
it do that? If it were to do that for us (and
it will because it's going to use SGD), what
would it have to do?
Well, it has no ability to use any weights
to get to this point (GlobalAveragePolling2D),
so it has to do everything by the time it
gets to this point (Convolution2D(8,3,3, border_mode='same')).
Which means this Convolution2D layer is going
to have to have in each of its 5 grid areas
something saying how fish-y is that area,
because that's all it can do. After that,
all it can do is to average them together.
We haven't done anything specifically to capture
it this way, we just have to create an architecture
which had to do that.
My feeling is this out to work fairly well
because as we saw in that earlier picture,
the fish only appears in one little spot.
As we discussed earlier, maybe even a Global
Max Pooling could be better.
So let's try this. We can fit it as per usual,
and you can see here, even without bounding
boxes, we've got a pretty good and a pretty
stable result (97.6) in about 30 seconds.
When I then tried this on the Kaggle leaderboard,
I got a much better result.
The 20th place was just me averaging together
four different models, four of the models
I'm showing you today.
But this one on its own was .986, which would
be 22nd. So
that little model on its own would get us
22nd position.
No data augmentation. No pseudo-labeling.
We're not using the validation set to help
us (which we should).
[Time: 1:10 hour mark]
So you can get 22nd position with this very
simple approach, which is to use a slightly
larger image and use a fully convolutional
network.
There's something else cool about this fully
convolutional network which can get us in
the 22nd position which is that we can actually
look at the output of this layer, the Convolutional2D
layer ... and remember it's 5x5.
Question: How are you using VGG?
Answer: VGG (as always before) is the input
to this model. Every single model I'm showing
you today, I've pre-computed the output of
the last convolutional layer.
I say get_data and get a 360x640 sized data
[trn = get_data(path='train', (360,640))]
and that gives me my image. Then I
create my model and pop off the last MaxPooling
layer [vgg640.pop()], and then call predict
to get the features from that last layer.
It's what we always do.
The only difference is that we passed 360x640
for our constructor for the model, and we
passed 360,640 to the get_data.
Question: So then you're adding a lot of layers
later on?
Answer: Exactly. Everything I'm showing you
today is taking as input the last convolutional
layer.
Question: Why did you replace all dense layers
with CNN?
Answer: A couple of reasons why.
The first beacuse the authors of the paper
which created fully ConvolutionalNet found
that it worked pretty well. The GlobalAveragePolling2D
layer turns out to have excellent generalization
characteristics.
You notice here we have no DropOut, yet we're
in 22nd place on the leaderboard.
The final reason is the thing I'm about to
show you ... which is we're maintained a sense
of x y coordinates all the way through, which
means that we can now visualize this last
layer.
I can say let's create a function which takes
our model's input and our 4th from last layer
as output (that is the convolutional layer
I just showed you).
I'm going to take that and I'm going to pass
into it the features of my first validation
image and draw a picture of it.
Here is my picture. You can see it's done
exactly what we thought it would do. It's
had to figure out that there's a fish here.
So these fully convolutional networks have
a nice side effect which is they allow us
to find whereabouts the interesting parts
are.
Question: Why does MaxPooling reduce the dimensions
along the x and y by half?
Answer: The default parameters for MaxPooling
are 2,2. So it's taking each 2x2 square and
replacing it with the largest value in that
2x2 square.
This is not the most high-res heatmap we've
ever seen. The obvious thing to make it all
more high-res would be to remove all the MaxPooling
layers.
So here's exactly the same thing as before,
but I've removed all the MaxPooling layers.
That means my model remains at 22x40 all the
way through. Everything else is the same.
That does not give quite as accurate a result.
You get 95.2 instead of 97.6.
But on the other hand, we do have a much higher
resolution grid. So if we now do exactly the
same thing to create the heatmap.
[Time: 1:15 hour mark]
The other thing we're going to do is we're
going to resize the heatmap to 360x640
[return scipi.misc.imresize(conv,(360,640))].
By default, this resize command will try and
interpolate and return big pixels for interpolated
small pixels. And that gives us, for this
image, this answer, which is much more interesting.
Now we can stick one on top of the other,
like so.
This tells us a lot. It tells us that on the
whole, this is doing a good job, identifying
the fish-y thing, the albacore-y thing (because
we're asking here for the albacore). Remember,
that layer of the model is 8x22x40 so we have
to ask how much like albacore is each one
of those areas, or how much like shark is
each of those areas.
So when we called this function, it returned
a heatmap for every type of fish. We can pass
in zero (the number for albacore) [ get_cm2(inp,
0) ]. Plus four is the number for no fish,
one of the classes you have to predict in
this competition is no fish.
So we could say how much of this part of the
picture looks like the no fish class [ get_cm2(inp,4)
].
What happens is if you look at the no fish
version of this heatmap, you get the exact
opposite. You get a big blue spot here and
pink all around it.
The other thing I wanted to point out here
-- these areas of pink-ishness that are not
where the fish is. This is telling me that
our model is not currently just looking for
fish, it's looking for particular characteristics
of the boat.
This is suggesting to me that since it's not
all concentrated on the fish, I do think that
there's some data leakage still coming through.
Question: How much do we know about why its
working.
Answer: I think we know everything about why
it's working. We have set up a model where
we've said we want you to predict each of
the 8 fish classes.
We have set it up so that the last layer simply
averages the answers from the previous layer.
The previous layer we have set up so it has
the 8 classes we need -- that's obviously
the only way you can average and get the right
number of classes.
We know that SGD is a general optimization
approach which will find a set of parameters
which will solve the problem you give it.
When you think of it that way, unless it failed
to train (which it could, for all kinds of
reasons), it could only get a decent answer
if it solved it in this way. If it actually
looked at each area and figured out how fish-y
it is.
Question: Could we build some sort of a attention
model for the heatmaps, and if so, would that
help with leakage?
Answer: We're not doing attention models in
this part of the course, per se.
I would say for now the simple attention model
that I would do would be to find the largest
area of the heatmap, crop it and maybe compare
that to the bounding boxes to make sure they
look about the same. Those that don't, you
might want to hand-fix. If you hand-fix them,
you have to give that back to the Kaggle community
of course, because that's hand-labeling.
Honestly, that's the state-of-the-art. In
terms of who wins the money in Kaggle competitions,
that's how the Kaggle winners have won these
type of competitions.
They have two-stages, first they find the
thing of interest and then they zoom into
it and they do a model on that thing.
Actually, the other thing that you might want
to do is to orient the fish so that the head
is in the same place and the tail is in the
same place.
Make it as easy as possible for your ConvNet
to do one of these.
[Time: 1:20 hour mark]
You guys might have heard about another architecture
called Inception. A combination of Inception
plus ResNet won this years ImageNet competition.
Let me give you a very quick hint as to how
it works. I have built the world's tiniest
Inception network here.
One of the reasons I want to show it to you
is that it actually uses the same technique
that we heard from Ben Bowles, remember his
language model used a trick where he had multiple
different convolution filter sizes, ran all
of them and concatenated them together.
That's actually what the Inception network
does.
Question: How would you align the head and
tail?
Answer: To align the head and tail, the easiest
way would be to hand-annotate the head and
hand-annotate the tail. That was what was
done in the whale competition.
Question: How is this a better way to isolate
the fish than just taking the boundary box
approach?
Answer: Hand-labeling always has errors. There
are quite a few people on the forum who pointed
out various bounding boxes that they don't
think are correct.
So it's great to have an automatic approach
which ought to give the same answer as the
hand approach, and you can compare the two
and use the best of both.
In general, this idea of combining human intelligence
and machine intelligence seems to be a great
approach.
Particularly early on. You can do that for
the first few bounding boxes to improve your
bounding box model and then use that to gradually
make the model have to ask you less and less
for your input.
Question: You showed finding the location
of the fish by finding out what kind of fish
it is. What is the purpose of finding the
location if you already found out kind of
fish it is? (for the heatmap)
Answer: For the heatmap you don't need to.
In the heatmap, we're just visualizing one
of layers of the network. It's just a side-effect
of this kind of model is that you can visualize
the last convolutional layer, and in doing
so will give you a heatmap.
Comment: It's nice because a lot of people
refer to neural networks as black boxes without
intermediate interpretability.
Response: There's so many ways of interpreting
neural nets and one of them is to draw pictures
of the intermediate activations. You can also
draw pictures of the intermediate gradients.
There's all kinds of things you can draw pictures
of.
Question: You just showed us a way to build
a model that implicitly defines the bounding
box and does classification all in one model.
Are you saying that people take the bounding
box model, crop it and then run a classifier?
Answer: Yes
The Inception network is going to use this
trick where we're going to use multiple different
convolutional filter sizes
and concatenate them all together.
Just like in ResNet there's this idea of a
block that we repeat again and again. In the
Inception network, there's an inception block
that's repeated again and again.
I've created a version of one here. I have
one thing that takes my input and does a 1x1
convolution. I've got one thing that takes
the input and does a 5x5 convolution. I've
got one thing that takes the input and does
two 3x3 convolutions. I've got one thing that
takes the input and just average pools it.
And then we concatenate them all together.
So what this is doing is each Inception block
is able to look for things at various different
scales and create a single feature map at
the end which adds all of these together.
So once I've defined that I can create a little
model InceptionBlock->InceptionBlock->InceptionBlock->Dropout->Conv2D->GlobalAveragePooling->Output.
[Time: 1:25 hour mark]
I haven't managed to get this to work terribly
well yet. I haven't tried submitting this
to Kaggle to see how it's generalizing.
Part of the purpose of this is to give you
a sense of the kinds of things we're going
to be doing next year. We've built the basic
pieces now of convolutions, fully-connected
layers, activation function, SGD.
From here, deep-learning is putting these
pieces together. What are the ways people
have put these things together to solve problems
as well as possible. The Inception network
is one of these ways.
The other thing I wanted to do was to give
you plenty of things to think about and play
with. Hopefully this notebook is going to
be full of things you can experiment with.
And maybe try submitting some Kaggle results.
The warnings about the Inception network are
a bit like the warnings about the ResNet network.
Like ResNet, the Inception network is available;
Keras has one that you can download and use.
It hasn't been well-studied in terms of its
transfer-learning capabilities. I haven't
seen people winning Kaggle competitions using
transfer-learning of Inception networks. It's
just a little bit less well-studied.
The combination of Inception plus ResNet is
the most recent ImageNet winner.
So if you are looking to start with the most
predictive predictive model, this is where
you want to start.
I wanted to finish off on a very different
note which is looking at RNNs one more time.
I've spent much more time on CNNs than RNNs.
The reason is that this course is much more
about being pragmatic, teaching you the stuff
that works.
In the vast majority of areas where I see
people using deep-learning to solve their
problems, they're using CNNs.
Having said that, some of the most challenging
problems are now being solved with RNNs. Like
speech recognition and language translation.
When you use Google Translate now, you are
using RNNs.
My suspicion is you're going to come across
these problems a lot less often.
I also suspect that in a business context,
a very common type of problem is a time-series
problem. Like looking at a time-series click
events on your website, or e-commerce transactions,
or logistics, or whatever.
These sequence-to-sequence RNNs we've been
looking at which we've been using to create
Nietzschean philosophy are identical to the
ones that you would use to analyze a series
of e-commerce transactions and try to find
anomolies.
I think CNNs are more practically important
for most people in most organizations right
now. RNNs also have a lot of opportunities.
We'll also be looking at them next year when
it comes to looking at attentional models,
which is figuring out in a really big image,
which part should we look at next.
Question: Does Inception have the merge characteristic
that ResNet does?
Answer: The Inception merge is a concat (rather
than an add) which is the same as what we
saw when we looked at Ben Bowles' Quid NLP
model.
We're talking multiple ConvNet convolution
filter sizes and we're sticking them next
to each other, so that feature basically contains
information about 5x5 features and 3x3 features
and 1x1 features. When you add them together,
you lose that specific information.
ResNet does that for a reason, we want to
cause it to learn residuals. In Inception,
we don't want that. In Inception we want to
keep them all in that feature space.
[Time: 1:30 hour mark]
The other reason I wanted to look at RNNs
is that last week we looked at building an
RNN nearly from scratch. I said "nearly from
scratch" because there's one key step which
it did for us, the gradients.
Really understanding how the gradients are
calculated is not something you would ever
have to do by hand, but I think it can be
helpful to your intuition of training neural
networks to be able to trace it through.
For that reason, this is the one time in this
course (in this year's course and next year's
course) where we're really going to go through
and actually calculate the gradients ourselves.
So here is a recurrent neural network in pure
Python.
The reason I'm doning a recurrent neural network
in pure Python is because this is kind of
the hardest. RNNs are the hardest thing to
get your head around back-propograting gradients.
So if you look at this and study this and
step through this over the next couple of
months, you will really get a great understanding
of what a neural net is supposed to be doing.
There will be no magic or mystery because
this thing is going to be every line of code.
It will be something you can see and play
with.
If we're going to do it all ourselves, we
have to write everything ourselves. If we
want a sigmoid function, we have to write
the sigmoid function.
Anytime we write any function, we have to
create its derivative - so here's its derivative.
I'm going to use this approach where underscore-d
( _d ) is the derivative of a function.
So I'm going to have to have relu and the
derivative of relu (relu_d).A
The Eucledian distance, and the derivative
of the Euclidian distance (dist_d).
The cross-entropy, and the derivative of the
cross-entropy (x_entropy_d). Note here that
I am clipping my predictions, because if you
have zeros or ones here, you're going to get
infinities - which destroys everything. This
did actually happen. I didn't have this clipping
at first and I started to get infinities.
Here's my softmax, here's my derivative of
softmax (softmax_d).
So then I go through and I double check that
the answers I get with my versions are the
same as the answers I get with the Theano
versions, and they all seem to be fine.
I am going to use as my activation function
relu, which means the derivative is relu_d.
And my loss function is cross-entropy (x_entropy),
so the loss function is x_entropy_d)
I also have to write my own scan.
Do you guys remember scan? Scan is this thing
where we go through a sequence one step at
a time, calling a function on each element
of the sequence.
Each time the function is going to get two
things - it's going to get the next element
of the sequence as well as the previous result
of the call.
So for example,scan on add two things together
on integers from one to five [ scan(lambda
prev,curr: prev+curr, 0, range((5)) ] is going
to give us the cumulative sum.
One of the reasons we do this is GPUs don't
know how to do loops. Our Theano version uses
scan, and I wanted to make this as close to
Theano as possible.
In Theano, scan is not implemeted like this
with a for loop. In Theano, they use a very
clever approach, creating a tree where it
does a lot of things simultaneously, and gradually
combines them together. Next year we may even
look at how that works, if anybody's interested.
In order to create our Nietzschean philosopy
we need an input and an output. So we have
the 8-character squences one-hot encoded for
our inputs. And the 8-character sequences
moved across by one, one-hot encoded, for
our outputs.
And we've got our vocab size, which is 86
characters.
So here's our input and output shape - 75,000
phrases, each one has 8 characters in, and
each of those 8 characters is a one-hot encoded
vector of size 86.
We first of all need to do the forward pass.
So the forward pass is to scan through all
the characters in the n-th phrase, the input
and output, calling some function.
So here is the forward pass. This is basically
identical as what we saw in Theano. In Theano
we had to lay out the forward pass as well.
To create the hidden state, we had to take
the dot product of x with its weight matrix,
and the dot product of the hidden with its
weight matrix, and then we had to put all
through the activation function.
[Time: 1:35 hour mark]
Then to create the predictions, we had to
take the dot product of the hidden with its
weight matrix, and then put that through softmax.
We have to keep track of all of the state
that it needs, so at the end we will return
the loss: The pre_hidden and the pre_pred,
because we're going to be using them every
time we go through. In the back-prop we'll
be using those
We need to know the hidden state of course,
we have to keep track of that because we're
going to be using it the next time we go through
the RNN. And of course we're going to need
our actual predictions.
So, that's the forward pass - very similar
to Theano.
The backward pass is the bit I wanted to show
you, and I wanted to show you how I think
about it.
This is how I think of it. All of my arrows,
I've reversed their direction. The reason
for that is when we create a derivative, we're
really saying how does a change in the input
impact the output.
To do that, we have to use the chain rule.
We have to go back from the end, all the way
back to the start.
So this is our output last hidden layer activation
matrix. This is our loss, adding together
at each of the characters. If we want the
derivative of the loss with respect to this
hidden activation, we would have to take the
derivative of the loss with this output activation
and multiply it by the derivative of this
output activation with this hidden activation.
You have to then multiply them together, because
that's the chain rule. The chain rule basically
tells you - to go from some function of some
other function of x, the derivative is the
product.
So I find it really helpful to literally draw
the arrows. So let's draw the arrors from
the loss function to each of the outputs as
well.
So to calculate the derivatives, we basically
have to go through and undo each of those
steps. In order to figure out how that input
would change that output, we have to basically
have to undo it. We have to go back along
the arrow in the opposite direction.
So how do we get from the loss to the output?
To do that we need the derivative of the loss
function. And we're also going to need, if
we're going to get back to the activation
function, we're going to need the derivative
of the activation function as well.
So you can see it here. This is a single backward
pass. We grab one of our inputs, one of our
outputs and then we go backwards through each
one, each of the 8 characters, from the end
to the start.
So grab our input character and our ouput
character. The first thing you want is the
derivative of pre_pred. [d_pre_pred = softmax_d(pre_pred).dot(loss_d(ypred,y))
] Remember, pre_pred was the prediction prior
to putting it through the softmax.
So that was the bit I just showed you. It
was the derivative of the softmax times the
derivative of the loss. So the derivative
of the loss is going to get us from here back
to here. And the derivative of the softmax
gets us from here back to the other side of
the activation function.
So we want to keep going further, which is
we want to get back to the other side of the
hidden. We want to get all the way over to
here.
For those of you that haven't done vector
calculus (which I'm sure is many of you),
just take my word for it when I say the derivative
of a matrix multiplication is the multiplication
with the transpose.
In order to take the derivative of the pre_hidden
by its weights, we simply take it by its transpose
of its weights.
[Time: 1:40 hour mark]
Remember, the hidden we actually have two
arrows coming back out of it, and also we've
got two arrows coming in to it. So we're going
to have to add together that derivative and
that derivative.
d_pre_hidden = (np.dot(d_pre_hidden, w_h.T)
+ np.dot(d_pre_pred, w_y.T) * act_d(pre_hidden)
So here is the second part, there it is with
respect to the outputs, and there it is with
respect to the hidden.
And then finally we have to undo the activation
function, so multiply it by the derivative
of the activation function. So that's the
chain rule that gets us all the way back to
here.
So now that we've got those two pieces of
information, we can update our weights.
We can now say for the blue line, what are
these weights now going to equal? We basically
have to take the derivative we got to at this
point (d_pre_pred), we have to multiply it
by our learning rate (alpha).
Then we have to undo the multiplication by
the hidden state to get the derivative with
respect to the weights. I created this little
columnify function (col) to do that -- it's
turning a vector into a column. It's taking
its transpose, if you like. That gives me
my new output weights.
My new hidden weights are basically the same
thing. It's the learning rate times the derivative
we just calculated, and then we have to do
its weights.
Our new input weights are the learning rates
times the pre_hidden times the columnified
version of x.
So I'm going through that very quickly. The
details aren't important, but it might be
fun to look at it. You can see here in this
here are all the steps to do backprop through
an RNN.
Which is also why we would never want to do
this by hand again. Thank god Theano does
this for us. I think it's useful just to see
it though.
Finally I have to create my initial weight
matrices, normally distributed matrices where
the normal distribution is just the square
root of 2 divided by the number of inputs.
For my hidden matrix for a simple RNN, we
will use the identity matrix to initialize
it.
Question: Is state maintained across the samples?
Answer: We haven't gotten to that bit yet.
It all depends on how we use it. At this stage,
all we've gotten to is we've defined the matrices
and we've defined the transitions. Whether
we maintain state will depend entirely on
what we do next, which is the loop.
And so here is our loop. In our loop, we're
going to go through a bunch of examples, run
one forward step, one backwards step and then
from time-to-time, print out how we're getting
along.
In this case, the forward step is passing
to scan the initial state is a whole bunch
of zeros. So currently, this is resetting
the state. It's not doing it statefully.
If you wanted to do it statefully, it would
be pretty easy to change. You would have to
have the final state returned by this and
then feed it back the next time through the
loop.
Having said that, you probably won't get great
results, because remember when you do things
statefully you're much more likely to have
gradients and activations explode, unless
you do a GRU or an LSTM.
So that was a very quick fly-through and more
showing you around the code. If you're interested,
you can check it out.
What I really wanted to get on to was this
more interesting type of RNN -- there's actually
two interesting types of RNN -- called Long
Short-Term Memory and Gated Recurrent Unit.
Many of you will have heard of the one on
the left, LSTM.
[Time: 1:45 hour mark]
Question: Mini-batches?
Answer: For stateful RNNs, you can't exactly
have mini-batches because you're doing one
at a time. And in our case, we were going
through it in order. Using mini-batches is
a great way to parallelize things on the GPU
and make things run faster. We have to be
careful about how we're thinking about state.
LSTMs, a lot of you will have heard about
because they've been very popular over the
last couple years for all kinds of cool stuff
that Google does.
On the right is the GRU, which is simpler
and better than the LSTM. I'm not going to
talk about the LSTM, I'm going to talk about
the GRU.
They're both techniques for building a RNN
where your gradients are much less likely
to explode. Another great example of a clever
architecture, but it's just going to be more
of using the same ideas that we've seen again
and again.
What we have here on the right hand side,
is this box is basically zooming in to what's
going on inside one of these circles in a
GRU.
Normally, in our standard GRU, what's going
on in here is pretty simple. We do a multiplication
by this w_h weight matrix and stick it through
an activation function, grab our input and
do a multiplication by weight matrix to its
activation function and we add the two together.
A GRU is going to do something more complex.
We still have the input coming in and the
output going out (that's what these arrows
are -- they represent new input character
and our prediction).
What's going on the middle is more complex.
We still have our hidden state just like before.
But whereas in a normal RNN, the hidden state
each time simply updates itself; it just goes
through a weight matrix and an activation
fuction and it updates itself.
But in this case, you can see that the loop
looks like its going to come back to itself,
but then there's this gate here (at Z), so
it's actually not just a self-loop ... there's
something more complicated.
In order to understand what's going on, we're
going to have to follow across to the right-hand
side. On the right-hand side, you can see
that the hidden state is going to go through
another gate (at r).
What's a gate? A gate is simply a little mini
neural network which is going to output a
bunch of numbers between 0 and 1, which we're
going to multiply by its input.
In this particular one, the "r" stands for
reset.
The numbers between 0 and 1 ... if they were
all 0, then the thing coming out of the reset
gate would be just a bunch of zeros. In other
words, it would allow this network to forget
the hidden state.
Or it could be a big bunch of 1's, which would
allow the network to remember the hidden state.
Do we want it to remember or forget? We don't
know, which is why we implement this gate
using a little neural network.
This neural network is going to have two inputs:
the input to the GRU unit and the current
hidden state. So it's going to learn a set
of weights so it can decide when to forget.
It's now got the ability to forget what it
knows. That's what the reset gate does.
Assuming that the reset gate has at least
some non-zero entries (which it surely will,
most of the time), then whatever comes through
we're going to call h-tilda (in my code, I
call it h_new).
So this is the new value of the hidden state
after being reset.
So then finally, the original hidden state
goes up to this top bit here, and there's
a gate (z) which decides how much of each
one should we have.
[Time: 1:50 hour mark]
So this gate "z" is an update gate. This gate
is going to decide if it's 1, we'll take more
from this (left) side. If it's 0, we'll take
more from this (right) side.
And again, that's implemented as a little
neural network. I think the easiest way to
understand this is probably to look at the
code. So I have implemented this in Theano.
You can use a GRU in Keras by simply replacing
the words "SimpleRNN" with "GRU". You don't
really need to know this to use it. And you
get pretty good results.
Here's what it looks like when implemented.
We don't just have a hidden weight matrix
and an input weight matrix and an output weight
matrix anymore. We also have a hidden and
input weight matrix for our reset gate neural
net and for our update gate neural net.
So here's the definition of a gate. A gate
is something that takes its inputs, its hidden
state, its hidden state weights, its input
weights and its biases. Then it does a dot
product of the x with W_x, a dot product of
h with W_h and adds the biases.
That's what I meant by a mini neural net.
It's hardly a neural net, it's just got one
layer.
So that's the definition of the reset gate
and the update gate.
In our step function (this is the thing that
runs each time on the scan), it looks exactly
the same as what we looked at last week.
The output equals the hidden state times the
hidden weight matrix plus the hidden biases.
The new hidden state equals our inputs times
its weights and the hidden state times its
weights plus the biases. But this time the
hidden weights are multiplied by the reset
gate. And the reset gate is just our little
neural net.
So now that we have h_new, our actual hidden
state is equal to that times 1 minus the update
gate plus our previous hidden state times
the update gate.
h = update*h + (1 - update)*h_new
You can see that update plus 1 - update will
add to 1, so you can see why it's being drawn
like so, this can be anywhere at either end,
or somewhere in between.
So the update gate decides how much is h_new
going to replace the new hidden state.
So actually although people tend to talk about
LSTMs and GRUs being pretty complex, it really
wasn't much code. It actually wasn't that
hard to write.
The key outcome of this though is because
we now have these reset and update gates is
that it has the ability to learn these special
sets of weights to make sure that it throws
away state when that's a good idea. Or to
ignore state when that's a good idea.
So these extra degrees of freedom allow SGD
to find better answers basically.
And so again, this is one of these things
where coming up with architectures which just
try to make it easier for the optimizer to
come up with good answers.
Everything up to this is identical to what
we looked at last week. We calculated the
scan function, we calculated the loss, we
calculated the gradients, we do the SGD updates.
Really the main reason I wanted to do all
that today was to show you the back prop example.
I know some learning styles are more detail-oriented
as well, so hopefully some of you will have
found that helpful.
Anytime you find yourself wondering how did
this neural network do this, you can come
back to this piece of code ... that's all
it did.
Where you really get successful with neural
nets is when you go to a whole nother level,
and you don't think of it at that level any
more. Instead you start thinking ... if I'm
an optimizer and I'm given an architecture
like this, what would I have to do in order
to optimize it.
[Time: 1:55 hour mark]
Once you start thinking like that, then you
can start thinking in this kind-of-like an
upside-down way that is necessary to come
up with good architectures.
You can start to understand why this convolution
layer, followed by this average pooling layer,
gives the answers that it does.
There's two levels at which you need to think
about neural nets, the sooner you can think
about it at this super high level I feel like
the sooner you'll do well with them.
One of the best ways to do that is over the
next couple of weeks, run this fish notebook
yourself and play around with it a lot.
Make sure you know how to do these things
that I did where I actually create a little
function that allows me to spit out any of
the layers and visualize it. Make sure you
know how to inspect it, really look a the
inputs and outputs. I think that's the best
way to get an intuition.
So this, especially the first half of this
class, was a bit of a preview of next year.
In the first six weeks, you learned all the
pieces.
Then today we very rapidly tried putting those
pieces together in 1000 different ways and
saw what happened. There's a million more
ways that we know of, and probably a billion
more ways we don't know of.
Knowing this little set of tools -- convolutions,
fully connected layers, activation functions,
sgd -- you're now able to be an architect
and create these architectures.
Keras' functional API makes it ridiculously
easy. Today I created all of the architectures
you see today. Today. This week, while I was
sick and my baby wasn't sleeping. My brain
wasn't even working, that's how easy Keras
makes this.
It takes a few weeks to build your comfort
level up, but hopefully you can try that.
Most importantly, over the next few weeks,
as Rachel and I (with some of your help) start
to develop the MOOC, you guys can stay talking
on the forums.
Keep working through whatever problems you're
interested in. Whether it be the problems
you are working on at your organizations,
or your personal passion projects, or if you
want to try and win a competition or two.
Rachel and I are going to still be on the
forums. In a few weeks time, when the MOOC
goes online, hopefully there will be thousands
of people joining this.
I really hope you guys will stay a part of
it and help. Can you imagine that first day,
when half the people think a python is a snake,
and don't know how to connect to an AWS instance.
You'll be able to say, "Read the Wiki, here's
the page, I had that problem too"
Our goal here is to create a new generation
of deep learning practicioners. People who
have useful problems that they're trying to
solve and can use this tool to solve them.
Rather than create more and more exclusive,
heavily mathematical content that's designed
to put people off. That's our hope, that's
why we're doing this.