Rachel added something which I think is super-helpful
to the wiki this week, which is in the section
about the assignments where it talks about
going through the notebooks, there's a section
called "How to Use the Provided Notebooks".
Each time I talk about the teaching approach
in this class, people get a lot out of it,
so I wanted to keep talking about that. As
we discussed before, the 2 hours that we spend
together each week, that's not nearly enough
time for me to teach you deep learning. I
can show you what kinds of things you need
to learn about, and I can show you where to
look and try to give you a sense of some of
the key topics, but then the idea is that
you're going to learn about deep-learning
during the week by doing a whole lot of experimenting.
And one of the places you can do that experimenting
is with the help of the notebooks that we
provided. Having said that, if you do that
by loading up the notebook and hitting shift-enter
a bunch of times to go through each cell until
you get an error message and then you go,
"Oh shit, I've got an error message", you're
not going to learn anything about deep-learning.
I was almost tempted to not put the notebooks
online until the week after each class because
it's just so much better when you can build
it yourself. But the notebooks are really
usefull if you use them really rigorously
and thoughtfully, which is as Rachel's described
here. Read through it and then put it aside.
Minimize it or close it or whatever, and then
try and replicate what you just read from
scratch. And anytime you get stuck you can
go back and open up the notebook, find the
solution to your problem, but don't copy and
paste it. Put the notebook aside again, go
and read the documentation about what it turns
out the solution was. Try and understand why
is this the solution, and type in that solution
yourself from scratch. If you can do that,
it means you really understand now the solution
to this thing you were previously stuck on,
and you've now learned something you didn't
know before.
You might still be stuck. And that's fine.
So if you're still stuck, you can refer back
to the notebook again. Still don't copy and
paste the copy, but whilst having both open
on the screen at the same time, type in the
code. That might seem pretty weird - why would
you type in code you could copy and paste,
but just the very kinesthetic process of typing
it in forces you to think about where are
the parantheses, where are the dots, what's
going on. Then once you've done that, you
can try changing the inputs to that function
and see what happens, see how it affects the
outputs, and really experiment.
Though this process of trying to come up and
think about what step do I take next, that
means you're thinking about the concepts you've
learned, and how do you do that step is having
to recall how the actual libraries are working.
And most importantly, though experimenting
with the inputs and outputs, you get this
really intuitive understanding of what's going
on.
So one of the questions I was thrilled to
see over the weekend, which is exactly the
kind of thing I think is super-helpful, sravya
asked, "Okay I'm trying to understand correlate,
so
I sent it 2 vectors with 2 things each and
I was happy with the result. Then I sent it
2 vectors with 3 things in, and I don't get
it."
So that's great. This is like taking it down
to make sure okay I really understand this.
So I type something in and the output was
not what I expected. What's going on?
And so then I tried it, by creating a little
spreadsheet and showed here are the 3 numbers
and here is how it was calculated. And now
you say, "Okay, I kind of get that, but not
fully.", then another communication, then
you now understand correlation and convolution.
You know you do because you put it in there,
you figured out what the answer ought to be,
and eventually the answer was what you wanted.
That is just great -- this is exactly the
kind of experimentation.
I find a lot of people try to jump straight
to full-scale image recognition before they've
gotten to the 1+1 stage. You'll see I do a
lot of this stuff in Excel. This is why. Simple
little things in Excel, in Python, that's
where you get the most experimental benefit.
So that's what we're talking about when we
talk about experiments.
[Time: 5 minute mark]
I want to show you something pretty interesting.
Remember last week we look at this paper from
Matt Zeigler where we saw what the different
layers of a convolutional neural network look
like. So you guys remember this.
One of the steps in How to Use the Provided
Notebooks is if you don't know why a step
is being done, or how it works, or why the
inputs and outputs are what you observed,
please ask. Anytime you're stuck for half
an hour, please ask.
So far (I believe) there has been a 100% success
rate in answering questions on the forums.
So when people ask, they get an answer.
So part of the homework this week is ask a
question on the forum. It's okay if that question
is about Lesson 1, it could be about anything
at all. I know a lot of people are still working
through Cats and Dogs, or Cats and Dogs Redux.
Different people here have different backgrounds.
There are plenty of people here who have never
used Python before; Python was not a prerequisite.
The goal is for those of you that don't know
Python, that we give you the resources to
learn it, and to learn it well enough to be
effective in deep-learning in it. That does
mean that you guys are going to have to ask
more questions.
There are no dumb questions. So if you see
somebody asking on the forum about, How do
I analyze functional brain MRIs with a 3D
convolutional neural network, that's fine.
That's where they are at. That's okay if you
then ask, What does this Python function do?
Or vice versa. If you see somebody ask, What
does this Python function do, and you want
to talk about 3D brain MRIs, do that too.
The nice thing about the forum is that as
you can see it really is buzzing now. The
nice thing is that the different threads allow
people to dig into the stuff that interests
them. I'll tell you from personal experience,
the thing I learn the most from is answering
the simplest questions. Answering that question
about a 1D convolution, I found very interesting
because I actually didn't realize that the
reflect parameter was the default parameter
and I didn't quite understand how it worked.
And so, answering that question I found very
interesting. And even sometimes if you know
the answer, figuring out how to express it
teaches you a lot.
So asking questions at any level is always
helpful to you and to the rest of the community.
So please, if everybody only does one part
of the assignments this week, do that one.
Just ask a question. Here's some ideas about
questions you could ask, if you're not sure.
Last week we kind of looked at this amazing
visualization of what goes on in a convolutional
neural network. I want to show you something
even cooler, which is the same thing in video.
This is by an amazing guy, Jason Yosinski,
his supervisor (Hod Lipson) and some other
guys. It's doing the same thing, but in video.
And so I'm going to show you what's going
on here.
And you can download this. It's called the
deep-visualization toolbox. So if you go to
google and search for deep-visualization toolbox,
you can do this. You can grab pictures, you
can click on any one of the layers of a convolutional
neural network and it will visualize every
one of the filters, the outputs of the filters
in that convolutional layer. So you can see
here with this dog, it looks like there's
a filter here which is kind of finding edges.
And you could even give it a video stream.
So if you give it a video stream of your own
webcam, you'll see video stream popping up
here.
[Time: 10 minute mark]
So this is a great tool, and looking at this
tool now I hope will give us a better idea
of what's going on in a convolutional neural
network. Look at this one herehe selected.
It's clearly an edge detector. As he slides
a piece of paper over it, you get a very strong
edge. And clearly it's specifically a horizontal
edge detector. And here is actually a visualization
of the pixels of the filter itself. And it's
exactly what you'd expect. Remember from our
initial Lesson 0, an edge detector has black
on one side and white on the other.
So you can scroll through all the different
layers of this neural network. And different
layers do different things. And the deeper
the layer, the larger the area it covers,
and therefore the smaller the actual filter
is, and the more complex objects it can recognize.
So here's an interesting example of a layer
5 thing, which it looks like is a face detetor.
So you can see that as he moves his face around,
this is moving around as well.
One of the coool things you can do with this
is you can say, Show me all the images from
ImageNet that match this filter as much as
possible, and you can see that it's showing
us faces. This is a really cool way to understand
what your neural network is doing, or in this
case, what ImageNet is doing. So you can see,
another guy's come along and here we are.
And so here you can see the actual result
in real time of the filter convolution and
the actual recognition that it's doing.
So clearly the face detector (which also detects
cat faces), the interesting thing about these
types of neural net filters is that they're
often pretty subtle as to how they work. They're
not looking for some pixels, but they really
understand concepts.
So here's a really interesting example. Here's
one of the filters in the 5th layer which
seems to be like an armpit detector. But actually
it's not an armpit detector, because look
what happens if he smooths out his fabric,
it disappears. So what this actually is is
a texture detector. It's something that detects
some kind of regular texture.
Here's an interesting example of one which
clearly is a text detector. ImageNet did not
have a category called, Text. One of the 1000
categories is not text. But one of the 1000
categories is bookshelf. So you cannot find
a bookshelf if you don't know how to find
a book and you can't find a book if you don't
know how to recognize a spine, and the way
to recognize a spine is by finding text.
So this is the cool thing about these neural
networks is that you don't have to tell them
what to find. They decide what they want to
find in order to solve your problem. So I
wanted to start at this end of "Oh my god,
deep-learning is really cool," and then jump
back to the other end of "Deep-learning is
really simple." So everything we just saw
works because of the things that we've learnt
about so far. And I've got a section here
called CNN Review in Lesson 3. And Rachel
and I have started to add some of our favorite
readings about each of these pieces. Everything
you just saw in that video consists of the
following pieces, Matrix Products, Convolutions
(just like we saw in Excel and Python), Activations
(such as ReLUs and SoftMax), Stochastic Gradient
Descent, which is based on BackPropogation,
which we'll learn more about today. And that's
basically it.
One of the challenging things is, even if
you feel comfortable with each of these 5
pieces of a Convolutional Neural Network,
is really understanding how all of those piees
fit together to actually do deep-learning.
So we've got 2 really good resources here
on putting it all together (Stanford CNN Class
and Chapter 6 of Michael Nielson's book).
So I'm going to go through each of these 6
things today, but what I suggest you do if
there's any piece where you feel like "I'm
not confident I really know what a convolution
is," or "I really don't know what an activation
is," see if this information is helpful, and
maybe ask a question on the forum.
So let's go through each of these. I think
a particularly good place to start is maybe
Convolutions. And a good reason to start with
Convolutions is because we haven't really
looked at them since Lesson 0, and that's
quite a while ago.
[Time: 15 minute mark]
So let's remind ourselves about Lesson 0.
So in Lesson 0 we learnt about what a convolution
is by actually running a convolution against
an image. So we used the MNIST dataset. The
MNIST dataset consists of 55,000 28x28 grey-scale
images of handwritten digits. So each one
of these has some known label. Here's 5 examples
with the known label.
So in order to understand what a convolution
is we tried creating a simple little 3x3 matrix.
So the 3x3 matrix we started had -1's at the
top, 1's in the middle and 0's in the bottom.
So we could kind of visualize that. So what
would happen if we took this 3x3 matrix and
we slid it over every 3x3 part of this image
and we multiplied -1 by the first pixel, -1
by the second pixel, -1 by the third pixel.
And then we moved to the next row and multiplied
by 1, by 1, by 1, moved to the bottom row
and multipled by 0, 0, 0 ... and added them
all together. And so we could do that for
every 3x3 area. That's what a convolution
does. So you might remember from Lesson 0,
we looked at a little area to see what this
looks like. So we could zoom in and here's
a small little bit of the "7". One thing that
I think is helpful is just to look at what
is that little bit?
So you can see that an image is just a bunch
of numbers. And lots of 0's and the things
in between, bigger and bigger numbers until
the weights are very close to 1. So what would
happen if we took this little 3x3 area ([0,0,0],[.35,.54,.92],[.98,.99,.99]),
and we multiply each of those 9 things by
each of these 9 things ([-1,-1,-1],[1,1,1],[0,0,0]).
So clearly, anywhere where the first row is
0's and the second row is 1's, this is going
to be very high when we multiply it all together
and add things up. And so given that white
means high, you can see that when we do this
convolution we end up with something where
the top edges become bright. Because we went
[-1,-1,-1] times [1,1,1], times [0,0,0] and
add them all together.
So one of the things we looked at in Lesson
0 (and we have a link to here) is this cool
little "Image Kernels Explained Visually"
site where you can actually create any 3x3
matrix yourself and go through any 3x3 part
of this picture and see the actual arithmetic
and see the result. So if you're not comfortable
with convolutions, this would be a great place
to go next.
Question: How did you decide on the values
in the top matrix?
Answer: Excellent question. So in order to
demonstrate an edge filter, I picked values
based on some well-known edge filter matrices.
You can see here's a bunch of different matrices
that this guy has. For example "top sobel",
that does a top edge filter. Or I could say
"emboss" and you can see it creates this embossing.
Here's a better example, which is nice and
big here.
So these types of filters have been created
over many decades and there's lots and lots
of filters designed to do things. So I just
picked a simple filter, which I knew from
experience would create a top-edge filter.
And so by the same kind of idea, if I rotate
that by 90 degrees (with -1's down the side),
that's going to create a left-edge filter.
[Time: 20 minute mark]
So if I create 4 different types, and I could
also create 4 different diagonal filters like
these, that would allow me to create top-edge,
left-edge, bottom-edge, right-edge, and then
each diagonal edge. So I created these filters
just by hand, through a combination of common-sense
and having read about filters, because people
spend time designing filters.
The more interesting question then really
would be what would be the optimal way to
design filters because it's definitely not
the case that these 8 filters are the best
way of figuring out what's a "7", what's an
"8", and what's a "1".
So this is what deep-learning does. What deep-learning
does is it says, "Let's start with random
filters. Let's not design them, let's start
with totally random numbers for each of our
filters." So we might start with 8 random
filters, each a 3x3. And we then use Stochastic
Gradient Descent to find out what are the
optimal values of each of those sets of 9
numbers. And that's what happens in order
to create that cool video we just saw, and
that cool paper we saw. That's how those different
kinds of image detectors and gradient detectors
and so forth were created. When you use Stochastic
Gradient Descent to optimize these kinds of
values when they start out random. It figures
out that the best way to recognize images
is by creating these kinds of different detectors,
different filters.
Where it gets interesting is when you start
building convolutions on top of convolutions.
We saw last week how, like if you have 3 inputs,
you can create a bunch of weight matrices.
We saw how you could create a random matrix
and then do a matrix multiply of the inputs
times a random matrix. We can then put it
through an activation function, such as max(0,x)
which is called a rectified linear or ReLU
and we could then take that and multiply it
by another weight matrix to create another
output. And then we could put that through
max(0,x), and we could keep doing that to
create arbitrarily complex functions. And
we looked at this really great neural networks
and deep-learning chapter where we saw visually
how that kind of bunch of matrix products
followed by activiation functions can approximate
any given function.
Where it gets interesting then is instead
of just having a bunch of weight matrices
and matrix products, what if sometimes we
had convolutions and activations. Because
a convolution is just a subset of a matrix
product. So if you think about it, a matrix
product says, here's 10 activations and then
a weight matrix going down to 10 activations.
The weight matrix goes through every single
element of the first layer to every single
element of the next layer. So if this goes
from 10 to 10, there are 100 weights. Whereas
a convolution is just creating a subset of
those weights.
So I'll let you think about this during the
week because it's a really interesting insight
to kind of a convolution is identical to a
fully-connected layer, but it's just a subset
of the weights. And so therefore everything
we've learned about stacking linear and non-linear
layers together applies also to convolutions.
But we also know that convolutions are particularly
well-suited to identifying interesting features
of images. By using convolutions, it allows
us to more conveniently and quickly find powerful
deep-learning networks.
[Time: 25 minute mark]
Question: Are the spreadsheets available for
download?
Answer: The spreadsheets will be available
for download tomorrow, hopefully. We're trying
to get to the point that we can actually get
the derivatives to work in the spreadsheet
and we're still slightly stuck in the details.
We'll make something available tomorrow.
Question: Are the filters the layers?
Answer: Yes, they are. This is something where
spending a lot of time looking at simple little
convolution examples is really helpful. For
a fully-connected layer, it's really easy.
If I have 3 inputs, then my matrix product
will have to have 3 rows (otherwise they won't
match) and I can create as many columns as
I like. The number of columns I create tells
me how many activations I create, because
that's what matrix products do.
So it's very easy to see how with what Keras
calls dense layers I can decide how big I
want each activation layer to be. If you think
about it, you can do exactly the same thing
with convolutions. You can decide how many
sets of 3x3 matrices you want to create at
random, and each one will generate a different
output when applied to the image.
So the way that VGG works, for example, the
VGG network (which we learned about in Lesson
1) contains a bunch of layers. It contains
a bunch of convolutional layers followed by
a Flatten. All Flatten does is just a Keras
thing that says don't think about the layers
anymore as being X by Y by channel matrices,
think of them as being a single vector. It
just concatenates all dimensions together,
and then it contains a bunch of fully-connected
blocks. So each of the convolutional blocks
is (you can kind of ignore the zero-padding,
that just adds 0's around the outside so that
your convolutions end up with the same number
of outputs as inputs) contains a 2D convolution
followed by a MaxPooling layer.
And you can see that it starts off with 2
convolutional layers with 64 filters, and
then 2 convolutional layers with 128 filters,
and then 3 convolutional layers with 256 filters.
So you can see what it's doing is it's gradually
creating more and more filters in each layer.
Question: Are these definitions in ConvBlock
specific to VGG?
Answer: Yes, these definitions are specific
to VGG. This is just me refactoring the model
so there wasn't lots and lots of code, I kind
of found that these lines of code were being
repeated so I turned it into a function.
So why would we have the number of filters
be increasing? Well, the best way to understand
a model is to use the summary command. Let's
go back to Lesson 1, let's go right back to
the first thing we learned, which is the 7
lines of code that you can run in order to
create and train a network.
I won't wait for it to actually finish training,
but what I do want to do now is go "vgg.model.summary()".
So any time you're creating models, it's a
really good idea to use the summary command
to look inside them, and it tells you all
about it. So here, we can see that the input
to our model has 3 channels, Red, Green, Blue,
and they are 224x224 images.
After I do my first 2D convolution, I now
have 64 channels of 224x224. So I've replace
my 3 channels with the 64, just like here
I got 8 different filters, here I've got 64
different filters, because that's what I asked
for.
[Time: 30 minute mark]
So again we have the second convolution set
with 224x224 on 64. And then we do MaxPooling.
So MaxPooling (remember from Lesson 0) was
this thing where we simplified things. We
started out with these 28x28 images and we
said let's take each 7x7 block and replace
that entire 7x7 block with a single pixel
which contains the maximum pixel value.
So here is this 7x7 block, which is basically
all grey so we end up with a very low number
here. And so instead of being 28x28 it becomes
4x4 because we are replacing every 7x7 block
with a single pixel. That's all MaxPooling
does. The reason we have MaxPooling is because
it allows us to gradually simplify our image
so that we get larger and larger areas and
smaller and smaller images.
So if we look at VGG after our MaxPooling
layer, we no longer have 224x224, we now have
112x112. Later on, we do another MaxPooling
and we end up with 56x56. Later on we do another
MaxPooling and we end up with 28x28. Each
time we do a MaxPooling we're reducing the
resolution of our image -- it's not really
an image anymore,but of our kind of analyzed
filters.
And so as we're reducing the resolution, we
need to hike up the number of filters otherwise
we're losing information. That's really why
each time we have a MaxPooling, we double
the number of filters. That means that for
every layer, we're keeping the same amount
of information content.
Question: If feature maps are position invariant.
Does it matter whether it sees a pattern in
one part of the picture (for example, top
right), or another part? But I guess it must
not be, because CNNs work so well.
Answer: It starts out with a very important
insight which is a convolution is position
invariant. So in other words, this thing we
created, which is a top edge detector. This
matrix here, which is a top edge detector,
we can apply that to any part of the image
and get top edges from every part of the image.
Earlier on, when we looked at the Jason Yosinski
video, it showed there was a face detector,
which could find a face in any part of an
image.
So this is fundamental to how a convolution
works. A convolution is position-invariant.
It finds a patterns regardless of whereabouts
in the image it is.
Now that is a very powerful idea, because
when we want to say, find a face, we want
to be able to find eyes, and we want to be
able to find eyes regardless of whether the
face is in the top left or the bottom right.
So position-invariance is important.
But also we need to be able to identify position
to some extent because if there's 4 eyes,
or if there's an eye in the top corner and
in the bottom corner, then something weird
is going on. Or if the eyes and the nose are
not in the right positions.
So how does a convolutional neural network
both have this location-invariant filter but
also handle location? And the trick is that
every one of the 3x3 filters cares deeply
about where each of these 3x3 things is. And
so as we go down through the layers of our
model, from 224 to 112 to 56 to 28 to 14 to
7, at each one of these stages. Think about
the stage that goes from 14x14 to 7x7, these
filters are now looking at large parts of
the image. We're now at a point where the
3x3 can say there needs to be an eye here,
an eye here and a nose here.
So this is one of the cool things about convolutional
neural networks, they can find features everywhere
but they can also build things which care
about how features relate to each other positionally,
so you get to do both.
[Time: 35 minute mark]
Question: Do we need zero padding?
Answer: Zero padding is literally something
that's going to stick 0's around the outside
of the image. If you think about what a convolution
does, it's taking a 3x3 and moving it over
the image. If you do that, when you get to
the edge, what do you do? Because at the very
edge, you can't move your 3x3 any further.
Which means that if you only do what's called
a Valid Convolution, which means you always
make sure your 3x3 filter fits entirely within
your image, you end up losing 2 pixels from
the side and 2 pixels from the top each time.
There's actually nothing wrong with that.
A little inelegant. It's kind of nice to be
able to have the size each time and be able
to see what's going on, so people like doing
what's called Same Convolutions so if you
add a black border around the outside, then
the result of your convolution is exactly
the same size as your input. That is literally
the only reason to do it.
In fact, this is a rather inelegant way of
doing zero padding and then convolution. In
fact, there's a parameter to nearly every
library's convolution function where you can
say I want Valid or Full or Half. This means
do you add no black pixels, 1 black pixel
or 2 black pixels. I don't quite know why
this one does it this way. It's really doing
two functions where one would have done, but
it does the job. So there's not right answer
to that question.
Question: Do convolution neural networks work
for cartoons?
Answer: Convolutional neural networks work
fine for cartoons, however, fine-tuning (which
is fundamental to everything we've learned
so far). It's going to be difficult to fine-tune
from an ImageNet model to a cartoon. Because
an ImageNet model, remember all those pictures
of corn we looked at and all those pictures
of dogs we looked at. An ImageNet model has
learned to find the kinds of features that
are in photos of objects that are out there
in the world. And those are very different
kinds of photos from what you see in a cartoon.
So if you want to be able to build a cartoon
neural network, you'll need to either find
somebody else who'se already trained a neural
network for cartoons and fine-tune that, or
you're going to have to create a really big
corpus of cartoons and create your own ImageNet
equivalent.
Question: Why doesn't an ImageNet network
translate to cartoons, given that an eye is
a circle.
Answer: Because the nuance level of a CNN
is very high. It doesn't think of an eye as
being a circle. It knows that an eye is very
specific, it has particular gradients and
particular shapes and a particular way that
the light reflects off of it, so when it sees
a round blob there, it has no ability to abstract
that out and say, oh I guess that's an eye.
One of the big shortcomings of CNNs is that
they can only recognize things that you specifically
give them to recognize. If you feed a neural
net with a wide rane of photos and drawings,
maybe it would learn about that kind of abstraction.
To my knowledge, that's never been done. It
would be a very interesting question. It must
be possible. I'm not sure how many examples
you would need and what kind of architecture
you would use.
[Time: 40 minute mark]
Question: Correlate versus convolution?
Answer: In this particular example I used
correlate, not convolution. So one of the
things we briefly mentioned in Lesson 1 is
that convolve and correlate are exactly the
same thing except that convolve is equal to
correlate of an image with a filter that has
been rotated by 90 degrees.
So you can see convolve images with 90 degrees
filter looks exactly the same and np.allclose
= True. So convolve and correlate are identical,
except that correlate is more intuitive. Correlate
each one goes rows then columns, whereas with
convolve one goes along rows and the other
one goes down columns. I prefer to think about
correlate because it's just more intuitive.
Convolve originally came from physics, I think.
It's also a basic math operation. They're
various reasons that people sometimes find
it more intuitive to think about convolution,
but in terms of everything they can do with
a neural net, it doesn't matter which one
you're using. And in fact, in many libraries
you set a parameter to True or False to decide
whether or not internally it uses correlation
or convolution. And of course, the results
are going to be identical.
So let's go back to our CNN review. So our
network architecture is a bunch of matrix
products, or more generally, linear layers.
And remember a convolution is just a subset
of a matrix product, so it's also a linear
layer. A bunch of matrix products or convolutions
stacked with alternating non-linear activation
functions. And specifically we looked at the
activation function which was the rectified
linear unit, which is just max(0,x). So that's
an incredibly simple activation function,
but it's by far the most common. It works
really really well for the internal parts
of a neural network.
I want to introduce one more activation function
today, and you can read more about it in Lesson
2, in the About Activation Functions section.
And you can see I have all the derivations
and the details of the activation functions
here. I want to talk about one called the
SoftMax function. And SoftMax is defined as
follows, e^x.i divided by the sum of e^x.i.
What is this all about?
SoftMax is used not for the middle layers
of a deep-learning network, but for the last
layer. The last layer of a neural network,
think about what it's trying to do for classification,
it's trying to match to a one-hot encoded
output. Remember a one-hot encoded output
is a vector with all zeros and just a 1 in
one spot.
And we had for Cats and Dogs two spots. The
first one was a 1 if it was a cat, the second
one was a 1 if it was a dog.
So in general, if we're doing classification,
we want our output to have one high number
and all of the other ones low. That's going
to be easier to create this one-hot encoded
output. Furthermore, we would like to be able
to interpret these as probabilites, which
means all of the outputs have to add to 1.
So we've got these 2 requirements here: Our
final layer's activations should add to 1
and one of them should be higher than all
the rest. This particular function does exactly
that and we will look at that by looking (as
usual) at a spreadsheet.
So here is an example of what an output layer
might contain. Here is e to the power of each
of those things to the left. Here is the sum
of e to the power of those things. And here
is the thing to the left, divided by the sum
of them. In other words, SoftMax.
You can see that we start with a bunch of
numbers that all have a similar kind of scale
and we end up with a bunch of numbers that
sum to 1 and one of them is much higher than
the others.
So in general, when we design neural networks,
we want to come up with architectures (by
which I mean convolutions, fully connected
layers, activation functions) where replicating
the output we want is as convenient as possible
[Time: 45 minute mark]
So in this case our activation function for
the last layer makes it pretty convenient,
pretty easy to come up with something that
looks like a one-hot encoded output.
And so the easier it is for our neural net
to create the thing we want, the faster it
is going to get there and the more likely
it is to get there in way that's quite accurate.
So we've learned that any big enough, deep
enough neural network because of the universal
approximation theorem can approximate any
function at all. And we know that stochastic
gradient descent can find the parameters for
any of these, which kind of leaves you thinking,
Why do we need 7 weeks of neural network training.
Like any architecture ought to work.
And indeed that's true. If you have long enough,
any architecture can translate Hungarian into
English, any architecture can recognize Cats
vs Dogs, any architecture can analyze Hillary
Clinton's emails, as long as it's big enough.
However, some of them do it much faster than
others. They train much faster than others.
A bad architectecture could take so long to
train that it doesn't train in the amount
of years you have left in your lifetime.
And that's why you care about things like
convolutional neural networks instead of just
fully connected layers all the way through.
That's why we care about having a SoftMax
as the last layer rather than just a linear
last layer. So we try to make it as convenient
as possible for our network to create the
thing that we want to create.
Question: What is the theoretical justification
for doing SoftMax?
Answer: I don't do theoreticaly justifications,
I do intuitive justifications. There is a
great book for theoretical justifications
and it's available for free. If you just google
for deep-learning book, or go to deeplearningbook.org.
It actually does have a theoretical justification
for why we use SoftMax.
The short version basically is as follows:
SoftMax contains an e-to-the in it. Our log
loss layer contains a log in it. The two nicely
mesh up against each other. And the derivative
of the two together is just (a - b). That's
kind of the short version, but I will refer
you to the deep-learning book for more information
about the theoretical justification.
The intuitive justification is because we
have an e-to-the here, it makes a big number
really really big and therefore once we take
one divided by the sum of the others, we end
up with one number that tends to be bigger
than all the rest, and that is very close
to the one-hot-encoded output that we're trying
to match.
Question: Could a network learn identical
filters?
Answer: A network absolutely could learn identical
filters, but it won't. The reason it won't
is because it's not optimal. Stochastic gradient
descent is an optimization procedure. It will
come up with (if you train it for long enough,
with an appropriate learning rate) the optimal
set of filters. Having the same filter twice
is never optimal. That's redundant. So as
long as you start off with random weights,
then it can learn to find the optimal set
of filters, which will not incude duplicate
filters. These are all fantastic questions.
So in this review, we've done our different
layers, and these different layers get optimized
with SGD. And so last week we learnt about
SGD by using this extremely simple example
where we said let's define a function which
is a line, A*x + B. Let's create some data
that matches the line (that is our X's and
Y's). Let's define a loss function which is
the sum-of-square errors. And let's say we
no longer know what a and b are, so let's
start with some guess.
[Time: 50 minute mark]
And obviously the loss for our guess is pretty
high. And let's now try and come up with a
procedure where each step makes the loss a
little bit better by making A and B a little
bit better. And the way we did that was very
simple.
We calculated the derivative of the loss with
respect to each of A and B. And that means
that the derivative of the loss with respect
to B is, if I increase B by a bit, how does
the loss change? And the derivative of the
loss with respect to A means, as I change
A a bit, how does the loss change? If I know
those 2 things then I know that I should subtract
the derivative times some learning rate, and
as long as our learning rate is low enough,
we know that this is going to make our A guess
a little bit better. And we do the same for
our B guess.
And so we learnt that that is the entirety
of SGD. Run that again and again and again.
And indeed, we set up something that would
run it again and again and again in an animation
loop and we saw that indeed it dows optimize
our line.
The tricky thing for me with deep learning
is jumping from this kind of easy-to-visualize
intuition, if I run this little derivative
on these 2 things a bunch of times it optimizes
this line. I can then create a set of layers
with hundreds of millions of parameters that
in theory can match any possible function,
and it's going to do exactly the same thing.
So this is where our intuition breaks down,
which is this incredibly simple thing called
SGD is capable of creating these incredibly
sophisticated deep-learning models. We really
have to just respect the basics of what's
gong on. We know it's going to work and we
can see it does work.
But even when you've trained dozens of deep-learning
models, it's still surprising that it does
works. It's always a bit shocking when you
start without any ability to analyze some
problem. You start with some random weights,
you start with a general architecture, you
throw some data in, do an SGD, and you end
up with something that works. Hopefully now
it makes sense, you can see why that happens,
but it takes doing it a few times to really
intuitive understand
it really does work.
Question: Can you use SoftMax for multi-class
classification.
Answer: Absolutely yes. In fact, the answer
I showed here was such an example. I showed
that these outputs were for cat, dog, plane,
fish, and building. So this might be what
these 5 things represent. And so this is exactly
showing a SoftMax for a multi-class output.
You just have to make sure that your neural
net has as many outputs as you want. To do
that, you just have to make sure that the
last weight layer in your neural net has as
many columns as you want. The number of columns
in your final weight matrix tells you how
many outputs.
If you want to create somethat that would
find more than one thing, then no, SoftMax
would not be the best way to do that. I'm
not sure if we're going to cover that in this
set of classes. If we don't we'll do it next
year.
Question: Different neural networks, how do
you combine them?
Answer: Let's go back to the question about
3x3 filters, and more generally, how do we
pick an architecture.
So the question of like, the VGG authors used
3x3 filters. The 2012 ImageNet winners used
a combination of 7x7 and 11x11 filters.
[Time: 55 minute mark]
What has happened over the last few years
since then is people have realized that 3x3
fitlers are just better. The original insight
for this was actually that Matt Zeigle visualization
paper I showed you. It's really worth reading
that paper because he really shows by looking
at pictures of all the stuff going on inside
a CNN, it clealy works better when you have
smaller filters and more layers.
I'm not going to go into the theoretical justification
as to why. For the sake of applying CNNs,
all you need to know is there's really no
reason to use anything but 3x3 filters. So
that's a nice simple rule-of-thumb which always
works, 3x3 filters.
Okay, how many layers of 3x3 filters? This
is where there is not any standard agreed-upon
technique. Reading lots of papers, looking
at lots of Kaggle winners, you will over time
get a sense of, for a problem of this level
of complexity, you tend to need this many
filters.
There have been various people that have tried
to simplify this. But we're really still at
the point where the answer is try a few different
architectures and see what works.
The same applies to this question of how many
filters per layer. So in general this idea
of having 3x3 filters with MaxPooling and
doubling the number of filters each time you
do MaxPooling is a pretty good rule-of-thumb.
How many do you start with? You've just kind
of got to experiment. And actually today we're
going to see an example of how that works.
Question: If you had a much larger image,
what would you do?
Answer: If you had a much larger image, what
would you do? For example, on Kaggle there's
a diabetic retinopathy competition which has
pictures of eyeballs which are at quite a
high resolution, a couple thousand by a couple
thousand.
The question of how to deal with large images
is as yet unsolved. So if you actually look
at the winners of that Kaggle competition,
all of the winners resampled that image down
to 512x512. I find that quite depressing.
It's clearly not the right approach.
I'm pretty sure I know what the right approach
is. I'm pretty sure the right approach is
to do what the eye does. The eye does something
call foviation, which means that when I look
directly at something the thing in the middle
is very high-res and very clear and the stuff
on the outside is not.
I think a lot of people now are generally
in agreement with the idea that if we could
come up with an architecture which kind of
has this concept of foviation.
And then secondly we need something (and there
are some good techniques on this already)
called Attentional Models. An Attentional
Model is something that says, Okay the thing
that I'm looking for is not in the middle
of my view, but my low-res peripheral vision
thinks it might be over there, let's focus
my attention over there.
And we're going to start looking at Recurrent
Neural Networks next week. And we can use
Recurrent Neural Networks to build Attentional
Models that allow us to search trough an image
to find areas of interest. That is a very
active area of research, but as of yet is
not really finalized.
By the time this turns into a MOOC and a video,
I wouldn't be surprised if that has been much
better solved. It's moving very quickly.
Question: Didn't the Matt Zeigler paper have
larger filters?
Answer: The Matt Zeigler paper showed larger
filters because he was showing what AlexNet,
the 2012 winner, looked like. And then later
on in the paper he said, based on what it
looks like, here are some suggestions about
how to build better models.
So let us know finalize our review by looking
at fine-tuning. So we learnt how to do fine-tuning
using the little VGG class that I built, which
is like one line of code, vgg.finetune.
We also learnt about kind of conceptually
how could you take 1000 predictions of all
the 1000 ImageNet categories and turn them
into 2 predictions, which is just a Cat or
a Dog by building a simple linear model (from
last week's lesson) that took as input the
1000 ImageNet catgory predictions and took
the true Cat and Dog labels as output and
we just created a linear model of that.
[Time: 1 hour mark]
And so that was this, here is that linear
model. It's got 1000 inputs and 2 outputs.
And to train that linear model, it took less
than a second to train and we got 97.7% accuracy.
So this was actually pretty effective. Why
was it pretty effective to take 1000 predictions
of is it a cat, is it a fish, is it a bird,
is it a poodle, is it a pug, is it a plane
and turn it into is it a cat or is it a dog.
The reason it worked so well is because the
original ImageNet architecture was already
trained to do something very similar to what
we wanted our model to do. We wanted our model
to separate cats from dogs and the ImageNet
model already separated lots of different
types of cats and lots of different types
of dogs, amongst other things as well.
So the thing we were trying to do was just
a subset of what ImageNet already does. So
that was why starting with 1000 predictions
and buiding a simple linear model worked so
well.
This week you're going to be looking at the
State Farm Competiton, and in the State Farm
Competion you're going to be looking at pictures
like this one and this one and his one. And
your job will not be whether or not to decide
if it's a person or a dog or a cat, your job
will be to decide is this person driving in
a distracted way or not. That is not something
that the original ImageNet categories included.
And therefore this same technique is not going
to work.
So what do you do if you need to go further?
What do you do if you need to predict something
which is very different from what the original
model did? The answer is to throw away some
of the later layers in the model and retrain
them from scratch, that's called fine-tuning.
And so that is pretty simple to do.
So if we just want to fine-tune the last layer,
we can just go model.pop (that removes the
last layer), we can then say make all of the
other layers non-trainable (so that means
it won't update those weights) and then add
a new fully-connected dense layer at the end
with just our Dog and Cat (our 2 activations)
and then go ahead and fit that model.
So that is the simplest kind of fine-tuning.
Remove the last layer (previously the last
layer was going to predict 1000 categories)
and replace it with a new last layer which
we train.
In this case, I've only run it through 2 epochs,
so I'm not getting a great result. But if
we ran it for a few more we would get a bit
better than the 97.7 we had last time. When
we look at State Farm, it's going to be critical
to do something like this.
So how many layers would remove? You don't
just have to remove 1. If you go back to your
Lesson 2 notebook, you'll see after this I've
got a section called Retraining More Layers,
and in it we can see that we can take any
model and we can say let's grab all layers
up to the n-th layer (in this case we said
all the layers after the first fully connected
layer) and set them all to trainable. What
would happen if we tried running that model?
So with Keras, we can tell Keras which layers
do we want to freeze (and leave them at their
ImageNet decided weights) and which layers
do we want to retrain based on the things
we're interested in.
In general, the more different your problem
is from the 1000 ImageNet categories, the
more layers you're going to have to retrain.
[Time: 1.05 hour mark]
Question: How do you decide how far to go
back in the layrs?
Answer: Two ways.
Way #1 = intuition. Have a look at something
like those Matt Zeigler visualizations to
get a sense of at what semantic level is each
of those layers operating at, and go back
to the point where you feel like that level
of meaning is going to be relevant to your
model.
Method #2 = experiment. It doesn't take that
long to train another model starting at a
different point. So I generally do a bit of
both. When I know that Dogs and Cats are subsets
of the ImageNet categories, I'm not going
to bother generally training more than 1 replacement
layer.
For State Farm, I really had no idea. I was
pretty sure that I wouldn't have to retrain
any of the convolutional layers because the
convolutional layers are all about spatial
relationships and therefore a convolutional
layer is all about recognizing how things
in space relate to each other. I was pretty
confident that figuring out that figureing
out whether somebody is looking at a mobile
phone or playing with their phone is not going
to use different spatial features. So for
State Farm I only looked at retraining the
dense layers.
In VGG, there are actually only 3 dense layers
and 2 intermediate layers and the output layer,
so I just trained all 3. Generally speaking,
the answer to this is try a few things and
see what works.
Question: Are you setting the weights randomly
when you retrain the layers?
Answer: When we retrain the layers we do not
set the weights randomly. We start the weights
at their optimal ImageNet levels and so that
means that if you retrain more layers than
you really need to, it's not a big problem
because the weights are already at the right
point.
If you randomized the weights of the layers
that you're retraining, that would actually
kill the earlier layers as well if you made
them trainable. There's no point setting them
to random most of the time, we'll be learning
a bit more about that after the break.
So far, we have not reset the weights. When
we say layer.trainable=True we're just telling
Keras that when you say fit, I actually want
you to use SGD to update the weights on that
layer.
So that's been a lot of review but I think
it's very useful. When we come back, we're
going to be talking about how to go beyond
these basic 5 pieces to ceate models which
are more accurate. Specifically we are going
to look at avoiding underfitting and avoiding
overfitting.
Next week, we're going to be doing half a
class on review of covolutional neural networks
and half a class an introduction to recurrent
neural networks, which we'll be using for
language.
So hopefully by the end of this class you'll
be feeling ready to really dig deep into CNNs
during the week. And this is really the right
time this week to make sure you're asking
questions you have about CNNs, because next
week we'll be wrapping up this topic.
So we have a lot to cover in our next 55 minutes.
I think actually this approach of doing the
new material quickly and then you can review
it in the lesson notebook, on the video, and
by experimenting during the week, and then
reviewing the next week is fine. I think that's
a good approach.
I just wanted to make you aware that the new
material over the next 55 minutes wil move
pretty quickly. Don't worry too much if not
everything sinks in straight-away. If you
have any questions, please do ask. But also
recognize that it's really going to sink in
as you study it, play with it during the week.
Then next week we're going to review all of
this. So if it's still not making sense, then
of course ask your questions on the forum.
If it's still not making sense, we'll be reviewing
it next week.
[Time: 1.10 hour mark]
Question: If you don't retrain a layer, does
that mean the layer "remembers"? Is that what
gets saved?
Answer: Yes, if you don't retrain a layer
when you save the weights, it's going to contain
the weights that it originally had.
Question: Why would we want to start out by
overfitting?
Answer: We're going to talk about that next.
Question: Am I correct in understandingt that
the last conv layer of VGG is a 7x7x output,
so 49 "boxes" over the original image, and
each one has 512 different things it could
recognize in each box?
Answer: That's kind of right. But it's not
like it recognizes 512 different things. When
you have a convolution on a convolution on
a convolution, you have a very rich function
with hundreds of thousands of parameters.
So it's not like it's recognizing 512 things,
it's that there are 512 rich complex functions.
So those rich complex functions can recognize
rich complex concepts. So for example, we
saw in a video that even in Layer 6 there's
a face detector which can recognize cat faces
as well as human faces.
So the later on we get in these neural networks,
the harder it is to even say what's being
found, because they get more and more sophisticated
and complex. So what those 512 things do in
the last layer of VGG, I'm not sure that anybody's
gotten to the point that they can tell you
that.
Comment: Deeper layers are getting to see
more of the original image.
So a deeper layer, because it's a 7x7 output
is seeing 1/7th of the X and 1/7th of the
Y, so it's going to see more and more.
The next section is all about making our model
better. At this point, we have a model with
an accuracy of 97.7%. How do we make it better?
Because we have started with an existing VGG
model, there are 2 reasons that you could
be less good than you want to be. Either you're
underfitting or you're overfitting.
Underfitting means that, for example, you're
using a linear model to try to do imagery.
You're using a model that is not complex and
powerful enough for the thing you're doing.
Or it doesn't have enough parameters for the
thing you're doing. That's what underfitting
is.
Overfitting means that you're using a model
with too many parameters that you've trained
for too long without correctly using the techniques
that we're about to learn about such that
you end up learning what your specific training
pictures look like rather than what the general
patterns in them look like. You'll recognize
overfitting if your training set has a much
higher accuracy than your test set and validation
set. So that means you've learnt how to recognize
the contents of your training set too well.
And so then when you look at your validation
set you get a less good result. So that's
overfitting.
I'm not going to go into detail on this because
any of you who have done any machine learning
have seen this before. So any of you who haven't,
please look up overfitting on the Internet,
learn about it, ask questions about it. This
is perhaps the single most important concept
in machine learning. So it's not that we're
not covering it because it's not interesting,
we're not covering it because I know a lot
of you are already familiar with it.
Underfitting we can see in the same way, but
opposite, if our training error is much lower
than our validation error, then we're underfitting.
So I'm going to look at this now because you
might have noticed that in all of our models
so far, our trainnig error has been lower
than our validation error, which means we
have been underfitting.
So how is this possible?
[Time: 1.15 minute mark]
And the answer to how this is possible is
because the VGG network includes something
called Dropout. Specifically Dropout with
a p of .5.
What does Dropout mean? It means that at this
layer (which happens at the end of every fully-connected
block), it deletes 0.5 (50%) of the activations
at random. It sets them to 0. That's what
a dropout layer does. It sets to 0 half (.5)
of the activations at random.
Why would it do that? Because when you randomly
throw away bits of the network, it means that
the network can't learn to overfit. It can't
learn to build a network that just learns
about your images, because as soon as it does,
you throw away half of it. And suddenly, it's
not working anymore.
So dropout is a fairly recent development
(about 3 years old?) and it's perhaps the
most important development over the last few
years because it's the thing that now means
we can train big complex models for long periods
of time without overfitting. Incredibly important.
But in this case, it seems that we are using
too much dropout. So the VGG network, which
used a dropout of .5, they decided they needed
that much in order to avoid overfitting ImageNet.
But it seems for our Cats and Dogs, it seems
that it's underfitting. So what do we do?
The answer is, Let's try removing dropout.
So how do we removed dropout? This is where
it gets fun.
We can start with our VGG fine-tuned model.
I've actually created a little function called
vgg_ft, which creates a VGG fine-tuned model
with 2 outputs. It looks exactly like we would
expect it to look. It creates a VGG model,
it fine-tunes it, it returns it.
What does ft (fine-tune) do? It does exactly
what we've learnt. It pops off the last layer,
sets all the rest of the layers to nontrainable
(layer.trainable=False) and adds a new Dense
layer. I just created a little thing that
does that.
Every time I start writing the same code more
than once, I stick it into a function so I
can use it again in the future. It's good
practice.
I then load the weights that I just saved
in my last model, so I don't have to retrain
it. So saving and loading weights is a really
helpful way of avoiding not refitting things.
So already I now have a model that fits Cats
and Dogs with 97.7% accuracy.
We can grab all the layers of the model and
we can ennumerate through them and we can
find the last one
that is a convolution. So at this point we
now have the index of the last convolutional
layer (30). So we can now grab that last convolutional
layer.
And so what we want to try doing is removing
drop-out from all the rest of the layers.
So after the convolutional layers are the
Dense layers. This is really kind of important
concept in the Keras library, playing around
with layers.
So spend some time looking at this code, really
look at the inputs and the outputs and get
a sense of it. So you can see here, here are
all the layers up to the last convolutional
layer. Here are all the layers from the last
convolutional layer. So all the fully connected
layers and all the convolutional layers.
I can create a whole new model that contains
just the convolutional layers. Why would I
do that? Because if I'm going to remove dropout,
then clearly I'm going to want to fine-tune
all of the layers that involve dropout, that
is all of the dense layers.
[Time: 1.20 hour mark]
I don't need to fine-tune any of the convolutional
layers because none of the covolutional layers
have dropout. Look at the ConvBlock. The ConvBlock
does not have dropout.
So I'm going to save myself some time. I'm
going to pre-calculate the output of the last
convolutional layer. You see this model I
have here, this model that contains all the
convolutional layers, if I pre-calculate the
output of that, then that's the input to the
Dense layers that I want to train.
So you can see what I do here is a say conv_model.predict
with my validation batches, conv_model.predict
with my batches and that now gives me the
output of the convolutional layer for my training
and the output of it for my validation. And
because that's something I don't want to do
over and over again, I save it.
So here I just go load_array and that's going
to load from the disk the output of that.
And I'm going to say trn_features.shape (this
is always the first thing you want to do when
you build something) is look at its shape.
Indeed it is what we would expect, 23,000
images, each one is 14x14 (because I didn't
include the final MaxPooling layer) with 512
filters. Indeed if we go model.summary, we
should find the last convolutional layer,
512 filters, 14x14 dimension.
So we have basically built a model that is
just a subset of VGG containing all of these
earlier layers. We've run it through our test
sets and our validation sets and we've got
the outputs. So that's the stuff that we want
to fix, and we don't want to recalculate that
every time. So now we create a new model that
is exactly the same as the dense part of VGG
but we replace the Dropout "p" with 0.
So here's something pretty interesting, and
I'm going to let you think about this during
the week. How do you take the previous weights
from VGG and put them into this model where
Dropout is 0? If you think about it, before
we had Dropout at .5, so half the activations
were being deleted at random. So since half
the activations were being deleted at random,
now that I've removed Dropout, I effectively
have twice as many weights active. Since I
have twice as many weights being active, I
need to take my ImageNet weights and divide
them by 2.
By taking my ImageNet weights and copying
them across to my new model but each time
divide them by 2, that means my new model
is going to be exactly as accurate as my old
model before I start training, but it has
no Dropout.
Question: Is it
wasteful to have in the Cats and Dogs model
filters that have been learnt to find things
like bookshelves?
Answer: Potentially it is, but it's okay to
be wasteful. The only place that it's a problem
is if we're overfitting. And if we're overfitting,
we can easily fix that by adding more Dropout.
So let's try this. We now have a model which
takes the output of the convolutional layers
as input, gives us our Cats vs Dogs as output
and has no Dropout. So now we could just go
ahead and fit it. Notice that the input to
this is my 512 by 14 by 14, my outputs are
my Cats and Dogs (as usual). Train it for
a few epochs, and here's something really
interesting, dense layers take very little
time to compute. A convolutional layer takes
a long time. If you think about it, you're
computing 512 3x3x512 filters for each of
14x14 spots. That is a lot of computation.
[Time: 1.25 hour mark]
So in a deep-learning network, your convolutional
layers is where all of your computation is
being taken up. Look, when I train my dense
layers, it is only taking 17 seconds. Super
fast.
On the other hand, the dense layers is where
all of your memory is taken up. Between this
4096 layer and this 4096 layer, there are
4000x4000=16,000,000 weights. And between
the previous layer, which was (after MaxPooling)
512x7x7=25088, there's 25088 x 4096 weights.
So this is a really important rule-of-thumb:
Your dense layers is where your memory is
taken up, and your convolutional layers is
where your computation time is taken up.
So it took me a minute or so to run 8 epochs.
That's really fast. Holy shit, look at that,
98.5%.
So you can see now I am overfitting. But even
though I'm overfitting, I'm doing pretty damn
well. Overfitting is only bad if you're doing
it so much that your accuracy is bad. So in
this case it looks like actually this amount
of overfitting is pretty good.
For Cats and Dogs, this is about as good as
I could have gotten. If I had stopped a little
earlier, you can see that it was really good
(98.7%). The winner was 98.8, and here I've
got 98.75. And there's some tricks I'll show
you later that always give you an extra 50%
accuracy, so this would definitely have won
Cats and Dogs, if we had used this model.
Question: Can you perform Dropout on a convolutional
layer?
Answer: You can definitely perform Dropout
on a convolutional layer. Indeed nowadays,
people normally do.
I don't quite remember the VGG days, I guess
that was 2 years ago, maybe people in those
days didn't.
Nowadays the general approach would be a Dropout
of .1 for your first layer, Dropout of .2
before this one, .3, .4, and then finally
a Dropout of .5 before your fully-connected
layers. That's kind of the standard.
If you then find that you're find that you're
underfitting or overfitting you can modify
all of those probabilities by the same amount.
But generally speaking, if you drop out in
an early layer, you're losing that information
for all of the future layers. So you don't
want to drop out too much in the early layers.
You can feel better dropping out more in the
later layers.
Question: How do you know how to tune dropout?
How do you determine if you're overfitting
or underfitting?
Answer: Tuning your dropout is very much black
magic.
This is how you manually determine whether
you're overfit or underfit. Another way to
do it would be to modify your architecture
to have less or more fitlers. But that's actually
pretty difficult to do.
Question: So is the point that we didn't need
Dropout anyway?
Answer: Perhaps it was. But VGG comes with
Dropout. So when you're fine-tuning you start
with what you start with.
We are overfitting here. So my hypothesis
is maybe we should try a little less Dropout.
But before we do, I'm going to show you some
better tricks.
And the first trick I'm going to show you
is a trick that lets you avoid overfitting
without deleting information. Dropout deletes
information, so we don't want to do it unless
we have to.
Here is a list, you guys should refer to it
every time you're building a model that is
overfitting.
Five steps:
Step 1: Add more data. This is a Kaggle competition,
so we can't do that.
Step 2: Use data augmentation, which we're
about to learn.
Step 3: Use more generalizable architectures.
We're going to learn that after this.
Step 4: Add regularization. That generally
means Dropout. There's another type of regularization
which is where you basically add up the value
of all of your weights and then multiply it
by some small number and you add that to the
loss function. Basically you say having higher
weights is bad. And that's called either L2
Regularization (if you take the square of
your weights and add them up. Or L1 Regularization,
if you take the absolute value of your weights
and add them up.
Keras supports that as well, also popular.
I don't think anyone has a great sense of
when do you use L1 and L2 Regularization and
when do you use Dropout. I use Dropout pretty
much all the time and I don't particularly
see why anyone would need both. I just wanted
to let you know that that other type of Regularization
exists.
[Time: 1.30 hour mark]
And then lastly, if you really have to reduce
architecture complexity (Step 5), remove some
filters. But that's pretty hard to do if you're
fine-tuning. Because how do you know which
filters to remove?
Now that we have Dropout, the first 4 are
what we do in practice.
Question: Is this like in Random Forest when
we randomly select some features?
Answer: Like in Random Forest, when we randomly
select subsets of variables at each point,
that's kind of what Dropout is doing. Dropout
is randomly throwing away half the activations.
So Dropout and Random Forest both effectively
create large ensembles. So it's actually a
fantastic kind of analogy.
Just like when we went from decision trees
to random forests, it's this huge step which
is basically create lots of decision trees
with some random differences. Dropout is automatically
creating lots of neural networks with different
subsets of features that have been randomly
selected.
Data augmentation is very, very simple. Data
augmentation is something which takes a cat
and turns it into lots of cats. That's it.
Actually it does it for dogs as well. You
can rotate, you can flip, you can move up
and down, left and right, zoom in and out.
In Keras, you do it by adding options to ImageDataGenerator.
What we always said before was image.ImageDataGenerator().
Now we say all these other things, like image.ImageDataGenerator(rotation_range=20,
width_shift_range=0.1, height_sifht_range=0.1,
shear_range=0.05, zoom_range=0.1, horizontal_flip=True,
dim_ordering='tf'). Flip it horizontally at
random, zoom in a bit at random, shear at
random, rotate at random, move it left and
right at random and move it up and down at
random.
Once you've done that, when you create your
batches, rather than doing it the way we did
it before, you simply add that to your batches.
So we said okay this is our data generator,
so when we create our batches, use that data
generator, the augmenting data generator.
It is very important to notice the validation
set does not include that. Because the validation
set is the validation set, that's the thing
we want to check against, so we shouldn't
be fiddling with that at all.
So the validation set has no data augmentation
and no shuffling. It's constant and fixed.
The training set on the other hand, we want
to move it around as much as we can. So shuffle
it's order, and add all these different types
of augmentation.
How much augmentation to use? This is one
of the things that Rachel and I would love
to automate.
For now, two methods. Use your intition, and
the best way to use your intuition is to take
one of your images, add some augmentation
and check whether they still look like cats.
So if it's like so warped that nobody takes
a photo of a cat like that, you've done it
wrong. This is kind of like a small amount
of data augmentation. Method two, experiment.
Try a range of different augmentations and
see which one gives you the best results.
So here, if we add some augmentation, everything
else is exactly the same, except we can't
precompute anything anymore. So earlier on
we precomputed the output of the last convolutional
layer. We can't do that now because every
time this cat approaches our neural network,
it's a little bit different. It's rotated
a bit, it's flipped, it's moved around, it's
zoomed in and out.
So unfortunately when we use data augmentation,
we can't precompute anything and so things
take longer. Everything else is the same though.
We grabbed our fuly-connected model, we add
it to the end of our convolutional model (and
this is the one without dropout), compile
it, fit it, and now run. Rather than taking
9 seconds per epoch, it takes 273 seconds
per epoch because it has to calculate through
all the convolutional layers, because of the
data augmentation.
So in terms of results here, we have not managed
to get back up to that 98.7 accuracy. If I
keep running them, again it's not over-fitting.
It's a little hard to tell because the validation
accuracy is moving around quite a lot (because
my validation set is a little on the small
side), it's a little hard to tell whether
this data augmentation is helping or hindering.
[Time: 1.35 hour mark]
I suspect that what we're finding here is
that maybe we're doing a little bit too much
data augmentation, so if I went back and reduced
my different ranges by half, I might get a
better result than this. But really this is
something to experiment with and I have better
things to do than experiment with this, but
you get the idea.
So data augmentation is something you should
always do. Like there's never a reason not
to use data augmentation. The question is
just what kind and how much.
So for example, what kind. Should you flip
X and Y? Clearly for Dogs and Cats, no. You
pretty much never see a picture of an upside-down
dog. So would you do vertical flipping in
this particular problem? No, you wouldn't.
Would you do rotations? Yes, you very often
see cats and dogs that are kind of on their
hind legs, or the photo is taken a bit uneven
or whatever.
You certainly would have zooming. Sometimes
you're close to the dog, sometimes you're
further away.
So use your intuition to think about what
kind of augmentation to use.
Question: Could you use data augmentation
with color?
Answer: Data augmentation with color, that's
an excellent point. Something I didn't add
to this but probably should have is that there's
a channel augmentation parameter for data
generating in Keras and that will slightly
change the colors. And indeed, that's a great
idea for natural images like these because
you have different white balance, you have
different lighting and so forth. I think that
would be a great idea.
So I hope during the week that people will
take this notebook and somebody will tell
me what is the best result they've got. I
bet that that data augmentation will include
some fiddling around with colors.
Question: Would
changing it to black and white help?
Answer: No it wouldn't because the Kaggle
competition test set is in color. So if you're
throwing away color, you're throwing away
information. The Kaggle competition is saying,
Is this a Cat or is this a Dog?, and part
of seeing whether it's a cat or a dog is seeing
what color it is. So if you're throwing away
the color, you're making that harder. So you
could run it on the test set and get answers,
but they're going to be less accurate because
you've thrown away information.
Question: How is it working to remove the
flattened layer?
Answer: What happened to the flattened layer
is that is was there. Oh, okay, gosh, I forgot
to add it back to this one. So I actually
changed my mind about whether to include the
flattened layer, and where to put it, where
to put MaxPooling. It'll come back later.
This is a slightly old version. That you for
picking it up.
Question: Can you perform DropOut on the raw
images by randomly blanking out pieces?
Answer: Can you do Dropout on the raw images,
the simple answer is yes you could. There's
no reason I can't put a DropOut layer right
here, and that's going to drop out pixels.
It turns out that's not a good idea. Throwing
away input information is very different from
throwing away model information.
Throwing away model information is letting
you effectively avoid overfitting the model.
You don't want to avoid overfitting the data,
so you probably don't
want to do that.
To clarify, the augmentation is at random.
I just showed you 8 examples of the augmentation.
So what the augmentation does is it says at
random, rotate by up to 20 degrees, move up
to 10% in each direction, shear by up to 5%,
zoom by 10% and flip at random half the time.
So then I just said here are 8 cats. So what
happens is every time an image goes into the
batch, it gets randomized. So effectively
it's an infinite number of augmented images.
Okay, the final concept to learn about today
is Batch Normalization.
[Time: 1.40 hour mark]
Batch normalization, like data augmentation
is something you should always do. Why doesn't
VGG do it? Because it didn't exist then. BatchNorm
is about 1 year old, maybe 18 months old.
Here's the basic idea. Anybody who's kind
of done any machine learning probably knows
that one of the first things you want to do
is take your input data, subtract it's mean
and divide by the standard deviation.
Why is that? Imagine we had like, 40 and -30
and 1. You can see that the outputs are all
over the place. Some of the intermediate values
are really big, some are really small. So
if we changed a weight which impacted x1,
it's going to change the loss function by
a lot. Whereas if we change a weight which
impacts x3, it will change the loss function
very little.
So the different weights have very different
gradients basically, very different amounts
that are going to affect the outcome.
Furthermore, as you go down further down through
the model, that's going to multiply. And particularly
when we're using SoftMax, which has an e to
the power in it, you end up with these crazy
big numbers. So when you have inputs that
are of very different scales, it makes the
whole model very fragile. Which means it is
harder to learn the best set of weights and
you have to use smaller learning rates.
This is not just true of deep-learning, it's
true of pretty much every kind of machine
learning model, which is why everybody who's
been through the MSAN program here, hopefully
you guys all learn to normalize your inputs.
So if you haven't done any machine learning
before, no problem. Just take my word for
it, you always want to normalize your inputs.
It's so common that pretty much all of the
deep-learning libraries will normalize your
inputs for you with a single parameter. Indeed,
we're doing it in ours because images like
pixel values only range from 0 to 255, you
don't generally worry about dividing by the
standard deviation with images, but you do
generally worry about subtracting the mean.
So you'll see that the first thing our model
does is this thing called preprocess, which
subtracts the mean. And the mean was something
basically you can look up on the Internet
and find out what the mean of ImageNet data
is, these 3 fixed values.
Now, what does that have to do with BatchNorm?
Imagine somewhere along the line in our training
we ended up with like one really big weight.
Then suddenly, one of our layers is going
to have one really big number. And now, we're
going to have exactly the same problem as
we had before, which is the whole model becomes
very unresiliant, very fragile. It becomes
very hard to train. It's going to be all over
the place. Some numbers could even get slightly
out of control.
So what do we do? Really what we want to do
is to normalize not just our inputs, but our
activations as well. So you may think, okay,
no problem. Let's just subtract the mean and
divide by the standard deviation by each of
our activation layers.
Unfortunately that doesn't work. SGD is very
bloody minded. If it wants to increase one
of the weights higher and you try to undo
it by subtracting the mean and dividing by
the standard deviation, the next iteration
is going to try and make it higher again.
So if SGD decides that it wants to make your
weights of very different scales, it will
do so. Just normalizing the activation layers
doesn't work.
So BatchNorm is a really neat trick for avoiding
that problem. Before I tell you the trick,
I will just tell you why you want to use it.
A) Because it is about 10X faster than not
using it, particularly because it often lets
you use a 10X higher learning rate, and
B) Because it reduces overfitting without
removing any information from the model.
So these are two things you want, less overfitting
and faster models.
I'm not going to go into detail about how
it works (you can read about it during the
week if you're interested), but brief outline:
First step it normalizes the intermediate
layers just the same way as input layers can
be normalized (the thing I just told you wouldn't
work). It does it, but it does something else
critical, which is it adds 2 more trainable
parameters. One trainable parameter multiplies
by all the activations and the other one is
added to all the activations.
[Time: 1.45 hour mark]
So that is able to undo that normalization.
Both of those two things are then incorporated
into the calculation of the gradient so the
model now knows that it can rescale all of
the weights if it wants to without moving
one of the weights way off into the distance.
And so it turns out that this does actually
effectively control the weights in a really
effective way. So that's what batch normalization
is.
The good news is for you to use it, you just
type batchnormalization(). You can put it
after Dense layers, you can put it after convolutional
layers, you should put it after all of your
layers.
Here's the bad news. VGG didn't train originally
with batchnormalization and adding batchnormalization
changes all of the weights. I think that there
is a way to calculate a new set of weights
with batchnormalization. I haven't gone through
that process yet.
So what I did today was I actually grabbed
the entirety of ImageNet and I trained this
model on all of ImageNet. And that then gave
me a model which was basically VGG plus batchnormalization,
and so that is the model here that I'm loading.
So this is the ImageNet Large Visual Recognition
Competion 2012 dataset. And so I trained this
set of weights on the entirety of ImageNet
so that I created basically a VGG plus batchnorm.
And so then I fine-tuned the VGG plus batchnorm
model by popping off the end and adding a
new Dense layer, and then I trained it. These
only took 6 seconds because I precalculated
the inputs to this. Then I added data augmentation
and I started training that, and then I ran
out of time because it was class. So I think
this was on the right track. I think if I
had had another hour or so ....
You guys can play with this during the week
because this is like all the pieces together.
It's batchnorm, and data augmentation and
as much dropout as you want.
So you'll see what I've got here is I have
Dropout layers with an arbitrary amount of
dropout. The way I set it up, you can go ahead
and say, Create batchnorm layers with whatever
amount of dropout you want. And then later
on you can say I want you to change the weights
to use this new amount of dropout.
So this is kindo of like the ultimate ImageNet
fine-tuning experience. I haven't seen anybody
create this before, so this is a useful tool
that didn't exist until today. Hopefully during
the week we'll keep improving it.
Interestingly, I found that when I went back
to even .5 dropout, it was still massively
overfitting. So it seems that batchnormalization
allows the model to be so much better at finding
the optimum, that I actually needed more dropout,
rather than less.
As I said, this is all kind of something I
was doing today, so I haven't quite finalized
that.
What I will show you is something I did finalize
(which I did on Sunday), which is going through
end-to-end an entire model building process
on NMIST.
And so I want to show you this entire process
and you guys can play with it.
MNIST is a great way to really experiment
with and revise everything you know about
CNNs, because it's very fast to train (because
they're only 28x28 images) and there's also
extensive benchmarks on what are the best
approaches to MNIST.
So it's very very easy to get started with
MNIST because Keras actually contains a copy
of MNIST. We can just go "from keras.datasets
import mnist" and "mnist.load_data()" and
we're done.
Now MNIST are greyscale images and everything
in Keras, in terms of convolution stuff, expects
there to be a number of channels, so we have
to use expand_dims to add this empty dimension.
So this is 60,000 28x28 images with one color.
[Time: 1.50 hour mark]
So if you try to use greyscale images and
get weird errors, I'm pretty sure this is
what you've forgotten to do, which is to add
this empty dimension. You actually have to
tell it, there is 1 channel. Otherwise it
doesn't know how many channels there are.
So there is 1 channel.
The other thing I had to do was take the Y
values, the labels, and one-hot encode them,
because otherwise they were like this, they
were actual numbers (5,0,4,1,9) and we need
to one-hot encode them, because remember this
is the thing that that SoftMax function is
trying to approximate, that's like how linear
algebra works.
So there are the two things I had to do to
preprocess this, add the extra dimension and
do my one-hot encoding.
Then I normalize the input by subtracting
the mean and dividing by the standard deviation
and then I try to build a linear model.
So I can't fine-tune from ImageNet now because
ImageNet is 224x224 and this is 28x28. And
ImageNet is full color, and this is greyscale.
So we're going to start from scratch. All
of these are going to start from random.
So a linear model needs to normalize the input,
it needs to flatten it, because I'm not going
to treat it as an image, I'm going to treat
it as a single vector. Then I create my one
Dense layer with 10 outputs, compile it, grab
my batches and train my linear model.
So you can see, generally speaking, the best
way to train a model is to start by doing
one epoch with a pretty low learning rate.
So the default learning rate is 0.001, which
is a pretty good default.
You'll find nearly all of the time I just
accept the default learning rate and I do
a single epoch and that's enough to kind of
get it started. Once you've got it started,
you can set the learning rate really high.
So .1 is about as high as you ever want to
go. Do another epoch and that's going to move
super-fast, and gradually you reduce the learning
rate by an order of magnitude at a time. So
go to .01, do a few epochs, and basically
keep going like that until you start overfitting.
So I got down to the point where I had a 92.7%
accuracy on the training, 92.4% on the test
and it's like, Okay that's about as far as
I can go.
So that's a linear model. Not very interesting.
So the next thing to do would be to grab 1
extra dense layer in the middle, so 1 hidden
layer. This is what in the 80's and 90's,
people thought of as a neural network, one
hidden layer fully connected. And so that
still takes 5 seconds to train.
We're going to do the same thing. One epoch
with a low learning rate, then pop up the
learning rate for as long as we can, gradually
decrease it. And we get to 94% accuracy.
So you wouldn't expect a fully connected network
to do that well. So let's create a CNN. This
was actually the first architecture I tried.
And basically I thought, we know VGG works
pretty well, so how about I create an architecture
that looks like VGG but it's much simpler
because this is just 28x28.
Okay, well VGG generally has a couple of convolutional
layers of 3x3, and then a MaxPooling layer
and then a couple more with twice as many
fitlers. So I just tried that. This is kind
of like my inspired by VGG model.
I thought, Okay after 2 lots of MaxPooling
it will go from 28x28 to 14x14 to 7x7, that's
probably enough. So then I added my 2 Dense
layers.
So I didn't use any science here, just kind
of some intuition. And it actually worked
pretty well. After my learning rate of .1
I had an accuracy of 98.9%, a validation accuracy
of 99%. Then after a few layers of .01, I
had an accuracy of 99.75%. But look, my validation
accuracy is only 99.2%, so I'm overfitting.
This is the trick. Start by overfitting. Once
you know you're overfitting, you know you
have a model that is complex enough to handle
your data.
So at this point I was like, Okay, this is
a good architecture, it's capable of overfitting.
So let's now try to use the same architecture
and reduce overfitting but reduce the complexity
of the model no more than necessary.
Step 1 of my 5 step list was data augmentation.
So I added a bit of data augmentation and
then I used exactly the same model as I had
before. Trained it for a while, and I found
this time I could actually train it for even
longer (as you can see) and I started to get
some pretty good results here, 99.3, 99.34.
[Time: 1.55 minute mark]
So by the end you can see I'm massively overfitting
again. 99.6 training vs 99.1 test.
So data augmentation alone is not enough.
I said to you guys always use batchnorm anyway,
so then I add batchnorm. I use batchnorm on
every layer. Notice when you use batchnorm
on convolution layers, you have to add "axis=1".
I'm not going to tell you why. I want you
guys to read the documentation about batchnorm
and try and figure out why you need this.
Then we'll have a discussion about it on the
forum because it's a really interesting analysis.
If you really want to understand batchnorm,
understand why you need this here. If you
don't care about the details, that's fine.
Just know to type "axis=1" anytime you have
batchnorm.
This is like a pretty good quality modern
network. You can see I've got convolution
layers (they're 3x3), and then I have batchnorm
and then I have MaxPooling and then at the
end I have some Dense layers. So this is actually
a pretty decent looking model. Not surprisingly,
it does pretty well.
So I train it for a while at .1, I train it
for a while at .01, I train it for a while
at .001, and you can see I get up to 99.5%.
That's not bad.
But by the end, I'm starting to overfit. So
add a little bit of dropout.
Remember what I said to you guys, nowadays
the rule for dropout is to kind of gradually
increase it.
I only had time yesterday to just try adding
1 layer of dropout right at the end, but as
it happened, that seemed to be enough. When
I just added one layer of dropout in the previous
model, trained it for a while at .1, .01,
.001 and it's like, Oh great, my accuracy
and my validation accuracy are pretty similar.
And my validation accuracy is around 99.5
to 99.6 towards the end here. So I thought,
Okay, that sounds pretty good.
So at 99.5% or 99.6% accuracy on handwriting
recognition is pretty good, but there's one
more trick you can do which makes every model
better, it's called Ensembling.
Ensembling refers to building multiple versions
of your model and combining them together.
So what I did was I took all of the code from
that last section and put it into a single
function. So this is exactly the same model
I had before. And this is the exact steps
that I took to train it - my learning rate
of .1, .01, .001. And so at the end of this,
it returns a trained model.
And so then I said, Okay, 6 times fit a model
and return a list of the results. Models at
the end of this contain 6 trained models using
my preferred network. So then what I could
do was go through every one of those 6 models
and predict the output for everything in my
test set.
So now I have 10,000 test images by 10 outputs
by 6 models. So now I can take the average
across the 6 models. So now I'm basically
saying, here are 6 models. They've all been
trained in the same way, but from different
random starting points. And so the idea is
that they will be having errors in different
places.
So let's take the average of them and I get
an accuracy of 99.7%. How good is that? It's
very, very good. It's so good that if we go
to the academic list of the best MNIST results
of all time (and remember many of these were
specifically designed for handwriting recognition),
it comes here. So one afternoon's work gets
us in the list of the best results that are
found on this dataset.
As you can see, it's not rocket science. It's
all stuff you've learnt before, you've learnt
now. It's a process which is fairly repeatable
and can get you right up here in the state-of-the-art.
It was easier to do on NMIST because I only
had to wait a few seconds for each of my trainings
to finish. To get to this point on State Farm,
it's going to be harder. You're going to have
to think about how do you do it in the time
you have available, how do you do it in the
context of fine-tuning. Hopefully you can
see that you have all of the tools now at
your disposal to create literally a state-of-the-art
model.
[Time: 2.0 hour mark]
So I'm going to make all of these notebooks
available. You can play with them. You can
try to get a better result from Dogs and Cats.
As you can see, it's kind of an incomplete
thing that I've done here. I haven't found
the best data augmentation, I haven't found
the best dropout, I haven't trained it as
long as I probably need to, so there's some
work for you to do.
So here are your assignments for this week.
This is all review now. I suggest you go back
and actually read, there's quite a bit of
prose in every one of these notebooks. Hopefully
you can go back and read that prose. Some
of that prose that was a first a bit mysterious,
now it's going to make sense; you'll go, Okay
I see what it's saying.
And if you read somethign and it doesn't make
sense, ask on the forum. Or if you read something
and you want to check, Oh is this kind of
another way of saying this other thing?, ask
on the forum.
So these are all notebooks that we've looked
at already and you should definitely review.
Make sure you can replicate the steps shown
in the lesson notebooks we've seen so far
using the technique in How to Use the Provided
Notebooks.
If you haven't yet got into the top 50% of
Dogs vs Cats, hopefully you've now got the
tools to do so. If you get stuck at any point,
ask on the forum.
And then this is your big challenge, can you
get into the top 50% of State Farm. This is
tough.
The first step to doing well in a Kaggle competition
is to create a validation set that gives you
accurate answers. So create a validation set
and make sure that the validation set accuracy
is the same as when you submit to Kaggle.
If you don't, you don't have a good enough
validation set yet.
Creating a validation set for State Farm is
really your first challenge. It requires thinking
long and hard about the evaluation section
on their page, what that means. And then thinking
about which layers of the pre-trained network
should I be retraining?
I actually have read through the top 20 results
of the competition, it closed 3 months ago.
I actually think all of the top 20 result
methods are pretty hacky, they're pretty ugly.
I feel like there's a better way to do this
that is in our grasp.
I'm hoping that somebody is going to come
up with a top 20 result for State Farm that
is elegant. We'll see how we go. If not this
year, maybe next year, because nobody in Kaggle
came up with a really good way of tackling
this. They got some really good results, but
with some really convoluted methods.
As you go through and review, please any of
these techniques that you're not clear about,
these 5 pieces, please go and have a look
at this additioal information and see if that
helps.
Hope everything goes well and I will see you
next week.