Hi and welcome To Lesson [one] of this Deep Learning MOOC. Thanks for Joining Us I'm Jeremy Howard and I'm Rachel Thomas
We're The People who put This together you'll be Seeing my face in Front of the Camera Most of the Time?
You'll Be Hearing Rachel's Voice However
[I'll] be asking Questions that are Coming Through a, slack Channel asked by students in the In-Person Version of this Course
So we thought before We Started We Should Tell you a little bit About?
What to Expect and Maybe you get to know Us a [little] bit
My Background is Really in
Coding and Data I spent 10 Years of Management Consulting and 10 Years Running Startups
Throughout That [Time] I've Been using Data and Machine [Learning] to try to solve Problems
My Backgrounds A lot more Academic and Theoretical I have a Phd in Math and Then I worked as a quant
Later as A software [Engineer] and Data scientist [-] at Uber
[One] of the Most fun exciting Parts of my [life]
Was when [I] spent some Time Really Competing Heavily in Capital Competitions [I]?
Was Really Pleased to win some of Those Competitions and Get to the Top of the leaderboard and
I'm hoping to show you guys during this Course some of the techniques that I used to do that
I think the techniques that allowed When [Cackled] Competitions are The Same as the techniques that allow you to create
Great Results on your own Models in Solving your own Problems?
We also both love Teaching and so type Calculus 1 [&] 2
When I was in Graduate [School] and?
Then I later Left my job as a software Engineer to teach
Full-Stack Software Development Women at hack rate Academy for a year and a half I think that's Really cool Rachel
was a quant and then she Worked with Both the Data scientist and a source tech Engineer uber
But She realized that one of the highest Leverage Things you can do is to teach and it's great Fun - I
Feel the Same Way even When I was Running Startups I was Creating?
Course Content online for Example on the Left here is an AngularJS tutorial that I originally created from my colleagues at Kaggle
But I recorded it and put it online and it's Had over 200,000 views
Makes you Feel Really good to [know] that People are Learning
From Some of the Things That I found Really Helpful Myself
so this is a Quote from paul lockhart who, was A and
He was Actually working as a primary School math teacher got
His Phd in Math at Columbia and Became A math Professor at Brown and then Left to go back to teaching Primary School
And he's written A
Wonderful Asset Called A mathematicians will meant on everything that's Horrible About how Mathematics Is Taught in The United States Yeah I think that that
Essay has Been Really Influential to Both Rachel and I
Although Rachel Stuck With her Math Education for
Decades Longer Than I did We Both Definitely Felt like modern Mathematics education is not done well
Paul Lockhart Uses a Wonderful Analogy about Imagine if With Music
We didn't Allow Children To sing or play Instruments until they had spent
Years and Even Decades Studying Set Theory and Music Notation and Could transcribe Scales and Only then Once They
Were in Their 20s, We would let them create Music he Says that's Exactly what, we're Doing Is Mathematics but They?
Don't We Should Let People kind of
Play and Create and Build Patterns With It and Something [very] Similar happens with Deep Learning and how its Taught
In fact One of my heroes is a guy Called David Perkins who at
Harvard Has Created some Really
Interesting Research About effective Educational Techniques and he Is very Similar Analogy to lockhart that he [Talks] About
Baseball Imagine if the way you like Baseball
Was that You Never saw A game of Baseball?
But Instead you learned About how to SKetch your baseball and you [learnt] the physics [a] Parabola and you learn Every Aspect
of Baseball and Then After 20 Years of Study Should be Considered Good Enough to go and Actually Watch your first Game
[We] tend to think that This Is Ralph as A way that most mathematics Perhaps Particularly Including Deep Learning is Really Taught
so, we
Decided When, we set up a, research lab that Say I that the first Thing
We would do Would be to try and Fill this need and Particularly We Decided to Focus on Deep Learning because?
We both Think That Deep Learning is the?
Most exciting Technology that, We have ever Seen?
We think it's going to be more transformative Than Even Than the Internet and so the more People who Can Participate the Better
Entering has Called it the new Electricity so kind of to Say that it's going to have the Impact on society That Electricity has
so
Some of The Kinds of Problems we've Seen With Technical change like These and I just want to say we're Introducing that to tell you?
That This Course Is Taught in A very Different Style and so
We want to Kind of set your Expectations Ahead of Time and motivate why? It's so different how, We teach it Here?
And One is that a lot
[of] them Existing Deep Learning Materials are very Math Centric and even as a mathematician and someone who loves Math I found them to be
Pretty Unhelpful for
Actually Building and Creating Practical Applications in Fact Every Time I see Somebody Ask on A forum or on Hacker News Whatever
What do I [need] in Order to get Into Deep Learning a, whole Bunch of People Replied by Saying
Well First you need Five Years of Real Analysis and Vector Analysis and then you need to study Probability and Statistics
And bla bla bla bla bla and it Really Comes across to me [as] something Which is all About being exclusive Rather than
Inclusive so that's why, We have This Little?
Thing
Making Neural Nets and cool again it's kind of out Yeah I slogan yes [Ai] Slogan
We're all About not being exclusive but About making Things as Simple as [Possible] but Never About
Dumbing it Down
Right
Another Way that Kind of
Technical Education Fails Is what David Perkins and the Harvard Professor Jeremy Mentioned a moment Ago called Element itis
And that's that often Masked Us
[of] so much
It teaches Kind of each
separate Element and it's only at the end when you've learned all the Elements Needed that you Can put them Together and See the whole
Thing and That's Kind of what was going on in That Baseball Analogy and that happens in A lot
Of Deep Learning it's like you know
We need to teach you Probability Theory and We need to teach you Information Theory and Only Way Later
On we're Going to Let you put it together you can think of it as being depth first rather than
breadth-first. If you like so the traditional depth-first approach, means that you as a student have to trust that at
some point all these things are going to come together and turn into something that's genuinely useful. I
think with this breadth-first approach you Still have to trust this Different kind of trust which Is that it's okay [that]
When, We first Show you an End-To-end Process that you don't Deeply Understand Every Part but [that] you are able to actually
do Useful Things
From The very first Lesson and [that] as the Lessons go Along you're Going to get More and More in Depth Understanding
Of each Piece and Two ways that the Element Titus or the Depth-First?
Approach Fails Are One is Motivation A lot of Students Kind, of Give Up because they
Don't have the Motivation of Seeing how are These going to fit Together
And then Secondly it's Harder to get the like you, don't have the Contacts when, you're Learning all These discrete Elements and you
Can't Learn How They're Going to fit Into the Process until Later
Right and in Fact This goes together With the idea of using A code Centric
Approach Instead of A math Centric Approach with A code Centric Approach and Looking at the whole Game that Is an End-To-end
Machine Learning Process From The very start it means that you can do Experiments you can
[Actually] Run Experiments and See what Goes in and out of each Part of the System and Build Up that Intuition
And if This whole Game Analogy I'm intrigued to David Perkins has a book Called Making Learning
Holes Where he goes Into A lot more Detail About it I love That Book
So then not not only are We going to be Showing you?
End-To-end Processes From This very First Lesson but These Processes are Going to not going to Just end up with good enough results
Nearly all of the Deep Learning educational Materials I've Seen so far get you to a point Where
You Can Kind of get an okay, ish result now the whole Point of Deep Learning
Is that you can get State-Of-The-Art results and so in the very first Piece of Code, we're going to run
We're Going to run a piece of code Which gives you a State-Of-The-Art Result
We know something is A state of [the] [Art] result If It is Better than other Approaches That People have Tried
The Best way to know that is to try [Things] on a [Kaggle] Competition Having
Been The President and Chief scientist of [Kaggle] I saw again and again That Every [Kaggle]
Competition Beat All Previous Academic States State of the Art results so very often in This Course
We're Actually going to use [kaggle] benchmarks and See if We Can Beat Because
We know if We Can then that's truly A, well best?
So this is from Actually A very Good Book
It's the Young good Fellow [Yoshi] of ngo Deep Learning Book
But it's A very Good math Book which teaches you the math of Deep Learning and so in This Book when they Say?
Here is how We gain some Intuition in how to back Propagation Through Time Works this is how They Develop Intuition?
Rachel as a math Phd did you find this Helped your Intuition
will Have A very Different Approach to Intuition so this is a good book if you're Interested in Math and
TheoreMs in This Course, We're Really Going to be Focused on Code
[in] fact This is what [Rachel] and I put together When
We were Trying to explain Back Prop and Specifically Stochastic Gradient descent and the Use of Back Prop There, was We created a Spreadsheet?
And we Found each Time that We Taught our Students in The In-Person Course Through A?
Spreadsheet They Could See Every Single Piece of what was going on every single Intermediate result it [was] very
Easy for Them to Experiment With and so one of the unusual things, We do Is that you'll See That Nearly Every Major
Idea is presented at some Point using a spreadsheet, We present it in Many Different Ways but Spreadsheets?
Diagrams and Code Three of the key Ways that We present These ideas?
We believe This is The first Deep Learning Course in The World to implement A?
Convolutional Neural Network in an Excel Spreadsheet [and] [also] as you See from this Page not Just to [guess] The Gradient descent but A
Degrade RMSprop [Adam] and Even [Eve] Which just Came out A few Weeks ago
Or modern examples of
Accelerated Sgd Approaches
so I think everything you Really need to know about the Course Comes in This very first Piece of Code [that] you See
And This very First Piece of Code [that] you see you can see that there's a number of Things Going on?
The First Is that this Piece of Code Shows not Just how to complete a project but
How to get a State-Of-The-Art Result on a project this Particular Piece [of] Code Gives you
97% Accuracy in Terminating Cats Versus Dogs
As Recently as about Five Years Ago [see] State of the Art for this Particular Problem, was About [80%] Accuracy
It's also an Example of Showing why
Working With Code Is so interesting rather than Showing Math
What we're Showing here Is Some working Code and I'll give you an example of what that means you Can?
Do so the Code Environment that
We're Working in Is something called Jupiter Notebook and you'll be using This in Every Single Lesson Throughout the Course and
Enjoy the Notebook as you can See, we Provide you with?
[Prose] and Information About What's Going on and Redraw Pictures and at any [Point] in Time
You Can Take a look at, one of These results and you can
You Can Take a look at
One of These results and you Can Look to see what's going on Behind the Scenes [so] for example in this case
We're Running something Called
[Ggg] Predict and we're Getting back some Probabilities and you might Wonder
Well what's [VGG] That Predicts Actually Doing so at any Time you Can Take Anything and put Two Question Marks on The front and
Run that Piece of Code and it will actually Show you the
Full Documentation and Source Code of what You just ran Now in this case it's Actually running a Function that We wrote for you?
One of the other Different Things About this Course Is that we're Not [Just] Showing you how
Existing Libraries Work But Every Time, We Found that using somebody Else's library Takes more than four or five lines of Code?
We would Make Sure We Found a way to do it Easier so Generally Speaking?
We show you how to do Things in One line of Code and then you Can Look Behind the Scenes and See what the lines
of Code Are Actually Doing so for example in this Case
The Predict Method is Running some other Predict Method Called Model Dot Predict and
So then what I always Encourage [People] to do is to do some Experiments so what does Model dot Predict Actually, do
One Thing that you can do in Chip your Notebook at any Time is to press Shift Tab a couple of Times
When you Press Shift Tab first Time it Pops Up it tells you what
Parameters you need to Pass This Method and it, also tells you what the Method Actually Does
If
You Press it Three Times it then Gives you
Additional Information About What each of Those arguments Are and What they're Expecting and what it returns
So it's really, Nice That
Using This Method you Can find out Exactly what's going on Behind the Scenes [and] do some Experiments and
So then [if] Example you could find out okay?
Well what is the Shape what Is the Size and Shape of the Array [that] This Thing returns?
[What] are The first Four Elements the Classes that are in This
Object and so Forth and This is really the way to
Use This Style of Teaching
Effectively it's to have the Code in Front of you all the Time and in
Every Line Look and See what's being Cuffed in What's Coming out what Else Could?
We do with [that] and then even Look at the Documentation so VGG Model is Apparently a
[Keras] Model Dot sequential so if We Would Just Copy that Into
[Google]
Then, We Can click on the first item and Find out Exactly what's going on what Is being Used here what are the other Methods
That This Could Take and then, We Can try Calling some of These other Methods
and See what kind of Results We get
so Really what We're Trying to do Is in the two hours of each Lesson
We're Trying to give you enough Information to get you Started With your own
Experiments, We're Not Trying to teach you everything and we're Certainly not Assuming that the Lesson Can stand alone
And we'll Talk more About this in A moment but The Videos are Just a small part of the Course but the Ipython
Notebooks and The [Coder] Huge Resource and We'll Talk About some of the other Resources that, We have Available for you?
But the important Thing to realize With These six lines of Code
Is that you Can run this for Anything not Just A dog versus Cat but These first six lines of Code you learn
Well Actually as it Says here Work for any Image Recognition
[Task] With Any Number of Categories so if you can get This far [in] Today's Lesson
Then You fly to, do
One of the most important Types of Computer Vision Which is image Classification or any Number of Categories for any Type of images
As Rachel Said we've Actually run this Course Already?
Specifically what you're Going to be Seeing are The recorded Lessons from an Interesting Course
And we thought it'd be Helpful for you to see what some of our?
Students Said About That [Impacts] and Cost Because it might Help you, should be A more effective Learner
And I do want to say I'm again because this Course Is Taught in Such a Different Way that
It Takes some face Kind of that this new Technique and is Worth Trying and Kind of sticking With but you can See that
Almost all the students Said that this, was that the Homework assignments Were very Helpful or?
Extremely Helpful in Understanding the Material
and the class resources Which includes the Wiki the scripts that
We give you [our] Forums our Slack Channel?
We're very Helpful or extremely Helpful and I want to [moshe] [Andrey] and We wanted to Mention that because
Rachel and I [are] Both being Kind of Coursera Addicts in the Past and Udacity [Addicts] and
Generally Speaking, We all often Watch a video at, [One-And-A-Half] [Speed] or two Speed and Just dip Through them
This Is not Designed to be Possible to do that this Way this is designed that you need to use the Homework
Assignments and The Class Resources so as you can [See] from the people who Have Already Been Through this Class
They Are Actually Finding These are Really Important Parts of the Overall Course
If each Video is giving you you're Kind of Seeing an end to end Process of
Solving A real Problem with Deep Learning and that means that There's not Though A separate Video on
Reddit This is Everything you need [to] know About AWs in your environment and This is everything you need to know about
This Piece of Code but Rather You're Kind of Seeing The end end Process but You'll See it again and again
Throughout The Lessons Now it's [okay] if you're Coming, Into this Course With either A very large
Amount Or A very Small Amount of Data science Background
Everybody in The [In-Person] Course Simply Had to have had at least a year [of] Coding [Experience]
[Even] With [A] very wide Variety in Background
[Nearly] Everybody Said They Found the Pace About right for Them and the Reason [for] that I think Is that we really?
Give People the Ability to pick up as much as little as they want
Through The Forums if You want to dig very very Deep Into
Advanced Topics you can Or if Absolutely everything is new to you
[Then] [That's] Fine Too there'll Be More than enough to do Just to get Through the basic Parts of your assignments and
Of Course on the Forums Would be very Happy to help you with all [of] your Questions There and if You are more Advanced
We really Appreciate your Help in Adding new Material to the Wiki answering others Questions on the Forums?
People Started Their Own Threads on the Forums Around Kind of Outside Related topics that they, were interested in
There are A Lot of Different Ways to be involved [so]
[Here's] A couple of Quotes We got from People after they completed the in Percent Clause and
This Is One That
We heard Again [and] Again so for example This Person Says I personally Fell Into the Habit of Watching the lectures too much and
Googling Definitions and Concepts and so Forth Too much Without Running the Code
At first I thought that I should Read the Code Quickly and then Spend Time Researching the Theory Behind it
in Retrospect I should have spent the Majority of my Time on the actual Code in the Notebooks Instead in Terms of Running It and
Seeing what goes Into It and Seeing what Comes out of it and [Actually] I know You've Seen similar things in your past
Teaching Error That I'Ve Seen This that in Teaching Called [Back] Software development and Students and I also know that I've Been Guilty of
It Myself
Sometimes
And that was that Students Would Sometimes Kind of Rather Than start Their Project they Would Keep Doing more and more Research
Reading More and More Tutorials and Feeling Like There's More and More They need to learn before They Can Start Coding
and two problems With that are
One and i mean [you] want to [have] some Background before you Begin but There's a point Where you [just] need to start Coding
Because you Can't know Exactly what you're Going to need until you start
Coding and Building and Seeing What Errors you get and what things you don't know how to do
and then Secondly the Test of Whether you understand something is whether you Can build with It [and]
So kind of Reading Tutorials it's very Possible to think, "Oh, I understand all this" -- but it's not Till you're writing Code Yourself
Kind of Seeing what your error rates Are and What
what's Working and what's not that you Know Whether or not to Really Understand Something
yeah so when I saw Students at the study Sessions during the week at
Usf I would Keep Going and the Same Thing again and again Just don't stop and Wait Till you Feel Ready to Code
Start Coding Now
And it's Through [that] Coding
[Experience] that you're Actually going to Figure out what you don't know and what you do know and Joey has developed the
Intuition By Running Lots of Experiments
[This] is Another Interesting Quote
From Somebody Talking About
This Learning Style He Said it's Been very Interesting Learning from Somebody who IS an Entrepreneur that
We make A very No-Nonsense Approach to getting Things Done very Hands-on very Smart and driven
Your usual Career Instructor is Quite the Opposite so it's Been Refreshing and Even Somewhat Shocking
This is Possibly understating things A bit it can be that We heard from quite A few People [at] the start it was
Somewhat Shocking To find so Many Things Taught so Quickly and it Kind of
Can Seem like Such a high level but of Course by the end of the seven Weeks and Assuming that each Time you're Putting 10
Hours Into Those Weeks you've Actually got
Many Many Full End-To-end Processes under your belt so by the end of it you're Actually going to Develop A very Deep and complete Understanding
Yeah I know after the first Lesson I heard a number of Students Kind of Say Things like
Oh I i didn't really get the Details from that Lesson and you know I feel like I need to Spend all [this] Time Understand
Studying The Details
and We hadn't Talked The Details in The first Lesson and
The idea Is that kind of We went More and More in Depth each Time
You're Seeing This End-To-end
Process and Then Kind of as Time Goes on digging Into it more but even After The first Lesson you Can apply it you can
Actually Create
World-Class Image Recognition [Models] and so you can go back to your Organization
and start Trying [Things] This is something Else We encourage People to do try things With your Own Data and your own Problems from the
very first Lesson
So it's been A
Interesting Experience in Every Way even the way
We built This Course is unusual?
for Example I actually wrote Most of the material real While Traveling from the Northern Tip to the southern Tip of
Japan I
Coded and wrote in Every possible place Six [imagined]
[and] this was a really an Experiment for me Because I studied Human Learning Theory A lot and I know that it is very
Human Creativity Is meant to be Better when you have a wider Variety of Contexts
Interestingly I Actually Found I was more Productive in That Month [Than] I feel I ever Have Been [Before] and You'll See Actually in the
Material That you learn We Show a lot of?
New Techniques Or Different techniques or Different Ways of Thinking about things and I think This kind of
Different Way of Building the Course Perhaps, was Really Helpful and Coming up with this kind of more creative Approach
so not everybody in the Course
In the In-Person Course were able [to] put in the at least eight Hours A, week but the vast Majority were
And Those who Didn't
Still Completed The Course They Just Found They Didn't Necessarily pick everything up the way that they hoped
They Would but of Course the nice Thing is you Can, always come back to it later [so]
[our] suggestion Would be now that it's a mooc now that you don't have to do it every Single Week
Ideally you will put in the ten Hours A week did you, want to talk about those [turn] out a little bit Rachel yeah
We wanted To give You some Suggestions on how how to use that Time?
and so the Videos are between Two and Two and a half Hours Long
and so
With Those Videos
You May find it Helpful as you
Review Them to use These notes A service Is coming from our Wiki Wiki say I?
There's A Page for each Lesson that has
Notes
Kind of About the Lesson it, also has links to other other Resources that May be useful to you
These Notes Are Pretty complete They're not [Designed] to be Read Entirely Independently from the Video Lesson
But They Are something Which you can
Read on your way to Work Maybe when you don't have
It's not Convenient to Actually Watch the Lesson
So I was going to Say
We're Expecting that you'll Watch the Lessons more Than Once
You know so the first Time Through [you're] Kind of Watching to get
Maybe A lot of the high Level Ideas then you'll Probably want to Read the Wiki
Try out The Notebooks and then then go back and Watch the Lesson again and
Kind of Maybe to get more Details yeah I don't think Any of our Students in the In-Person Course Just Watch the Lessons Once
They saw Them live of Course but then, we, also they?
Also had the recording from the next day and I think Everybody has spoken to Watch them at least Twice and
Then of Course The other Thing you've got [is] the notebooks the Notebooks as you
See, has Quite A lot of Pros in Them as well
[They've] Got Quite A Lot [of] Additional Detail that, We don't Necessarily get Into in the Video Lesson but Most Importantly as
We described They Give you an Environment in Which you Can Experiment?
in
Fact not only do We suggest that you Experiment We have A very Specific suggestion about how to use These Notebooks?
yeah so we recommend that you Read Through the Notebook and then and This is after you've Watched the Video
At least Once and Everything Makes sense [put] it Aside and Try Creating A
New a new Notebook where you go Through [that] Process Yourself [and] so this is from scratch right This is like Creating your Own
Notebook to Test that you Can Actually Build it Yourself [yeah]
We do not want you to just hit Shift enter Shift Center and run Through the Existing Notebook Because again the test of Whether
Whether you know something is Can you Can you build and Code With it Yourself
So if You get Stuck you can
Always Then go back in [Or] third of the Class Notebook and then rather Than Copying and Pasting it
Make Sure you do Understand what it's Saying Maybe Look up some
Documentation About That Concept and Then put That Notebook Aside and See if you Can now do it Yourself so in A sense you're
Plagiarizing A lot from the Notebook but you're plagiarizing in A good way you know
you're plagiarizing not by Copying and Pasting but by plagiarizing the Concepts and Making sure that you Can recreate them Yourself
And then if You have that have Questions Please ask Them and the Forums are The first place you Should go to
And first search to See if Someone's Already Asked your Question as
We said [Earlier] There's separate Thread for each Lesson that are Already [a.m.]
Tons of Helpful Questions and Answers From the Students That Took our In-Person Course in Fact There's a great Quote Which
We talked [About] in One of the Lessons From the head of Google Brain who Says that the rule of Google Brain Is that if
You have a problem you first of all try to Fix it Yourself for half an Hour
[and] if After Half an Hour you Can't Fix it Yourself you then have to ask Somebody so that ensures that you
Always Give it A go Yourself and Hopefully Learn from the Experience but you
Never waste too much Time on [something] Which somebody Else Can Help you with yes This created Ways
So if Rachel Said the Forums are Really Helpful Resource and when you go to the Forums you'll find that There's A lot of Existing
Discussions There's A separate Discussion for Every Lesson for Example and each of Those
Discussions You'll See That There's a summary of the Existing Discussion at the start so you
May find that what you need Is
Already in The Question and answers There
If it's not of Course
Feel free to Add your Question and you'll Generally Found it's responded to Within a small Number of Hours
Maybe by Rachel or I or maybe by, one at the other Students
The Other Thing you May find helpful Is that each Lesson has a timeline on the Wiki and Those Hyperlinks are Actually
Hyperlinks Directly to the Part of the Video Which Discusses That Topic so if you're Trying to remember how
Momentum Works you Can Just Click on that Link and you'll Jump straight to me Telling you about Momentum
As Rachel Said There's, also a number of resources Available to Help you
So this Is Taken from the front Page of our Wiki there's a whole Section of tools With links Where you Can Learn About
Learn more About each of the pieces that We use in The development Environment?
[and] so our goal here [Is] not to be a single source of Truth if Somebody Else has Already done A great Job of Teaching
One of These tools we'll leave it to them so?
We don't attempt to give you a great Bosch Reference Or a great Umpire Reference Because
People Have Already Done that yeah so if you want to learn more About one of These things
Jump on to the Wiki Click Through Here and You'll find some curated resources that We think are Really Helpful?
so this Lesson
You're Going to Cover a lot
Of Stuff But These are the four things to Keep in mind
By the end of the Lesson [you] want to Make sure that you Can create an Aws Instance
That you Can connect To [it] with
Ssh so you Can run a Cupidon Notebook Image and you Can run Those That State-Of-The-Art Custom Model Code that we showed you Earlier?
So first Three things
You're Going to be Doing every single Project in Every Single Lesson so you're going to want to be Really Comfortable at doing that [and]
For Those of You who doesn't haven't done That before it might Take you a little while to get the Hang of it and Maybe
A few
Unsuccessful Attempts First
So this first Lesson is unusual in that it's A lot more About kind of getting your development environment set Up and
Not as much About People Learning
so indeed if You've got a Background in
Python and AWs and Os and Linux you
May find This Lesson on the Easy Site in Which case you Can zip Through it Pretty fast if you
Don't have a background in These tools Today's Class May Seem Really Overwhelming and [We] don't don't want you to be Discouraged by
That Because This Is very Different from the future Lessons but it's Necessary to get your environment Set up so that you can be Coding
Throughout The Course Yeah i mean the folks who Didn't Have That Background in the In-Person [Course] Once They
Actually Got Through This and often it, was A lot of Work and it
Was pretty Tough at The end They Finally Got The point and They Could Say okay I've Set up a gpu Instance in the Cloud
I've Set up my development
Environment and I Have trained from Scratch a model That Can Recognize Dogs from Cats and it was very very
Exciting so if This is hard Work for you
Just know that when You get Through the other end of it [it's] going to be Really exciting
so I ask That Everyone who is trying to Decide if This Courses for them and
Try at Least The first Few Lessons Since The first Lesson is so much about Setup
Yeah These Lessons [Become]
Obviously We build More and more on the techniques we've learned and so?
We're Going to be using this Infrastructure in Every Lesson by the time, We get to Lesson [seven]
We're Going to be Looking at some pretty Sophisticated and Custom Neural Network Architectures, we're Going to cover Every Different type of
Sgd Optimization, We're Going to be Covering Convolutional Neural Networks and recurrent Neural Networks [too] be A lot of exciting stuff
and yeah, We really Look Forward to Seeing [you] on the Forums [and]
Good luck With Learning About tech Learning